<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .45 Auto Rim, also known as 11.5x23mmR, is a rimmed cartridge specifically designed to be fired in revolvers originally chambered for the .45 ACP cartridge.
The Peters Cartridge Company developed the cartridge in 1920 for use in the M1917 revolver, large numbers of which had become available as surplus following the end of World War I.
Two issues related to the use of .45 ACP ammunition in the M1917 revolver led to the development of the .45 Auto Rim. The M1917 had previously been used with half-moon clips that held three rounds of .45 ACP, a rimless cartridge. But if half-moon or moon clips are not used when firing a rimless cartridge in a revolver, the spent cases must be ejected by hand—either by shaking the revolver and its swing-out cylinder or by poking the cases with a rod or field-expedient tool, like a pencil—as the revolver's extractor cannot grab them. The second issue concerned headspace. In revolver cylinders not engineered to allow .45 ACP to headspace properly, as in early production Colt M1917s, the cartridges could slip forward, stopping them from firing. Adding a rim to the .45 ACP cartridge solved both these issues.
Loads offered were similar to the standard military loads for the .45ACP, but with fully lead bullets rather than the full metal jacket bullets used for .45ACP. This was done to reduce barrel wear in the shallow rifled revolvers in which it was to be used.
The round is currently still in production by Corbon in their DPX and Performance Match lines of ammunition and is also manufactured by Georgia Arms and Buffalo Bore Ammunition.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.45_Auto_Rim)
</EN>
<ES>El .45 Auto Rim o 11,43 x 23 R es un cartucho con pestaña específicamente diseñado para dispararse desde revólveres que originalmente empleaban el cartucho .45 ACP.
La Peters Cartridge Company desarrolló este cartucho en 1920 para emplearlo en el revólver M1917, que estaba disponible en grandes cantidades como armamento sobrante después de la Primera Guerra Mundial.​
Anteriormente, el M1917 había sido empleado con peines semicirculares que sostenían tres cartuchos .45 ACP sin pestaña.​ Si los peines semicirculares o circulares no son empleados con un cartucho sin pestaña en un revólver, deben ser eyectados manualmente con una baqueta o una herramienta improvisada, como un lápiz. En los revólveres cuyos tambores no fueron diseñados para que el cartucho .45 ACP se inserte adecuadamente, como los primeros Colt M1917 de serie, los cartuchos podían deslizarse hacia adelante y el percutor no podía golpear su cápsula fulminante. La adición de la pestaña resolvió ambos problemas.​
El .45 Auto Rim tenía cargas propulsoras similares a las cargas propulsoras militares estándar del .45 ACP, pero montaba balas de plomo macizo en lugar de las balas encamisadas empleadas por el .45 ACP. Esto era para reducir el desgaste del ánima ligeramente estriada de los revólveres que lo dispararían. El casquillo del .45 Auto Rim es más fuerte que el casquillo del .45 ACP y tiene una capacidad ligeramente mayor, permitiendo incrementar su desempeño.​ Puede tener un desempeño balístico similar al de los antiguos cartuchos de revólver con cargas propulsoras estándar de mayor tamaño, como el .45 Colt.​
El cartucho todavía es producido por la Cor-Bon/Glaser en sus líneas de cartuchos DPX​ y Performance Match,​ así como también por la Georgia Arms.​


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.45_Auto_Rim)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>