<loc>

	<DE>N/A</DE>
	<EN>
The .45 Winchester Magnum is a .45 caliber rimless cartridge intended for use in semi-automatic pistols. The cartridge is externally a lengthened .45 ACP with a thicker web to withstand higher operating pressures. The 45 Win Mag is nearly identical in dimensions and loading to the .45 NAACO developed by the North American Arms Corporation for their Brigadier pistol, developed to supply to the Canadian Army after World War II. The army ultimately did not adopt the pistol and its non-NATO standard ammunition.
The cartridge has been primarily used by small game hunters and metallic silhouette shooters.
Although the .45 Winchester Magnum may be based on the .45 ACP and have the same Rim and Base dimensions, the .45 Winchester Magnum has no parent case. The .45 Winchester Magnum case is redrawn with thicker walls and longer case. The thicker wall dimensions of the .45 Winchester Magnum are designed to accommodate a higher internal pressure (40,000 cup) than that of the .45 ACP (18,000 cup [21,000psi or 140MPa]).
The .45 Winchester Magnum had been on the drawing board for two years before its introduction, in 1979, by Winchester. The cartridge did not gain much popularity due to the intermittent availability of the Wildey and LAR Grizzly pistols. The cartridge was chambered in the Thompson-Center Contender single shot pistols. The cartridge was also chambered for the Freedom Arms Model 83 single-action revolver via an available optional cylinder.
The .45 Winchester Magnum gained a following among IHMSA competitors as it provided the power and performance necessary to knock down targets at an extended range. The cartridge has been used by handgun hunters and is among the few semi-automatic pistol (as opposed to revolver) cartridges which have been adopted for this sport.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.45_Winchester_Magnum)
	</EN>
	<ES>
El .45 Winchester Magnum es un cartucho para pistola.
Fue diseñado por la Winchester expresamente para la pistola semiautomática Wildey Magnum. Debido a los problemas de producción de esta pistola, el calibre no está muy extendido y pocas armas lo han adoptado, a pesar de la buena acogida inicial entre los usuarios.
Se trata de un calibre de capacidad similar al famoso .44 Magnum, para uso en pistolas semiautomáticas en lugar de revólveres. Por lo tanto, su potencia y retroceso son adecuados para el tiro deportivo sobre silueta metálica o la caza mayor con arma corta, pero no la defensa personal, por resultar inmanejable para la mayoría de personas en fuego rápido.
Con una bala de 16,2 gramos, desarrolla 425 m/s y 1050 joules.


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.45_Winchester_Magnum)
	</ES>
	<FR>
Cette page est une très courte ébauche oubliée.
À l'instar du célèbre « Une pomme est un fruit » qui a marqué l'histoire de Wikipédia, n'hésitez pas à la développer (comment ?) Vous pouvez également enrichir les pages proposées dans la rubrique « Pommes à croquer » du bistro du jour.
Cet article est une ébauche concernant les armes.
Vous pouvez partager vos connaissances en l’améliorant (comment ?) selon les recommandations des projets correspondants.
Le .45 Winchester Magnum, ou simplement .45 Magnum, est un calibre de cartouche essentiellement employé pour les pistolets semi-automatiques.


(https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.45_Magnum)
	</FR>
	<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>