<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .500/450 Magnum Nitro Express is a large bore centerfire rifle cartridge developed by Holland &amp; Holland.
The .500/450 Nitro Express is a rimmed bottlenecked cartridge designed for use in single-shot and double rifles. It is based on the old black-powder .500/450 Magnum Black Powder Express. It fires a .458-inch (11.6 mm) 480-grain (31 g) projectile at over 2,175 feet per second (663 m/s).
In response to initial case extraction problems with John Rigby &amp; Company's revolutionary .450 Nitro Express, both Eley Brothers and Holland &amp; Holland looked to develop alternatives that would match that excellent cartridge in performance.  Whilst Eley developed the completely new, mammoth .450 No 2 Nitro Express, Holland &amp; Holland followed Rigby's example and loaded the old black powder .500/450 Magnum Black Powder Express with cordite, creating the .500/450 Nitro Express. The larger case capacity allowed the same ballistics at reduced chamber pressures to the .450 Nitro Express.
500/450 Magnum Nitro Express was introduced by Holland &amp; Holland for their single shot and double rifles during the late 1890s. 
By the time the .500/450 Nitro Express appeared, the early issues with the .450 Nitro Express had been resolved, and it quickly became the most popular and widely used Elephant hunting round, leaving the .500/450 Nitro Express behind in popularity. In 1907, the .500/450 Nitro Express's fortunes were further eroded by the British Army's ban of .450 caliber ammunition into India and the Sudan. In response to this ban, Holland &amp; Holland developed their .500/465 Nitro Express. By the time the ban was lifted, Mauser's Gewehr 98 bolt actioned rifles offered cheaper alternatives to the expensive double rifles required by the Nitro Express cartridges.
Ballistically the .500/450 Nitro Express is almost identical to the .450 Nitro Express and is considered a good large-bore round, suitable for all dangerous game.
One prominent user of the .500/450 Nitro Express was Theodore Roosevelt who carried a Holland &amp; Holland double rifle in this calibre, along with a .405 Winchester and a .30-03 during the 1909-1910 Smithsonian–Roosevelt African Expedition.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.500/450_Nitro_Express)
</EN>
<ES>
El .500/450 Magnum Nitro Express es un cartucho de gran calibre desarrollado por Holland &amp; Holland, que proviene de un cartucho de pólvora negra diseñado en 1873.​
El .500/450 Nitro Express es un cartucho con un casquillo en forma de botella y un anillo en la base, propio de la munición usada en rifles dobles y de un solo tiro. Su diseño parte del casquillo del .500/450 Magnum Black Powder Express, y dispara proyectiles de 0.458 pulgadas (11.6 mm ) y 480 granos (31 g) a más de 2175 pies por segundo (663 m/s).
En respuesta a problemas de extracción reportados por el .450 Nitro Express, desarrollado por John Rigby &amp; Co., tanto Eley Brothers como Holland &amp; Holland empezaron a trabajar en una alternativa más fiable que pudiera igualar su rendimiento.​ Eley Desarrolló un cartucho completamente nuevo; el .450 No.2 Nitro Express, mientras que Holland &amp; Holland siguió el ejemplo de Rigby, y cargó el .500/450 Magnum Black Powder Express con cordita, creando así el .500/450 Nitro Express. La capacidad del casquillo le permitió obtener la misma balística pero reduciendo las presiones generadas en la recámara del .450 Nitro Express.​
Para cuando el .500/450 Nitro Express fue introducido al mercado, los problemas de extracción del .450 Nitro Express de Rigby ya habían sido resueltos, volviéndose rápidamente el cartucho más popular para cazar elefantes y relegando al .500/450 Nitro Express a una posición inferior.​ En 1907, el .500/450 Nitro Express perdió incluso más popularidad cuando el ejército británico prohibió la importación de munición calibre .450 en sus colonias de India y el Sudán. En respuesta a esta prohibición, Holland &amp; de Holland desarrolló su .500/465 Nitro Express. Cuando se levantó la prohibición, aparecieron alternativas más económicas a raíz de la introducción del Mauser 98 que usaba cartuchos distintos a los Nitro Express.
El .500/450 Nitro Express es balísticamente casi idéntico al .450 Nitro Express y está considerado un buen cartucho para la caza de todo tipo de animales peligrosos.
Un prominente entusiasta del .500/450 Nitro Express fue el presidente de los Estados Unidos, Theodore Roosevelt, quien llevó un rifle doble Holland &amp; Holland, junto con un .405 Winchester y un .30-03 durante la 1909-1910 Expedición africana Smithsonian-Roosevelt.​


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.500/450_Nitro_Express)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>