<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .500 Jeffery is a big-game rifle cartridge that first appeared around 1920, and was originally introduced by the August Schuler Company, a German firm, under the European designation "12.7×70mm Schuler" or ".500 Schuler". When offered by the famed British outfitter W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co, it was renamed the .500 Jeffery so as to be more palatable to British hunters and sportsmen following World War One.
The .500 Jeffery was introduced to bring firepower comparable to the .505 Gibbs into a standard-sized 1898 Mauser action as used with the 8x57mm and 7x57mm cartridges. The Gibbs and .416 Rigby cartridges required oversized magnum Mauser actions. To shoehorn a large round into the 98 action required a rebated rim.  When introduced, the .500 Jeffery was technically rated as the most powerful rifle cartridge although in reality not quite up to .505 Gibbs' performance. The .505 Gibbs, with greater capacity, can be loaded far in excess of the .500 Jeffery today.
Like the .505 Gibbs, the .500 Jeffery is enjoying somewhat of a renaissance among American shooters and African big game hunters in the early 21st century, almost 100 years after its introduction. As of 2009, Norma, Kynoch, Mauser, Corbon, and Westley Richards were offering loaded ammunition in .500 Jeffery with ammunition costing $150 for a box of 20 or more.
There have been a few rifles chambered in the .500 Jeffery including Jeffery, Heym, CZ-USA, and a few single shots including the Ruger No. 1, and the Butch Searcy &amp; Co.
Mauser offers its Model 98 magnum in the caliber. Its "elephant" model is offered in .500 Jeffery exclusively. In 2011, Sako began offering the caliber in its Model 85 "safari" rifle using a new XL size action, and since 2014 the XL action has been available in the more affordable Model 85 brown bear rifle. Blaser also offers rifles chambered in the caliber. Many of the modern rifles have feeding issues due to the rebated rim. The original Jeffery uses a single-column two-shot magazine to get around the potential reliability problems resulting from a rebated rim.
The .500 Jeffery has had a few issues since its introduction. It has a rather short neck length that can make it difficult to seat bullets with a relatively high sectional density. Also it has a small shoulder. This is not usually an issue but as the .500 Jeffery also has a rebated rim it makes it rather difficult to extract in extreme conditions.
When the .500 Jeffery was first introduced it was loaded to a velocity of 2,350 feet per second (720 m/s) topped off with a 535-grain bullet generating 6,560 ft⋅lbf (8,890 J) of muzzle energy, which made it a pretty good hunting caliber for thick-skinned dangerous game. Since then, reloading capabilities have advanced to be able to launch heavier bullets at higher velocities. Now, with modern reloads, the .500 Jeffery can launch a 600-grain bullet at a muzzle velocity ranging from 2,450 to 2,500 ft/s (750 to 760 m/s), generating 7,995 ft⋅lbf (10,840 J) to 8,100 ft⋅lbf (11,000 J) Newer reloads made the .500 Jeffery the most powerful production cartridge in the world until the introduction of the .460 Weatherby Magnum. With reloads the .460 Weatherby can reach levels of power of about 8,300 ft⋅lbf (11,300 J) of muzzle energy. Also the .600 Nitro Express exceeds the .500 Jeffery in muzzle energy, with 120 grains of cordite.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.500_Jeffery)
</EN>
<ES>

El .500 Jeffery es un cartucho de rifle de animales peligrosos  introducido alrededor de 1920 por August Schuler Company, una empresa alemana, bajo la designación Europea "12.7×70mm Schuler" o ".500 Schuler", y que fue comercialmente rebautizado .500 Jeffery, por la afamada armería británica W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co,  para generar más interés entre los cazadores Ingleses después de la Primera Guerra Mundial.​
El .500 Jeffery fue introducido para generar una energía comparable al .505 Gibbs en un cajón de mecanismo Mauser acción 98, de longitud similar al usado con el 8x57mm y el 7x57mm, mientras que tanto el .505 Gibbs como el .416 Rigby requieren de un cajón de mecanismo de magnum largo. 
Cuándo fue introducido, el .500 Jeffery se valoró técnicamente como el cartucho más potente a pesar de que en realidad no igualaba la performance del .505 Gibbs, que con mayor capacidad de carga puede superar hoy en día al Jeffery. No que  importa la presa, ambos cartuchos ofrecen suficiente energía para abatir a los animales más grandes del mundo desde su introducción.
Al igual que el .505 Gibbs, el .500 Jeffery está experimentando un renacimiento casi 100 años después de su introducción.​  Actualmente Norma, Kynoch, Mauser, Corbon, y Westley Richards comercializan munición cargada en .500 Jeffery.
Existen algunos cuantos rifles deportivos modernos que son recamarados en .500 Jeffery, incluyendo Jeffery, Heym, CZ-EE.UU., y algunos monotiros como el Ruger No. 1, el Butch Searcy &amp; Co. Mauser Ofrece su Modelo 98 magnum en .500 Jeffery también. Su "modelo" de Elefante está ofrecido en 500 Jeffery exclusivamente. En 2011, Sako empezó ofrecerlo en su Modelo 85 Safari Rifle, que utiliza la nueva acción XL, y desde eL 2014 la acción XL también está disponible en su modelo 85 Brown Bear. Blaser también ofrece rifles recamarados en .500 Jeffery. 
Cuándo el 500 Jeffery fue introducido, estuvo cargado para generar una velocidad de 2,350 pies por segundo (720 m/s) con fuera con una bala de 535 granos que genera 6,560 lb.pie (8,890 J) de energía, haciéndolo adecuado para cazar animales duros.
Actualmente, con pólvoras modernas, el .500 Jeffery puede lanzar una bala de 600 granos a una velocidad de salida que varía entre 2,450 y 2,500 pies/segundo (750 a 760 m/s), generando 7,995  (10,840 ) a 8,100 libras (11,000 J). Con las nuevas cargas el .500 Jeffery se posicionó como el más poderoso cartucho de producción en el mundo hasta la introducción del .460 Weatherby Magnum, que puede lograr niveles de energía de aproximadamente 8,300 lbs.pie (11,300 J). También el .600 Nitro Expresa supera al 500 Jeffery con un cargas de 120 granos de cordita. Sin duda el 500 Jeffery sigue siendo respetado en todo el mundo.


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.500_Jeffery)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>