<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .505 Gibbs cartridge was designed by George Gibbs in 1911. The cartridge was originally known as the .505 Rimless Nitro Express. The C.I.P. refers to the cartridge as the 505 Mag. Gibbs in their publications. It is a .50 caliber (12.8 mm) rimless bottlenecked cartridge intended for magazine-fed rifles.
The .505 Gibbs has a case capacity of 178 grains (11.5 g) of water. This cartridge was originally loaded with 90-grain (5.8 g) of cordite and 525-grain (34.0 g) bullet at 2,300 ft/s (700 m/s) for 6,166 ft⋅lbf (8,360 J) of kinetic energy. While the .505 Gibbs has a greater case capacity than most modern cartridges, it is loaded to lower pressures. The C.I.P. recommends a pressure of 2,700 bar (39,000 psi) for the cartridge. As .505 Gibbs was intended for hunting dangerous game in tropical environments, and due to the temperature sensitivity of cordite, the lower pressures provide a greater safety and reliability margin.
The .505 Gibbs has a unique bullet diameter of .505 in (12.8 mm) while most other .50 caliber bullets have diameters of .510 in (13.0 mm). Barnes Bullets and Woodleigh Bullets are a few of the bullet manufacturers who produce component bullets for reloading in this caliber. Woodleigh Bullets does not recommend impact velocities of over 2,200 ft/s (670 m/s) for their .505 caliber 600 gr weldcore bullets.
George Gibbs Ltd. (England) continues to manufacture .505 Gibbs rifles; other premium dangerous game rifle makers, such as Hartmann &amp; Weiss  and Westley Richards build expensive and reliable .505 Gibbs rifles on Mauser 98 actions.
Ceska Zbrojovka (CZ) currently manufactures the Safari Classics rifle for this cartridge. Doumoulin Herstal SA of Belgium offers the cartridge in their White Hunter model.
As of 2019, Federal, Kynoch, Norma, and Swift are offering factory loaded ammunition in .505 Gibbs. Bullets for reloading are available from Barnes, Cutting Edge Bullets, North Fork Bullets, and Woodleigh Bullets.
The .505 Gibbs is one of the most voluminous cases designed. The large volume was required as the cartridge was designed to burn cordite as its propellant. The C.I.P. has published specifications for the cartridge.
The C.I.P. recommends that commencement of rifling begin at 8.97 mm (0.353 in). Bore diameter is given as 12.55 mm (0.494 in) and groove diameter is 12.80 mm (0.504 in). The C.I.P. recommends a five groove barrel contour with each groove having an arc length of 5.33 mm (0.210 in) and a twist rate of one revolution in 406 mm (16.0 in). The recommended pressure for the .505 Gibbs is 2,700 bar (39,000 psi).
The .505 Gibbs is a niche cartridge designed for hunting heavy, thick-skinned dangerous game animals, such as cape buffalo, elephant, and rhino.
The cartridge's claim to fame was its use by the fictional character, Robert Wilson, the hunter of Ernest Hemingway's short story "The Short Happy Life of Francis Macomber".



(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.505_Gibbs)
</EN>
<ES>
El .505 Gibbs fue diseñado por George Gibbs en 1911. El cartucho era originalmente conocido como el .505 Rimless Nitro Express. El C.I.P. Refiere al cartucho como el 505 Mag. Gibbs en sus publicaciones. Es un calibre .50 (12.8 mm) diseñado para funcionar en fusile de cerrojo.
El casquillo del .505 Gibbs tiene una capacidad de 178 granos (11.5 g) de agua.​ Este cartucho era originalmente cargado con 90 granos (5.8 g) de cordita y una bala de 525 granos (34.0 g) que era disparada a 2,300 p/s (700 m/s), generando una energía de 6,166 libras.pie (8,360 J) de energía.​ Si bien tiene mayor capacidad de carga que otros cartuchos más modernos, este opera a presiones relativamente bajas .​ El C.I.P. Recomienda una presión de 2,700 Bar (39,000 psi) para el cartucho.​ Debido a que el .505 Gibbs estuvo diseñadoo para cazar animales peligrosos en un entorno tropical y debido a la sensibilidad de la cordita a la temperatura, las presiones más bajas proporcionaron mayor seguridad más  margen de fiabilidad.​
George Gibbs Ltd. (Inglaterra) continúa fabricando rifles en .505 Gibbs; otro reconocido fabricante de rifles africanos, como Hartmann &amp; Weiss  y Westley Richards también fabrican rifles .505 Gibbs en mecanismos Mauser 98.
Ceska Zbrojovka (CZ) Actualmente fabrica un rifle de cerrojo en este calibre .​ Doumoulin Herstal SA De Bélgica ofrece el cartucho en su modelo de Cazador Blanco.​
Para el 2019, Federal, Kynoch, Norma, y el Swift ofrecen munición cargada en .505 Gibbs.
El .505 Gibbs fue desarrollado exclusivamente para cazar animales grandes de pellejo grueso, como el búfalo de cabo, el  elefante, y el rinoceronte.
Fue usado por el personaje de ficción, Robert Wilson, el cazador del libro «La vida corta y feliz de Francis Macomber» de Ernest Hemingway.​


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.505_Gibbs)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>