<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .50 GI (12.7×23mmRB) pistol cartridge was developed by Alex Zimmermann of Guncrafter Industries. The .50 GI was introduced at the 2004 SHOT Show alongside the Guncrafter Industries Model No. 1, a variation of the M1911. The round has a rebated rim that is the same diameter as that of the .45 ACP.
In 2006, Guncrafter Industries introduced its 1911 Model No. 2 which sports a full length light rail/dust cover and is chambered for the .50 GI cartridge. Both the M1 and the M2 can be fitted with Guncrafter Industries' .45 ACP conversion unit, the .45 ACP magazines hold 8 rounds.
Physically, the .50 GI round is wider than the .45 ACP and slightly longer. The M1 and M2 magazines can hold seven rounds. The Glock conversion can hold eight rounds in the standard magazine and nine with the extended base pad. 

The .50 GI operates at pressures comparable to the .45 ACP, around 15,000 psi (100 MPa). Felt recoil is not unlike that of the .45 ACP. The .50 GI has developed a reputation for accuracy, though this may be due to the high precision of the semi-custom and very expensive Guncrafter pistols themselves. In one test, the 300 grain (19 g) jacketed flatpoint (JFP) gave a 25-yard group of 2.24 inches, and the 300-grain Jacketed hollow point (JHP) and 275-grain JHP gave a 25-yard group of 2.14 inches.
The penetration in gelatin (but not necessarily the kinetic energy) of the .50 GI is significantly different than the .45 ACP. While it is one of the few examples of the largest legally allowed caliber projectile (.50) in a semiauto handgun, it was purpose built to have a recoil impulse and kinetic energy substantially less than the magnum .50 caliber rounds such as the .50 Action Express (semiautomatic) or .500 S&amp;W Magnum (revolver). Factory loaded ammunition has a kinetic energy of around 500 ft·lb.
The cartridge is not used in law enforcement and rarely for personal defense due to limited availability of ammunition and guns chambered for the cartridge. Currently, the only commercial handguns available in this caliber are Guncrafter Industries' own Colt 1911 handgun variants and its Glock 21/Glock 20 conversion upper receiver, and Magnum Research chambers their BFR revolver in this caliber on a custom basis.

https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.50_GI
</EN>
<DE>
Das Kaliber .50 GI ist eine seltene Patrone aus der Entwicklung der Firma Guncrafter Industries (USA).
Im deutschen Nationalen Waffenregister (NWR) wird die Patrone unter Katalognummer 2226 ohne weitere Synonyme geführt. 
Ziel der Entwicklung war eine große Patrone mit hoher Mannstoppwirkung für eine Pistole nach dem Prinzip der 1911er-Pistolen, Browning-System. Es sollte die Stoppwirkung des Kaliber .45 ACP deutlich übertroffen werden, um die Patrone und Waffen diese Kalibers deutlich für den taktischen Bereich zu qualifizieren. Im Gegensatz zur durchschlagstarken 9-mm-Parabellum sowie den Kalibern .45 ACP und 10 mm Auto sollte das Kaliber .50 GI nur gute Eigenschaften wie Stoppwirkung, verbunden mit leichter Beherrschbarkeit der Waffe im Schuss, durch verminderte Druckverhältnisse, erhalten.
Die .50 GI ist, im Gegensatz z. B. zur 10 mm Auto, eine Patrone mit geringem Innendruck, was zu geringerem Rückstoß und geringerer Durchschlagskraft, aber zu verbesserter Stoppwirkung führt. Andere, leistungsstärkere Patronen im Kaliber .50, wie z. B. die .50 AE, erfordern schwerere Waffen. So liegt das Verwendungsgebiet bei der Selbstverteidigung, dem Polizeieinsatz oder der jagdlichen Nachsuche. Besonders geeignet ist dieses Kaliber durch seinen hohen Hit-Faktor auch für das sportliche Schießen mit der praktischen Pistole.

https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.50_GI
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
N/A
</FR>
</loc>