<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .577/500 No 2 Black Powder Express, also known as the 12.7mm British No 2, is a British centerfire fire rifle cartridge.
The .577/500 No 2 BPE was developed as a black powder round some time before 1879 by necking down the .577 Black Powder Express to .507-inches (12.9 mm) for use in single or double rifles, as well as a variety of Martini-based lever rifles.
Like the .450 Black Powder Express, the .577/500 BPE came in several case lengths, the most common having a 3-inch case. A 3+1⁄8-inch variant would later be loaded with cordite to become the .577/500 Nitro Express.
For some time the .577/500 No 2 BPE was loaded with cordite to become the .577/500 No 2 Nitro for Black, the same cartridge loaded with mild loadings of cordite, carefully balanced through trial to replicate the ballistics of the Black powder version.
The .577/500 No 2 BPE was a popular cartridge in India for hunting all thin-skinned game up to tiger. It didn't face competition from comparable .450 rounds there in the decades following 1907 due to the ban on British military calibres. Like the .500 Black Powder Express, the .577/500 No 2 BPE was never popular in Africa, not being powerful enough for thick-skinned game such as elephant.
Moderately popular in its day, the round has long since ceased to be offered commercially.

This ammunition-related article is a stub. You can help Wikipedia by expanding it.

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.577/500_No_2_Black_Powder_Express)
</EN>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>

(+) 340 gr - 22 g
(+) 1 925 ft/s - 587 m/s
(+) 3 800 J J
 Le .577/500 No 2 Black Powder Express, également connu comme 12.7 mm British No 2, est une cartouche à bourrelet et à percussion centrale britannique destinée aux fusils.
Le .577 / 500 No 2 B.P.E. a été développé en tant que munition propulsée par poudre noire avant 1879 en réduisant le .577 Black Powder Express à .507 pouces (12,9 mm)
, pour une utilisation avec des fusils, comme par exemple une grande variété de fusils à levier Martini-Henry. 
Comme le .450 Black Powder Express, le .577 / 500 B.P.E. est disponible en plusieurs longueurs de douille, la plus courante étant 3 pouces. Une variante de 3⅛ pouces serait plus tard chargée de cordite pour devenir le .577 / 500 Nitro Express.  
Le .577 / 500 No 2 B.P.E. a parfois été également chargé de cordite pour devenir le .577 / 500 No 2 Nitro for Black, la même cartouche utilisant de petites charges de cordite, soigneusement déduite après essai, pour reproduire la balistique de la version à poudre noire.
Le .577 / 500 No 2 B.P.E. était une cartouche populaire en Inde pour chasser tout type de gibier à peau mince, jusqu'au tigre.  Comme le .500 B.P.E., le .577 / 500 No 2 B.P.E. n'a jamais été populaire en Afrique, n'étant pas assez puissant pour le gibier à peau épaisse comme l'éléphant.  
Modérément populaire à son époque, cette munition a depuis longtemps cessé d'être commercialisée. 


(https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.577/500_No_2_Black_Powder_Express)
</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>