<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .577 Nitro Express is a large-bore centerfire rifle cartridge designed for the purpose of hunting large game such as elephant. This cartridge is used almost exclusively in single-shot and double express rifles for hunting in the Tropics or hot climates in general and is a cartridge associated with the golden age of African safaris and Indian shikars.
The .577 Nitro Express is a straight rimmed .584-inch (14.8 mm) calibre cartridge designed for use in single-shot and double rifles. It has been made in three case lengths based on their respective black-powder .577 Black Powder Express cartridges.
The .577 Nitro Express 2+3⁄4-inch [70 mm] is a conversion of the .577 Black Powder Express 2+3⁄4-inch, it fires a 750-grain (49 g) projectile at over 1,800 feet per second (550 m/s). Never as popular as the 3-inch version, today it is only available by special order.
The .577 Nitro Express 3-inch [76 mm] is a conversion of the .577 Black Powder Express 3-inch, it fires a 750-grain (49 g) projectile at over 2,050 feet per second (620 m/s). This cartridge was to become the most popular of the three and a standard round for African elephant hunters in the early 20th century.
The .577 Nitro Express 3+1⁄4-inch [83 mm] is a conversion of the .577 Black Powder Express 31⁄4-inch, again it was never as popular as the 3-inch version.
Following the success of the development in 1898 of the revolutionary .450 Nitro Express by John Rigby &amp; Company, achieved by loading the old .450 Black Powder Express with cordite, similar conversions were made to other blackpowder Express cartridges, including the .577 Black Powder Express in its various case lengths.
Once a standard rifle calibre, the rise of Mauser's Gewehr 98 bolt-action rifles offered cheaper alternatives to the expensive double rifles required by the Nitro Express cartridges. Several manufacturers still make rifles chambered in .577 Nitro Express, including Butch Searcy &amp; Co., Hambrusch Hunting Weapons, Hartmann &amp; Weiss, Heym, Holland &amp; Holland, James Purdey and Sons and Westley Richards.
In 1914 and early 1915, German snipers were engaging British Army positions with impunity from behind steel plates that were impervious to .303 British ball ammunition. In an attempt to counter this threat, the British War Office purchased fifty-two large-bore sporting rifles from British rifle makers which were issued to regiments, including two .577 Nitro Express rifles. These large-bore rifles proved very effective against the steel plates used by the Germans, in his book Sniping in France 1914-18 Major H. Hesketh-Prichard, DSO, MC stated that they "pierced them like butter".
The .577 Nitro Express is suitable for hunting all dangerous game, although it was considered something of a specialist elephant hunter's tool for close-cover hunting and emergencies, the harsh recoil this round produces requires a rifle of 13-pound (5.9 kg) minimum weight. Typically a hunter carried a lighter rifle in a smaller calibre for general hunting whilst a rifle bearer carried a heavy gun such as this, a necessity as an exhausted man could not reliably aim such heavy rifles as these.
In his African Rifles and Cartridges, John "Pondoro" Taylor says the .577 Nitro Express is "a magnificent killer – it literally crumbles up an elephant", further stating the shock of a head shot from a .577 Nitro Express bullet is enough to knock an elephant out for up to 20 minutes.
James H. Sutherland, who over the course of his life shot between 1,300 and 1,600 elephants, stated in his The Adventures of an Elephant Hunter, "after experimenting with and using all kinds of rifles, I find the most effective to be the double .577 with a 750 grains bullet and a charge in Axite powder equivalent to a hundred grains of cordite." And further stating "I think the superiority of the .577 over the .450 and .500 rifles, will be evident when I state that I have lost elephants with these last two rifles, while I have bagged others with identically the same shots from a .577."
Other famous African users include Major G.H. Anderson (shot between 350 and 400 elephants), Deaf Banks (shot over 1,000 elephants), Quentin Grogan, John A. Hunter (shot more than 1,000 rhinoceros) and Pete Pearson (shot over 2,000 elephants).
"Pondoro" Taylor used a Westley Richards .577 Nitro Express double rifle, stating "it did great work for me amongst elephant, rhino and buffalo; it's much too powerful for anything lighter." He parted with the rifle after only a short period because the single-trigger mechanism was unlike all of his other rifles.
Ernest Hemingway and Alfred Józef Potocki both owned Westley Richards Droplock .577 Nitro Express double rifles, Stewart Granger owned two including Potocki's rifle.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.577_Nitro_Express)
</EN>
<ES>
El .577 Nitro Express es un cartucho de fuego central de gran calibre, diseñado para la caza de elefantes y animales similares, y para ser usado exclusivamente en rifles de dos cañones en regiones tropicales. Está asociado con la época dorada de los safaris africanos e indios.
El .577 Nitro Express es un cartucho recto de .584 pulgadas (14.8 mm), con un anillo en la base del casquillo para ser usado solo en rifles monotiro y dobles. Se hizo en tres longitudes de casquillo, derivadas del .577 Black Powder Express.
El .577 Nitro Express de 2 3⁄4 puladas (70mm)  es una conversión del .577 Black Powder Express de 2 3⁄4 pulgadas,  despidiendo un proyectil de 750 granos (49 g) a más de 1,800 pies por segundo (550 m/s). Nunca tan popular como la versión de 3 pulgadas, hoy solo está disponible por encargo especial.
El .577 Nitro Express de 3 pulgadas (76,2 mm), derivado del .577 Black Powder Express de 3 pulgadas, dispara un proyectil de 750 granos (49 g) a más de 2,050 pies por segundo (620 m/s). Este cartucho fue el más popular de las 3 opciones y el round estándar para los cazadores de elefantes en el África a principios del siglo 20..
El .577 Nitro Express de 3 1⁄4 pulgada (8mm)  derivado también del .577 Black Powder Express de 3 1⁄4-pulgadas, nunca fue tan popular como la versión de 3 pulgadas.
Siguiendo el éxito del revolucionario .450 Nitro Express desarrollado en 1898 por John Rigby &amp; Co., logrado al cargar el antiguo cartucho .450 Black Powder Express con cordita, devino en nuevas conversiones de otros cartuchos Express de pólvora negra, incluyendo el .577 Black Powder Express en sus varias longitudes de casquillo.
El .577 Nitro Express es adecuado para cazar todo tipo de animales peligrosos, a pesar de considerado un cartucho netamente para la caza de elefantes en zonas de monte y en caso de emergencias, debido al fuerte retroceso que estos cartuchos generan, haciendo que el peso mínimo de los rifles recamarados en este calbire sean de aproximadamente 13-libras (5.9 Kg) de peso. Típicamente un cazador llevaba un rifle más ligero de menor calibre para caza general, mientras un portador cargaba este rifle ya que un hombre agotado por cargar un arma de este peso no podría apuntar de manera confianza este rifle..
En sus Rifles africanos y Cartuchos, John "Pondoro" Taylor describe al .577 Nitro Express como "un asesino magnífico  lo literalmente derriba a un elefante", declarando también que el shock de un tiro a la cabeza con un .577 Nitro Express es suficiente para noquear a un elefante por 20 minutos.
James H. Sutherland, quién a lo largo de su vida cazó entre 1,300 y 1,600 elefantes, declarados en su libro Las Aventuras de un Cazador de Elefantes, "después de experimentar con todo tipo de rifles,  encuentro el más eficaz al rifle doble calibre .577 con una 750 bala de granos y una carga equivalente a cien granos de cordite." Y más allá declarando " pienso que la superioridad del .577 sobre el .450 y .500 rifles, se evidencia cuándo preciso que he perdido elefantes con estos últimos dos rifles, mientras  he cazado otros con tiros idénticos disparados de un .577."
"Pondoro" Taylor utilizó un Westley Richards .577 Nitro Express rifle, declarando "hizo un gran trabajo para mí con el elefante, rinoceronte y búfalo; es demasiado potente para cualquier cosa más ligera.".
Ernest Hemingway y Alfred Józef Potocki ambos tuvieron rifles doble Westley Richards Droplock .577 Nitro Express, Stewart Granger tuvo dos incluyendo Potocki  rifle.
 


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.577_Nitro_Express)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>