<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .600 Nitro Express is a large bore Nitro Express rifle cartridge developed by W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co for the purpose of hunting large game such as elephant.
The .600 Nitro Express is a slightly tapered walled, rimmed, centerfire rifle cartridge designed for use in single-shot and double rifles.
The cartridge fires a .620 in (15.7 mm) diameter, 900 gr (58 g) projectile with three powder loadings: the standard being 100 gr (6.5 g) of cordite at a muzzle velocity of 1,850 ft/s (560 m/s); a 110 gr (7.1 g) loading which generates a muzzle velocity of 1,950 ft/s (590 m/s); and a 120 gr (7.8 g) loading which generates a muzzle velocity of 2,050 ft/s (620 m/s).
Because of the recoil forces generated by this cartridge, rifles chambered in it typically weigh up to 16 lb (7.3 kg).
The .600 Nitro Express was developed by London gunmakers W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co. Sources vary about the date of its introduction,[note 1] although it would seem in 1900 the first .600 Nitro Express rifle was produced by W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co, a 15 lb (6.8 kg) double barrelled hammer rifle. Jefferys produced around seventy rifles in .600 Nitro Express in four actions, double barrelled hammer break-open, single barrelled break-open, falling block and double barrelled break-open with and without ejectors.
Until the introduction of the .700 Nitro Express in 1988, the .600 Nitro Express was the most powerful commercially available hunting rifle cartridge in the world. Aside from W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co, several gunmakers have and continue to offer rifles chambering this .600 Nitro Express, although in 2009 it was estimated by Holland &amp; Holland that only around one hundred .600 Nitro Express rifles had ever been produced to that time.
In 1914 and early 1915, German snipers were engaging British Army positions with impunity from behind steel plates that were impervious to .303 British ball ammunition. In an attempt to counter this threat, the British War Office purchased sixty-two large-bore sporting rifles from British rifle makers, including four .600 Nitro Express rifles, which were issued to regiments. These large-bore rifles proved very effective against the steel plates used by the Germans. In his book, Sniping in France 1914-18, Major H. Hesketh-Prichard, DSO, MC stated they "pierced them like butter".
Stuart Cloete, sniping officer for the King's Own Yorkshire Light Infantry, stated "We used a heavy sporting rifle - a .600 Express. These had been donated to the army by big game hunters and when we hit a plate we stove it right in. But it had to be fired standing or from a kneeling position to take up the recoil. The first man who fired it from the prone position had his collar bone broken."
The .600 Nitro Express, along with the .577 Nitro Express, was a specialist backup weapon for professional elephant hunters. Too heavy to be carried all day and used effectively, it was usually carried by a gun bearer. It was used when in thick cover and when an effective shot at the heart and lungs was not possible.
In his African Rifles and Cartridges, John "Pondoro" Taylor says the shock of a head shot from a .600 Nitro Express bullet is enough to knock out an elephant for up to half an hour.
In the course of his career, Taylor owned and used two .600 Nitro Express double rifles, the first was regulated for 110 gr (7.1 g) loadings, the second was a W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co double rifle that weighed 16 lb (7.3 kg) with 24 in (610 mm) barrels and was regulated for 100 gr loadings.  He states he was very fond of his Jeffery .600 which he used as a second backup rifle to a .400 Jeffery Nitro Express, and with it he killed between 60 and 70 elephants.
Bror von Blixen-Finecke, Karl Larsen and Major Percy Powell-Cotton all used W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co .600 Nitro Express rifles extensively.
In 1929 Holland &amp; Holland produced the .600/577 Rewa by necking down the .600 Nitro Express to accept a .582 in (14.8 mm) bullet.
The .50 British ammunition used in the Vickers .50 machine gun was initially a necked-down .600 NE.
In the 1997 film The Lost World: Jurassic Park the character Roland Tembo carries a Searcy Double Barrel Rifle chambered in .600 Nitro Express.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.600_Nitro_Express)
</EN>
<ES>
El .600 Nitro Express es un cartucho de rifle de gran calibre desarrollado por W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co para la caza de elefantes. 
El .600 Nitro Express es un cartucho de casquillo recto, de fuego central y con un anillo en la base del casquillo para su uso en rifles monotiro y rifles dobles.
El .600 Nitro Express dispara un proyectil de .620 pulgadas (15.7 mm) de 900 granos (58 gr) con tres cargas de pólvora. La estándar con 100 granos (6.5 gr) de cordita, logrando una velocidad de salida de 1,850 pies por segundo. Una segunda carga de 110 granos de cordita, generando una velocidad de salida 1,950 pies por segundo; y una tercera carga de 120 granos, que genera velocidades de salida de 2,050 pies por segundo.
Debido al abrupto retroceso del cartucho, los rifles recamarados en este calibre pesan aproximadamente 16 libras (7.3 kg ).
El .600 Nitro Express, junto con el .577 Nitro Express son cartuchos especializados para su uso por los cazadores profesionales de elefantes en caso de emergencia. Es demasiado pesado de ser cargado todo el día y ser disparado eficazmente, fue normalmente cargado por un portador, para ser solo usado por el cazador cuando se encontrase en zonas de monte tupido  y un tiro eficaz al corazón y pulmones no fuera posible.
.
En sus Rifles africanos y Cartuchos, John "Pondoro" Taylor dice que shock de un tiro en la cabeza con un .600 Nitro Express la bala es suficiente para noquear a un elefante  por media hora.
Durante su carrera, Taylor uso dos rifles .600 Nitro Express. El primero estuvo calibrado para disparar con las cargas de 110 granos, y el segundo, un W.J Jeffery &amp; Co, que pesaba 16 libras con dos cañones de 24 pulgadas, estuvo calibrado para ser usado con cargas de 100 granos de cordita. Le tuvo mucho aprecio a su Jeffery .600 NE, el cual usaba como back up a su .400 Jeffery Nitro Express. Con este rifle cazó entre 60 y 70 elefantes.
1929 Holland &amp; de Holland produjo el .600/577 Rewa ajustando el  casquillo del.600 Nitro Express para alojar una bala de .582 en (14.8 mm).
 
 


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.600_Nitro_Express)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>