<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .256 Newton was a high-velocity, rimless centerfire cartridge based on the .30-06 Springfield military cartridge and developed in 1913 by Charles Newton in conjunction with the Western Cartridge Company. To make the .256 Newton cartridge, the .30-06 case was necked down to a caliber of .264 inches, the overall case length was shortened, body taper was increased, the neck was moved back, and the shoulder was given a sharper, 23-degree angle, as opposed to the 17-degree shoulder of the parent cartridge.
The .256 Newton suffered from a lack of available slow-burning powders capable of fully exploiting the large capacity of the parent case. Newton's company went bankrupt after the end of World War I and production of commercially loaded ammunition ceased by 1938.
After World War II, with a supply of 6.5mm rifles (.264 caliber), the availability of slower burning powders, and inexpensive, surplus .30-06 brass cases, shooters developed the 6.5mm-06 wildcat cartridge by necking down the .30-06 case to 6.5mm (.264 inches). In 1997, the A-Square company standardized the chambering as the 6.5-06 A-Square with the Sporting Arms and Ammunition Manufacturers' Institute (SAAMI). Although substantially similar, the .256 Newton is not interchangeable with the .30-06 parent cartridge, the 6.5-06 wildcat chambering, or the SAAMI standardized 6.5-06 A-Square cartridge.

This ammunition-related article is a stub. You can help Wikipedia by expanding it.

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.256_Newton)
</EN>
<ES>
El .256 Newton es un cartucho descontinuado, de fuego central basado en el casquillo del .30-06 Springfield y desarrollado en 1913 por Charles Newton en conjunto con la Western Cartridge Company.​ 
Para desarrollar el .256 Newton, el cuello del casquillo del .30-06 Springfield se ajustó para alojar un proyectil de .264 pulgadas (6.5mm), y se redujo la longitud del casquillo, moviendo el cuello hacia atrás, dándole al hombro un ángulo más agudo, de 23 grados, opuesto al hombro de 17 grados del cartucho padre.​
El .256 Newton adoleció una carencia de pólvoras de combustión lentas en aquella época.​ La compañía del newton entró en banca rota después del fin de Primera Guerra mundial y la producción comercial de munición cesó en 1938.​
Después de que Segunda Guerra mundial, con un suministro de 6.5mm rifles (.264), la disponibilidad de pólvoras en llamas más lentas, y económicas, además del superávit de casquillos .30-06, los tiradores deportivos desarrollaron el 6.5mm-06 ajustando el cuello del 30-06 para alojar munición de 6.5mm (.264 pulgadas).​ En 1997, A-Square estandarizó el 6.5-06 en conjunto con (SAAMI).​​
El .256 Newton es capaz de estabilizar proyectiles de hasta 130 granos y con las pólvoras actuales puede lograr velocidades de salida de 3,000 pies por segundo con un proyectil de 120 granos, y 2,900 pies por segundo con un proyectil de 130 granos.​
Un proyectil de 6.5mm con un peso de entre 120 y 130 granos con velocidades de salida de alrededor de 3,000 pies por segundo es adecuado para la caza mayor de cualquier presa de ligera o de tamaño medio.
 


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.256_Newton)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>