<loc>
<IT>N/A</IT>
<EN>
The .25 Stevens Short was an American rimfire rifle cartridge, introduced in 1902.
Developed by J. Stevens Arms &amp; Tool Company, it was intended to be a lower cost, less potent variant of the .25 Stevens, on which it was based. It initially used a 4.5 to 5 gr (0.29 to 0.32 g) black powder charge; this was later replaced by smokeless. It was offered in Stevens, Remington, and Winchester rifles, and could be used in any .25 Stevens rifle, also (in the way the .38 Special can be fired in weapons chambered for .357 Magnum).
It was more powerful than the .22 Short, as well as less expensive, but more costly than the .22 Long Rifle and offering no edge in performance. It was also inferior to its parent cartridge. As a result, it was not a popular hunting round.
It was dropped in 1942. 

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.25_Stevens_Short)

The .25 Stevens was an American rimfire rifle cartridge. To differentiate from the related .25 Stevens Short it is sometimes also referred to as .25 Stevens long.
Developed by J. Stevens Arms &amp; Tool Company and Peters Cartridge Company, it was developed between 1898 and 1900; catalogs suggest it was introduced in 1898, but most sources agree on 1900. It was offered in the Crack Shot #15 rifle, which debuted in 1900. It was also available in the Favorite rifle, which was first released in 1894 and discontinued in 1935. It originally used a 10 to 11 gr (0.65 to 0.71 g) black powder charge under a 67 gr (4.3 g) slug; this was later replaced by smokeless.
Some handguns were also chambered for .25 Stevens, most notably the Stevens-Lord single shot pistols.
The round was available with either solid lead or hollow point bullet and developed a good reputation for small game (such as rabbit) and varmint.
In comparison to the .22 Long Rifle some sources note that its ballistics suffered from an excessively high trajectory for a rifle cartridge (a drop of 5.1 in (130 mm) at 100 yd (91 m)), while others praise its inherent accuracy, and larger versatility due to being much more powerful, especially when being used in revolvers.
Serving as the parent for the less-successful .25 Stevens Short and experimental Remington .267 Rimfire, it was dropped in 1942.
Notable handgun authority Elmer Keith lamented its demise and advocated its revival for use in revolvers. 

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.25_Stevens)
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>