<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .275 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum is a semi-obsolete rifle cartridge similar to the 7mm Remington Magnum.  Essentially the .275 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum is a necked down shortened variant of the .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum. It was introduced by the British company Holland &amp; Holland with the .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum that was introduced in 1912 as the .375 Belted Rimless Nitro-Express.  The .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum was intended for dangerous African game animals, while the .275 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum was intended for longer range shooting of antelope in Africa and Red Stag in the highlands of Scotland.
Aside from the belted case, the .275 H&amp;H was very similar to the .276 Enfield cartridge of the Pattern 1913 Enfield rifle then under development by the British military to replace the Lee–Enfield.  Cordite loadings gave both cartridges a reputation for unpleasant muzzle flash and short barrel life. Western Cartridge Company offered United States loadings of the .275 H&amp;H Magnum in 1925 with the .300 H&amp;H and the .375 H&amp;H.  The .275 H&amp;H was omitted when Winchester Repeating Arms Company started chambering their Winchester Model 70 rifle for the other two in 1937.  The .275 H&amp;H offered little ballistic advantage over the .270 Winchester with contemporary smokeless powders.  U.S. ammunition production ceased during 1939.
Following World War II, independent gunsmiths in the United States began exploring the ballistic possibilities of military surplus IMR 4831 powder salvaged from Oerlikon 20mm cannon cartridges and marketed by Hodgdon Powder Company.  The long range ballistics of wildcat cartridges resulted in commercial availability of the 7×61mm Sharpe &amp; Hart in 1953, and the 7mm Remington Magnum in 1962.  The .275 H&amp;H had been a cartridge ahead of its time.
Holland &amp; Holland continue to supply factory loaded .275 ammunition and the cartridge is occasionally chambered in custom made modern "classic" rifles. 275 H&amp;H enthusiasts have noted that the distinctive "H&amp;H taper" of the case offers some advantages over the 7×61mm and 7mm Rem mag. Namely, more reliable and smoother feeding in bolt-action rifles, and more compact stacking in a box magazine allowing longer overall length of cartridge. With modern powders, the 275 H&amp;H can be handloaded to equal any of the currently available 7mm Magnum chamberings, up to 2.5"(63mm) case length. Correctly headstamped empty brass cases are made by Quality Cartridge Co. USA.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.275_H%26H_Magnum)
</EN>
<ES>
El .275 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum es un cartucho de rifle que si bien es considerado casi obsoleto, con cargas adecuadas con pólvoras modernas es capaz de igualar la performance del .7mm Remington Magnum. Esencialmente, el .275 H&amp;H Magnum es el resultado de la reducción de la longitud y el ajuste del cuello del casquillo del .375 H&amp;H Magnum.
Fue introducido por la compañía inglesa en 1912 en conjunto con el .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum, siendo el .375 destinado para la caza de animales peligrosos, mientras que el .275 H&amp;H Mag como un complemento para la caza de animales más ligeros como antílopes en África y ciervo rojo en Escocia.
Aparte del cinturón en el casquillo, el .275 H&amp;H era muy similar al .276 Enfield, el cartucho que alimenta el rifle Enfield Pattern 1913, que para entonces estaba siendo desarrollado por el ejército Inglés para reemplazar al Lee–Enfield. Las cargas con Cordita dio a ambos cartuchos la reputación de generar una explosión desagradable en la boca del cañón cuando eran disparados, además de una corta vida de los cañones.​ Western Cartridge Company de los Estados Unidos comercializaba cargas para el 275 H&amp;H Magnum en 1925 además del .300 H&amp;H y el .375 H&amp;H. El .275 H&amp;H fue omitido cuándo Winchester Repeating Arms Company empezó a recamarar su Winchester Modelo 70 para los otros dos cartuchos en 1937, ya que el .275 H&amp;H no ofrecía ventaja balística alguna sobre el .270 Winchester con su cargas entonces contemporáneas de pólvora sin humo.​ La producción de munición en los EE.UU. cesó en1939.
Holland &amp; Holland continúa suministrando munición .275 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum y el cartucho es ocasionalmente usado para la producción de rifles "clásicos" modernos.
Quienes son entuciastas del 275 H&amp;H han notado que el distintivo diseño del casquillo del "H&amp;H" ofrece algunas ventajas sobre el 7×61mm y 7mm Rem mag. Concretamente, más fiable y de alimentación más lisa en rifles de cerrojo, y más compactos para almacenar en un cargador de caja que permitiendo una longitud global más larga para el cartucho. Con pólvoras modernas el 275 H&amp;H puede ser recargado para igualar a cualquiera de las opciones de 7mm Magnum disponibles actualmente que tengan casquillos de hasta 2.5"(63mm) de longitud.


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.275_Holland_%26_Holland_Magnum)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>