<loc>

<DE>
Die .280 Remington, auch bekannt als 7 mm Remington Express, wurde 1957 für die Gewehre von Remington Modelle 740, 760, 721 und 725 eingeführt. Sie basiert auf der .30-06 Springfield, bei der der Hülsenhals verjüngt und etwas verlängert wurde, so dass ein 7-mm-Geschoss (0.284 inch) passt.
Als Konkurrenzmodell zur .270 Winchester gedacht, unterscheidet sich die .280 Remington von dieser nur durch ihre etwas schwächere Ladung und etwas größeren Geschossdurchmesser.
Die .280 Remington konnte sich jedoch nicht wirklich gegen die .30-06 und die .270 Winchester durchsetzen, was sich insbesondere in den Verkaufszahlen widerspiegelte. So versuchte Remington im Jahr 1979, mit der Umbenennung auf 7 mm Remington Express den Umsatz der .280 Remington zu steigern. Da der Absatz weiter stagnierte und die Schützen in den USA durch die neue Bezeichnung verwirrt wurden, sah sich Remington im Jahr 1981 gezwungen, die Umbenennung wieder rückgängig zu machen.
Im deutschen Nationalen Waffenregister (NWR) wird die Patrone unter Katalognummer 49 unter folgenden Bezeichnungen geführt (Auswahl, gebräuchliche Bezeichnungen in Fettdruck)


(https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.280_Remington)
</DE>
<EN>
The .280 Remington, also known as the 7mm-06 Remington and  7mm Express Remington, was introduced in 1957 for the Remington model 740, 760, 721, and 725 rifles.
Having been released 32 years after the .270 Winchester, it had somewhat unspectacular sales. Remington renamed the cartridge in late 1978 to 7mm-06 Remington. but just before the end of the year, they renamed it again, calling it the 7 mm Express in an attempt to increase sales.  This resulted in people confusing it with the 7 mm Remington Magnum, and Remington changed the name back to .280 in 1981.
The .280 is based on the .30-06 necked down to accept 7 mm (.284 in) bullets, with the neck moved forward .050 in (1.27mm). The neck was deliberately moved forward to prevent chambering in a .270 Winchester rifle, as firing a .280 round in a .270 rifle could cause the projectile to get stuck in the barrel or rupture the barrel due to excessive pressure.
The .280 Remington is capable of generating slightly higher velocities in heavier bullet weights (150 grains and above) than the .270 Winchester due to a marginally greater case capacity. However, the ballistic coefficient of equal-weight bullets favors .270 caliber bullets over 7mm (.284) bullets of similar design. In the heavier bullets (150 grains and above) of similar design, the .280 Remington has a slight edge in muzzle energy.
With equal-weight bullets of similar design, the .270 Winchester surpasses the .280 Remington's long-range velocity and energy due to the 270's higher ballistic coefficient according to Federal's ammunition catalog. There are also many more factory loads available for the .270 Winchester over the .280 Remington at a lower price point due to the .270's much greater popularity.
Renowned for being a strong advocate of the .270 Winchester, gun writer Jack O'Connor's last rifle was a Ruger M77 restocked by Alvin Biesen but this time chambered in .280 Remington, which tells about the high regards O'Connor had on the cartridge.
The .280 Remington is capable of developing energy nearly equal to the .30-06 Springfield, but with lighter bullets having a better ballistic coefficient.  The .30-06 produces more energy than the .280 with bullets heavier than 180 grains, though .284" 175-grain bullets have a high sectional density of .310, compared to the 30-06 180-grain bullet with a moderate sectional density of .271. The .280 is suitable for hunting any game in North America with good shot placement.
SAAMI pressure limit for the .280 Remington is set at 60,000 PSI, 50,000 CUP.
Most American rifle and ammunition manufacturers catalogue the .280 Remington.
The .30-06 is substantially more popular and manufacturers thus offer a much greater selection of loads at a substantially lower price point.
While it is true that a .280 Remington case can be formed from a .30-06 Springfield case, the case length of a .30-06 is 63.3 millimetres (2.494 in) while the case length of a .280 is 64.5 millimetres (2.540 in), the same as a .30-03 Springfield. However, "The slight difference in length of reformed cases doesn't make any practical difference."  
In Europe the .280 Remington is not popular in bolt-action rifles since it competes directly with the 7×64mm, which is of the almost exact same size as the .280 Remington but has slightly more power,  because of having a slightly higher maximum allowed chamber pressure and a slightly higher case capacity. The twist rate for the 7x64 is 1 in 8.66 inch against 1 in 10 inch for the 280 Remington. Nearly every European rifle producer offers the 7x64 as a standard caliber.
The .280 Remington does, however, have a larger than expected number of European users in imported self-loading rifles such as those by Remington.
One of P.O. Ackley's earliest wildcats was the 7mm-06 Improved, which was made by necking down the .30-06
Springfield case and fire-forming it to have less body taper and a 40-degree shoulder angle. Soon after the .280 Remington came out, Fred Huntington reformed its case to an improved configuration with minimum body taper, a 35-degree shoulder angle, and called it the .280 RCBS. Since cases for the .280 RCBS could be formed by firing .280 Remington ammo in a rifle chambered for the former, Ackley abandoned the 7mm-06 Improved and started chambering rifles for the .280 RCBS. He then changed the 35-degree shoulder to 40-degrees and the .280 Ackley Improved was born. If barrel length and chamber pressure are equal, the .280 Ackley Improved is about 100 fps faster with all bullet weights than the standard .280 Remington. In 2007, ammunition manufacturer Nosler registered the .280 Ackley Improved with SAAMI and began providing factory loaded ammunition and rifles for it.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.280_Remington)
</EN>
<ES>
El .280 Remington, previamente conocido como el 7mm Remington Express, es un tipo de munición para rifle que se introdujo en 1957 para los fusiles Remington modelos 740, 760, 721, y 725.​ El .280 Remington se desarrolla a partir del casquillo del .30-06 Springfield, al cual se le alarga y ajusta el cuello a .050 (1.27mm), para alojar un proyectil de 7mm o .284",y que pueda ser usado en un mecanismo de cerrojo de longitud estándar.​ 
32 años después de la aparición del popular .270 Winchester, Remington lanzó al mercado el .280 Remington, llamándolo al poco tiempo el 7mm Remington Express, en un intento por aumentar las ventas. Pero en 1962 fue introducido el 7 mm Remington Magnum, generando confusiones por la similitud en el nombre. Debido a este problema, Remington cambió el nombre nuevamente a .280 en 1981.​
El último rifle de Jack O' Connor, el famoso escritor de armas norteamericano responsable en parte del éxito del .270 Winchester, fue un Ruger M77 recamarado en .280 Remington.​
El .280 Remington es un cartucho similar al .270 Winchester y el .30-06 Srpingfield, disparando un calibre intermedio entre ambos, y que muchos consideran el balance perfecto entre ambos calibres. Con un proyectil de 140 granos es capaz de tener una trayectoria más plana a distancias aceptables para fines cinegéticos, que el .30-06 Springfield, y a su vez, un mayor coeficiente balístico y densidad seccional que el .270 Winchester con el popular proyectil de 130 granos, permitiéndole sortear vientos cruzados de manera más eficiente y ofrecer una mayor penetración con balas de similar construcción. A pesar de estas características, el .280 Remington nunca logró alcanzar la popularidad de ninguno de los otros dos.​ 
El .280 Remington es un calibre versátil de caza mayor, capaz de replicar las prestaciones del .30-06 y del .270 Winchester. Actualmente el .280 Ackley Improved, una versión mejorada del .280 Remington, por P.O Ackley, ha resucitado y viene ganando mucha popularidad entre los aficionados a la caza deportiva, debido a una mejora en la velocidad de salida que resulta en una trayectoria más templada obtenida por el efecto de modificar los hombros del casquillo de 35 a 40 grados, acercando la velocidad de salida del .280 AI al 7 mm Remington Magnum sin un incremento sustancial en la carga de pólvora.


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.280_Remington)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>