<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro .30 - 378 Weatherby Magnum è un derivato diretto della cartuccia calibro .378 Weatherby Magnum (V. voce a se) ottenuto per restringmento del colletto fino a consentire l'introduzione di una palla del diametro nominale di 7,62mm (.308") . Storicamente parlando, essa venne sviluppata da Roy Weatherby negli anni '50 del XX secolo in collaborazione con le FF.AA. USA (N.B. ed in particolare con l'Esercito) allo scopo di creare una cartuccia da destinare al tiro di precisione a lunga distanza (long distance sniping). Purtroppo, anche se i presupposti sembravano molto incoraggianti, questa munizione, visse per lunghi anni , fondamentalmente come munizione sperimentale (wildcat), pur se con diverse forme, e venne standartizzata solo nel 1996. 
Il motivo va ricercato nel fatto che l'impianto strutturale della cartuccia richiedeva l'impiego specifico di propellenti estremamente LENTI a bruciare, che all'epoca della sua nascita erano scarsamente reperibili (per non dire del tutto assenti sul mercato). Tanto per fare un esempio, polveri adatte a questo calibro sono prodotti altamente specifici come la MRP-2, la N-170, la H-1000 o la H-870 (N.B. quest'ultima oggi difficilmente reperibile !!), oggi facilmente reperibili, ma in passato di più difficile reperibilità. In altre parole, dopo circa 30 anni il .30-378 Weatherby Magnum è uscito dal dimenticatoio ed ha potuto essere apprezzato ed utilizzato. 
Come tutti i calibri ideati da R. Weatherby, anche le armi camerate per questa cartuccia sono caratterizzate dal fatto di possedere una camera con :
- una gola (throat) particolarmente lasca
- un inizio di rigatura (free bore) estremamente lungo
Questo insieme di particolari costruttivi deriva dalla precisa volontà del produttore di tenere le pressioni di esercizio il più basse possibili durante l'uso a qualsiasi condizione ambientale. 

(https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/fucili/30-378.html)
</IT>
<EN>
The .30-378 Weatherby Magnum is a .30 caliber, belted, bottle-necked rifle cartridge. The cartridge was developed in response to a US Army military contract in 1959. While still unreleased to the public, the cartridge went on to set world records for accuracy including the first ten 10X in 1,000 yards (910 m) benchrest shooting. It is currently the highest velocity .30 caliber factory ammunition available. 
The .30-378 was originally designed by Roy Weatherby as an anti-personnel/anti-materiel military cartridge for a government contract. The cartridge was created by necking down the .378 Weatherby Magnum to accept a .308 in (7.8 mm) diameter bullet. The United States Army’s Redstone Arsenal requested a rifle cartridge that could develop 6,000 ft/s (1,800 m/s) for the effects of light bullets against armor. The .30-378 Weatherby Magnum was able to attain over 5,000 ft/s (1,500 m/s). Using a slower burning and denser propellant, the .30-378 Weatherby Magnum surpassed the US Army’s requirement of 6,000 ft/s (1,800 m/s).
However, the shooting public had to wait until 1996 for Weatherby to release the cartridge. In the meantime, the .30-378 Weatherby Magnum had gone on to set world records in 1,000 yards (910 m) benchrest competitions. Earl Chronister, shooting a .30-378 Weatherby Magnum shot the first ever ten shot 10X with the first nine shot to 3.125 inches and the tenth flyer for an overall group of 4.375 inches. This record stood for over 30 years. Several variations of the .30-378 Weatherby Magnum were created by custom ammunition manufacturers, known as wildcatters. Hammond rifles and H-S Precision were among the several custom gun manufacturers who chambered and built rifles long before Weatherby got around to releasing the rifle to the public.
In 1991 Shooting Times editor Layne Simpson met with Ed Weatherby, the son of Weatherby Inc. founder Roy Weatherby, and urged him to release the .30-378 Weatherby to the public as a standard chambering in the Mark V action. In 1995 Layne Simpson built a rifle chambered for the .30-378 Weatherby and developed loading data and passed the data on to Norma Precision to provide a basis for their factory loaded ammunition. 

The .30-378 Weatherby Magnum is one of the most accurate rifle cartridges. The cartridge held the world record for accuracy at 1,000 yards (910 m) for over thirty years. Given factory ammunition, Weatherby guarantees 1.5 MOA accuracy from their Weatherby Mark V action rifles and sub-MOA (.99 MOA or better) accuracy from their Range Certified line of rifles and Vanguard rifle lines. Careful handloading – checking for bullet jacket concentricity, weighing of brass and bullets, uniformity of case length and overall cartridge length, choice of components, seating of bullet – can all increase the accuracy of the cartridge.
The .30-378 Weatherby Magnum is a long range cartridge. It is the most powerful - in terms of energy - .30 caliber production cartridge available. It is also the flattest-shooting .30 caliber factory ammunition available. Dependent on the ammunition chosen the cartridge has a maximum point blank range of over 400 yd (370 m). The cartridge retains enough energy for deer-sized game at distances over 1,000 yd (910 m), and has enough retained energy for elk and moose-sized game at a distance of over 700 yd (640 m). 

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.30-378_Weatherby_Magnum)
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>