<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro .30-40 Krag-Jorgensen (N.B. questa cartuccia è nota, in alcune fonti bibliografiche, con alcuni  sinonimi quali .30 - 40 Krag, 7,62x59R, .30 - 40 Krag - Jorgenson, .30 - 40 Krag danese, .30 - 40 Krag  americano M-1896, .30 USA, .30 Army oppure .30 - 40 Krag americano M-1898) è una munizione di origine europea che è diventata famosa poichè è stata la PRIMA munizione caricata con polvere infume (smokeless powder) ad essere adottata dalle FFAA americane (N.B. più precisamente venne adottata dall'Esercito nel 1899, mentre NON venne mai adottata dalla Marina). L'adozione risale al 1892, inizialmente con il fucile originale di provenienza europea 
(N.B. si tratta del famoso fucile Krag - Jorgensen progettato da O. Krag ed E. Jorgensen della Regia Fabbrica d'Armi di Kongesdert, in Norvegia, un'arma originariamente camerata per il 6,5x55mm e nota tra i collezionisti per la presenza di un INUSUALE caricatore posizionato lateralmente e non, come accadeva di solito, in posizione verticale !!). Nel frattempo, l'arsenale di Springfield approntò due fucili noti nelle fonti bibliografiche come Modello 1896 e Modello1898, che non erano altro che delle versioni americane dell'arma originale che camerava il .30 - 40 Krag. La munizione impiegata dall'esercito USA era strutturata su di una palla completamente blindata da 220grs. (circa 14,3 GRAMMI) lanciata a circa 670m/s. 
Le successive evoluzioni tecnologiche nel campo degli esplosivi e delle munizioni per armi portatili decretarono in BREVE tempo il SUPERAMENTO del .30 - 40 Krag e la sua sostituzione prima con la cartuccia sperimentale calibro .30 - 03 (N.B. è l'antenato dell'attuale .30-06 Springfield !!) e, successivamente, con il .30-06 Springfield (V. voce a se). Nonstante il destino avverso, il .30 - 40 Krag goda ancora oggi di una notevole diffusione tra gli appssionati delle armi ex-ordinanza. Il motivo va ricercato nel fatto che secondo molti collezionisti, questa arma avrebbe "...l'azione più fluida del mondo...". Questa sua caratteristica dipende dal fatto che l'otturatore possiede una sola aletta di chiusura (locking lug), cosa che secondo alcuni collezionisti sarebbe positiva

(https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/fucili/30-40.html)
</IT>
<EN>
The .30-40 Krag (also called .30 U.S., or .30 Army) was a cartridge developed in the early 1890s to provide the U.S. armed forces with a smokeless powder cartridge suited for use with modern small-bore repeating rifles to be selected in the 1892 small arm trials. Since the cartridge it was replacing was the .45-70 Government, the round was considered small-bore at the time. The design selected was ultimately the Krag–Jørgensen, formally adopted as the M1892 Springfield. It was also used in M1893 and later Gatling guns. 
Though the U.S. Navy and Marine Corps had adopted limited numbers of smokeless powder and bolt-action rifles, the .30-40 was the first cartridge adopted by the US Army that was designed from the outset for smokeless powder. After a brief experiment with a 230-grain bullet loading, the .30 Army loading was standardized in 1894 using a 220-grain (14 g) metal-jacketed round-nose bullet with 40 gr (2.6 g) of nitrocellulose powder. This loading developed a maximum velocity of 2,000 ft/s (610 m/s) in the 30-inch (760 mm) barrel of the Krag rifle, and 1,960 ft/s (600 m/s) in the 22-inch (560 mm) barrel of the Krag carbine.
The rimmed .30-40 round was also known as .30 Army, or .30 U.S. Although the .30-40 Krag was the first smokeless powder round adopted by the U.S. military, it retained the "caliber-charge" naming system of earlier black powder cartridges, i.e. a .30-caliber bullet propelled by 40 grains (2.6 g) of smokeless powder. The first use of a smokeless powder round by Winchester was a single shot in 30-40, and it was one of only three rounds for which the 1895 Winchester lever action, introduced in 1896, was originally chambered.
From the outset, the .30-40 cartridge proved popular for hunting, and was chambered in a variety of firearms. In 1899, a Krag in .30-40 caliber was used to shoot the world-record Rocky Mountain elk. The record stood until the latter half of the 20th century.
In October 1899, after reviewing the experiences of the Spanish–American War, U.S. Army ordnance authorities developed a new loading for the .30 Army used in the Krag rifle, in an attempt to match the ballistics of the 7×57mm Mauser cartridge employed by Spanish forces in that conflict. The new loading increased the muzzle velocity in the rifle version of the Krag to 2,200 ft/s (670 m/s) at 45,000 psi. However, once the new loading was issued, reports of cracked locking lugs on service Krags began to surface. In March 1900 the remaining stocks of this ammunition (some 3.5 million rounds) were returned to the arsenals, broken down, and reloaded back to the original 2,000 ft/s (610 m/s) specification.
In 1903, after recommendations from the infantry Small Arms Board, the U.S. Army formally adopted a higher-velocity .30-caliber replacement for the .30-40 or .30 Army cartridge. The new cartridge was designated by its year of adoption, the .30-03. 

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.30-40_Krag)
</EN>
<DE>
Die .30-40 Krag-Gewehrpatrone, offizielle Bezeichnung in der U.S. Armee, Cartridge, ball, caliber .30, Model 1898, wurde 1892 gleichzeitig mit dem U.S. Model 1892 Krag-Jørgensen Gewehr, dem Nachfolger des Springfield Model 1873-Gewehres und seiner nachfolgenden Varianten, als Ordonnanzpatrone für die US-Armee entwickelt.
Der Vorgänger der .30-40 Krag Patrone war die seit 1873 von der US-Armee als Ordonnanzpatrone im Springfield Model 1873 verwendete .45-70 Government Schwarzpulverpatrone. Die .30-40 Krag war die erste moderne kleinkalibrige Munition mit rauchlosem Pulver der amerikanischen Armee. Allerdings war sie wegen neuen Anforderungen an Militärpatronen relativ kurzlebig und wurde nur zwischen 1894 und 1903 im Spanisch-Amerikanischen Krieg und dem Philippinisch-Amerikanischen Krieg verwendet. Später wurde sie nur noch bis zum Rückzug der durch das modernere Springfield M1903 abgelösten Krag-Gewehre verwendet; eine weitere Verwendung fand sie bei einigen Staatsmilizen.
Von der US-Armee wurden um die Jahrhundertwende folgende Maschinengewehre im Kaliber .30-40 Krag eingesetzt:
    das mehrläufige Gatling-Maschinengewehr Colt Gatling Gun Model 1893
    das Colt-Browning Model 1895 Machine Gun, ein als Gasdrucklader konzipiertes Maschinengewehr.
Einer der bekanntesten Einsätze des Krag-Karabiners und seiner .30-40 Munition war die Erstürmung des San Juan Hills in Kuba durch die Rough Riders unter dem Kommando von Teddy Roosevelt im Spanisch-Amerikanischen Krieg. Der Sturm war auch deshalb erfolgreich, weil er durch das Feuer aus drei vom 1st Lieutenant John "Machine Gun" Parker kommandierten Gatling Guns, cal .30-40 unterstützt wurde.
Der Großteil der .30-40 Krag Munition für die Armee wurde vom staatlichen Frankford Arsenal in der Nähe von Philadelphia, PA am Fluss namens Frankford Creek hergestellt. Diese Patronen sind am Boden mit den Buchstaben F und A sowie mit dem Herstellungsdatum (Monat, Jahr) gestempelt. 

Die .30-40 Krag ist eine Zentralfeuerpatrone mit einer Flaschenhalshülse mit Rand. Die Zahl .30 bezeichnet das ungefähre Kaliber in Zoll (inch), die Zahl 40 beschreibt das Pulvergewichts in der Maßeinheit Grain und bezieht sich auf die Pulverladung mit modernem weil sogenanntem rauchlosen Nitrocellulose- (NC-) Pulver. Für die Armee wurden Vollmantel-Rundgeschosse mit einem Gewicht von 220 Grains entsprechend 14,3 g eingesetzt. Private Hersteller wie Winchester, Remington Arms und andere stellten für den zivilen Gebrauch Jagd- und Sportpatronen mit Voll- und Teilmantel- sowie Hohlspitzgeschossen her.
Ballistische Daten von Winchester Western Cartridges ca. 1960:

    Geschossgewicht 180 Grains, 12 g, Mündungsgeschwindigkeit: 2.470 ft/s, 753 m/s, Mündungsenergie 3.308 J
    Geschossgewicht 220 Grains,14,3 g, Mündungsgeschwindigkeit: 2.200 ft/s, 671 m/s, Mündungsenergie 3.200 J

(https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.30-40_Krag)
</DE>
<ES>
El .30-40 Krag (también llamado .30 U.S., o .30 Army) era un cartucho desarrollado a inicios de la década de 1890 para dotar a las Fuerzas Armadas estadounidenses con un cartucho de pólvora sin humo adecuado para usarse en los fusiles de repetición de pequeño calibre que serían seleccionados en las pruebas de armas ligeras de 1892. Como el cartucho que reemplazaba era el .45-70 Government, el .30-40 Krag fue considerado "de pequeño calibre" en aquel entonces. El modelo de fusil que finalmente se eligió fue el Krag–Jørgensen, formalmente adoptado como el Springfield Modelo 1892. 
Aunque la Armada de los Estados Unidos y el Cuerpo de Marines de los Estados Unidos habían adoptado cantidades limitadas de fusiles de cerrojo que empleaban cartuchos con pólvora sin humo, el .30-40 Krag fue el primer cartucho diseñado desde el inicio para usar pólvora sin humo en ser adoptado por el Ejército de Estados Unidos. Luego de un breve experimento con una bala de 14,9 g (230 granos), la bala del .30 Army fue estandarizada en 1894 con una bala encamisada de punta redonda y 14,2 g (220 granos), que era propulsada por una carga de 2,5 g (40 granos) de nitrocelulosa. Esta carga propulsora desarrollaba una velocidad máxima de 610 m/s en el cañón de 760 mm de largo del fusil Krag, y de 600 m/s en el cañón de 560 mm de la carabina Krag. 
A pesar que el .30-40 Krag fue el primer cartcuho con pólvora sin humo en ser adoptado por el Ejército estadounidense, conservaba la nomenclatura "calibre-carga" de los primeros cartuchos con pólvora negra, o sea una bala de 7,62 mm (.30), propulsada por una carga de 2,6 g (40 granos) de pólvora sin humo. La Winchester utilizó por primera vez el .30-40 Krag en un fusil monotiro, además de ser uno de los tres cartuchos que utilizaba el fusil de palanca Winchester Modelo 1895, introducido en 1896.
Desde el inicio, el .30-40 Krag demostró ser un cartucho popular para cacería, siendo empleado en una variedad de armas. En 1899, un fusil Krag que utilizaba este cartucho fue empleado para abatir al uapití récord de las Montañas Rocosas. El récord se mantuvo hasta finales de la segunda mitad del siglo XX.
En octubre de 1899, después de revisar las experiencias de la Guerra hispano-estadounidense, los oficiales de maestranza del Ejército estadounidense desarrollaron una nueva carga propulsora para el .30 Army en un intento de igualar las características del cartucho 7 x 57 Mauser. La nueva carga incrementó la velocidad de boca del fusil a 670 m/s con una presión de 45.000 psi. Sin embargo, una vez que el nuevo cartucho fue suministrado, empezaron a surgir reportes sobre rajaduras en los tetones de acerrojado de los cerrojos de los Krag en servicio. En marzo de 1900, los lotes restantes de este cartucho, unos 3,5 millones, fueron devueltos a los arsenales, se los desensambló y se los volvió a recargar con la anterior carga propulsora de 610 m/s.
En 1903, tras las recomendaciones del Comité de Armas Ligeras de Infantería, el Ejército estadounidense adoptó formalmente un cartucho de calibre 7,62 mm y alta velocidad que reemplazaría al .30-40 Krag o .30 Army. El nuevo cartucho .30-03 Springfield fue designado por su año de adopción. 

(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.30-40_Krag)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>