<loc>

<DE>
Die Patrone .300 Remington Ultra Magnum ist eine leistungsstarke und sehr präzise Patrone für Büchsen. Im zivilen Bereich wird sie hauptsächlich bei der Jagd eingesetzt. Im deutschen Nationalen Waffenregister (NWR) wird die Patrone unter Katalognummer 2073 unter der Bezeichnung .300 RUM (ohne Synonyme) geführt.
Remington führte die Patrone 1999 ein. Die .300 Remington Ultra Magnum basiert auf der .404 Jeffrey-Hülse und kommt ohne Gürtel aus. Durch die steile Hülsenschulter und eine fast zylindrische Form konnte das Volumen für das Treibladungspulver vergrößert werden, was der Rasanz der Patrone zugutekam.


(https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.300_Remington_Ultra_Mag)
</DE>
<EN>

The .300 Remington Ultra Magnum, also known as the .300 Ultra Mag, 7.62×72mm or .300 RUM is a 7.62 mm (.308 inch) rifle cartridge introduced by Remington Arms in 1999. The .300 Remington Ultra Magnum is one of the largest commercially available .30 caliber magnums currently being produced. It is a beltless, rebated rim cartridge, capable of handling all large North American game, as well as long-range shooting. Among commercially produced .30-caliber rifle chamberings, the .300 Remington Ultra Magnum is second only to the .30-378 Weatherby Magnum in cartridge-case capacity.
In the early 1980s Aubrey White and Noburo Uno of North American Shooting Systems (NASS) based in British Columbia Canada began experimenting with the full length .404 Jeffery by reducing the taper and necking it down to various calibers such as 7 mm, .308, 311, 338, 9.3 mm and .375. These cartridges were known variously as the Canadian Magnum or the Imperial Magnums. Rifles were built on Remington Model 700 Long Actions and used McMillan stocks. Cartridges were fire formed from .404 Jeffery cases with the rim turned down, taper reduced and featured sharp shoulders.
Both Remington and Dakota Arms purchased the brass designed by Noburo Uno for use in their own experimentation and cartridge development. In 1999 Remington released the first of a series of cartridges virtually identical to the Canadian Magnum cartridges which featured a slightly wider body, increased taper, and shallower shoulders and named it the .300 Remington Ultra Magnum. Dakota too released their own version of the cartridge but chose not to turn down the rim and shortened the case to work in a standard length action. Remington would go on to design their own shortened versions of the Ultra Magnum cartridge which they were to call the Remington Short Action Ultra Magnum or RSAUM for short.
The .300 Remington Ultra Magnum is a member of the Remington Ultra Magnum cartridge family based on the .404 Jeffery via the Canadian Magnum cartridges. As these cartridges feature wider bodies than the belted magnums based on the .375 H&amp;H case, these cartridges have greater case capacities than their corresponding full length belted Magnum cartridges such as the 7 mm Shooting Times Westerner, the .300 Weatherby Magnum, .340 Weatherby Magnum and the .375 Ackley Improved.
The .300 RUM features a rebated rim much like the .300 Canadian Magnum so as to allow the cartridge to function in the Remington M700 action without having to increase the bolt and bolt face diameter of the action. Unlike the belted Magnum cases based on the .375 H&amp;H Magnum cartridge, the .300 RUM does not have a belt. All things being equal, a beltless cartridge would feed more reliably and more smoothly than a belted cartridge. Furthermore, as this is a beltless cartridge headspacing is designed to take place on the shoulder, which is considered beneficial by some as it is thought to promote accuracy and prolong case life of the cartridge. As modern belted magnums such as 7mm Remington Magnum and .300 Winchester Magnum actually headspace on the shoulder despite retaining the belt found on their parent cartridge, belted or unbelted is basically irrelevant in discussions of modern cartridges, and particularly so in discussions of unbelted cartridges.
SAAMI recommends that the barrel have a 6 groove contour with a twist rate of one revolution in 10 in (250 mm). The barrel is to have a groove width of .115 in (2.9 mm). Bore is given as .300 in (7.6 mm) and a groove is .308 in (7.8 mm). Maximum case overflow capacity is 122.5 gr. of water (7.30 cm3). SAAMI recommended Maximum Average Pressure is set at 65,000 psi (4,500 bar).
Remington's ultra magnum cases were made wider than the .404 Jeffery case by .006 in (0.15 mm). The brass was made thicker so as to withstand the higher pressure of the new cartridge as the Jeffery cartridge had a maximum average pressure rating of 3,650 bar (52,900 psi).
Remington ammunition for the .300 RUM is available in three Power Levels. Power Level I duplicates the .30-06 Springfield, Power Level II that of the .300 Winchester Magnum and Power Level III is the full power load. Remington offers the full power (Power Level III) .300 Remington Ultra Magnum ammunition in 150 gr (9.7 g) at 3,450 ft/s (1,050 m/s), the 180 gr (12 g) at 3,250 ft/s (990 m/s) and the 200 gr (13 g) at 3,032 ft/s (924 m/s). These are among the highest velocities attained by a .30 caliber production rifle cartridge.
The .300 RUM is an excellent long range cartridge with the ability to deliver a useful level of energy downrange especially with the power level III ammunition. Due to its high velocity it exhibits less bullet drop than most other .30 caliber (7.62 mm) cartridges.
Compared to other production .30 caliber (7.62 mm) cartridges, only the .30-378 Weatherby Magnum surpasses the .300 Remington Ultra Magnum. Factory loaded .30-378 Weatherby Magnum ammunition has a 150–200 ft/s (46–61 m/s) velocity advantage over the .300 RUM cartridge with any given bullet weight. However, the .30-378 Weatherby Magnum is considered the most overbore production sporting cartridge available and is not considered as efficient as the .300 RUM cartridge.  In part due to its excessive freebore lengths the claimed velocities by Weatherby is a resultant factor of this freebore length.  If chambered to allow bullets to seat to the lands of the rifling the large Weatherby cartridges would exhibit overpressure signs immediately.  All things equal the .300 RUM and .30-378 Weatherby if chambered with the same throat and freebore would be comparable.  Known freebore lengths of older Weatherby rifles have been in excess of 1 inch.  The .30-378 is one of the most extreme cases of overbore and has among the highest throat erosion levels of any rifles.
The .300 Remington Ultra Magnum cartridge was conceived as a long range hunting cartridge and in this it exceeds most other cartridges. It is able to launch heavy bullets with high sectional densities at high velocities there by retaining energy to take game cleanly at longer ranges than less powerful cartridges such as the .30-06 Springfield and even the .300 Winchester Magnum.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.300_Remington_Ultra_Magnum)
</EN>
<ES>
El .300 Remington Ultra Magnum, abreviado .300 Ultra Mag, 7.62×72mm o .300 RUM es un cartucho metálico para rifle, calibre 7.62  mm (.308 pulgadas), que fue introducido por Remington Arms en 1999. El .300 Remington Ultra Magnum es uno de los .300 Magnums comerciales de mayor potencia, capaz de abatir a cualquier especie de caza mayor en Norte América. De todos los .300 Magnums disponibles, el .300 Remington Ultra Magnum, es el segundo más potente y de mayor capacidad de carga de pólvora, después del .30-378 Weatherby Magnum.
A inicios de los años 1980 Aubrey White y Noburo Uno, del NASS (North American Shooting Systems) en la Columbia Británica, en Canadá, empezaron a experimentar con el casquillo del .404 Jeffery reduciendo la longitud de carga y ajustando el cuello del casquillo para alojar diferentes calibres, como el 7 mm, .308, 311, 338, 9.3 mm y el .375.​ Estos cartuchos se conocieron como los Magnum Canadienses o Magnum Imperiales, y se recamararon con acciones largas del Remington Modelo 700 y culatas McMillan. 
Tanto Remington y Dakota Arms adquirieron los casquillos desarrollados por el equipo de NASS para experimentar y desarrollar sus propios cartuchos. En 1999 Remington introdujo su primera línea de cartuchos basados en estos Magnum Canadienses, a los que se les amplió la capacidad de carga ligeramente y se les pronunció el ángulo del hombro, nombrándolos Remington Ultra Magnum. Dakota también introdujo su versión propia, pero decidiendo rebajar la longitud del casquillo para que estos sean usados en mecanismos de longitud estándar. Remington por su parte desarrolló una versión corta a la que llamó Remington Short Action Ultra Magnum, abreviado RSAUM.
El .300 Remington Ultra Magnum es un miembro de la familia de cartuchos Remington Ultra Magnum, basados en el .404 Jeffery vía los Magnum Canadienses. que presentan un diámetro de cuerpo mayor que los belted magnums que parten del casquillo del .375 H&amp;H Mag, como el 7 mm Shooting Times Westerner, el .300 Weatherby Magnum, .340 Weatherby Magnum y el .375 Ackely Improved.
Los casquillos Remington Ultra Magnum son ligeramente más anchos que el .404 Jeffery  por .0,006 plg (0,2 mm) en (0.15 ). El latón es ligeramente más grueso para aguantar la presión más alta que genera el cartucho ya que  el Jeffery cartucho tuvo un índice de presión mediano máximo de 3,650 bar (52,900 psi ).
Remington comercializa tres niveles de carga de munición para el .300 RUM. El nivel 1 duplica al .30-06 Springfield, Nivel de Poder II replica al .300 Winchester Magnum y Nivel de Poder III es la carga de poder llena genera, con munición de 150 granos una velocidad de salida de 3,450 pies por segundo, con 180 granos una velocidad de 3,200 pies por segundo, el cual, centrado para impactar 3 pulgadas arriba del blanco a 100 yardas, logra una máxima trayectoria plana a las 300 yardas y cae solo 7 pulgadas abajo a 350 yardas. Con 200 granos logra una velocidad de 3032 pies por segundo.​ 
El .300 Remington Ultra Magnum se ha concebido para la caza mayor de animales de diferentes pesos, desde venados de cola blanca hasta alces y osos pardos, a largas distancias, siendo capaz de disparar balas pesadas de altas densidades seccionales  a velocidades altas y así abatir a las presas limpiamente a distancias mayores que cartuchos menos potentes como .30-06 Springfield. ​
 


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.300_Remington_Ultra_Magnum)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>