<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .303 Savage is a rimmed, .30 caliber rifle cartridge developed by the Savage Arms Company in 1894 which was designed as a short (as short as the .30-30 Winchester) action cartridge for their Savage Model 1895 later 1899 hammerless lever-action rifle. The cartridge was designed for smokeless powder at a time when black-powder cartridges were still popular. The .303 Savage round  was ballistically superior to the .30-30, but only marginally. The .303 Savage remained popular through the 1930s. Savage produced a half dozen loads for it. With its 190-grain loading, it was used on such animals as deer and moose.
The .303 Savage and the .303 British cartridge are not interchangeable with each other. Neither the bullet diameter nor the cartridge dimensions are compatible.
Savage Arms created the .303 Savage as part of an unsuccessful attempt at creating a cartridge for the military. Although the cartridge was never popular with the military, it did become a popular round for civilian hunters. Initially designed round-nosed but becoming a pointed-tip rimmed cartridge in early 1900s, it worked well in the Model 99 rifles that Savage produced because of their rotary magazine. It wasn't as successful in other lever-action rifles because only the round-nose loading were safe to use with their tubular magazines. However, the pointed-tip bullets gave it a ballistic advantage over other traditional lever-action cartridges such as the .30-30 Winchester.
The .303 Savage has a small, but loyal fraternity of shooters who reload this cartridge. While major ammunition manufacturers have long since halted production of ammo, dedicated followers can procure loaded ammunition and brass cases through smaller enterprises. The brass cases can be formed from .30-30 Winchester,  .32 Winchester Special,  and .38-55 Winchester casings, if no correct brass is available.  Great care must be taken as the Winchester brass is about .020” smaller at the base and case failure is possible. It is safer to obtain correct .303 Savage brass, which shows up occasionally in runs from Norma or Prvi Partizan.
Loads respond well to traditional loads in the same range as the .30-30 or .30 Remington. However, the slightly larger case volume, and stronger rifle action allow for loads that improve significantly over standard loads for the .30-30. It is quite possible to put 190 grain flat points at 2200fps as well as 160 grain FTX bullets at 2400 fps, even from 20” featherweight barrels.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.303_Savage)
</EN>
<ES>
El .303 Savage es un cartucho de fuego central para rifle calibre .30, anillado. Fue desarrollado por Savage Arms Company en 1894 para ser recamarado en su rifle de mecanismo de palanca sin martillo Savage Modelo 1895 posterior a 1899 . El cartucho fue diseñado para ser cargado con pólvora sin humo en un momento en que los cartuchos de pólvora negra todavía eran populares. El .303 Savage fue balísticamente superior a la .30-30 Winchester, pero solo marginalmente, y popular durante la década de 1930 ​ con una variedad de media docena de cargas comercializadas por Savage. Con su carga de 190 granos, era principalmente utilizado para la caza de venados y alces.
El .303 Savage y el  .303 British no son intercambiables entre sí. Ni el diámetro de la bala ni las dimensiones del cartucho son compatibles. ​
Savage Arms creó el .303 Savage como parte de un intento fallido de crear un cartucho para el ejército. Aunque el cartucho nunca fue popular entre los militares, se convirtió en una ronda popular para los cazadores civiles. Al ser un cartucho con borde de punta puntiaguda, funcionó bien en los rifles Modelo 99 que produjo Savage debido a su cargador giratorio. No tuvo tanto éxito en otros rifles de palanca debido a sus cargadores tubulares . Sin embargo, las balas de punta puntiaguda le dieron una ventaja balística sobre otros cartuchos tradicionales de acción de palanca como el .30-30 Winchester. ​


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.303_Savage)
</ES>
<FR>
Le calibre .300 Savage est une munition développée par Savage Arms en 1920 pour remplacer la .303 Savage . Malgré un étui court et un épaulement très prononcé, la cartouche est capable de propulser une balle de 165 grains à plus de 800 m/s (3558 J) avec une redoutable précision à plus de 300 m.
Ses dimensions proches de celles de la .308 Winchester et ses caractéristiques en ont fait une munition de choix pour la conversion des armes classées en première catégorie avant 2013. En effet, entre ces deux munitions la différence est au niveau de la douille. L'angle d'épaulement de la .300 Savage est plus grand, et le collet plus court : ceci fait que sa contenance jusqu'à la base du collet est plus faible de 0,07 gramme de poudre.
Le choix en poudre pour ce calibre est assez large.
Dans la gamme Vectan, on peut utiliser de la Tu3000 pour les balles de moins de 9 grammes (138 grains), à la Tu5000 pour les projectiles de 13 grammes (200 grains). Les Sp7 et Sp9 conviennent parfaitement, les doseuses volumétriques sont plus régulières avec ces poudres sphériques.
Les charges réduites, qu'elles soient pour un projectile plomb, un rechargement subsonique ou simplement pour simuler une cible plus lointaine, doivent être effectués de préférence avec la poudre A0.
Cette poudre s'enflamme très facilement avec une amorce standard, sans mettre de bourre pour tenir la charge contre l'amorce. La pression reste relativement faible par rapport aux charges normales. Le fonctionnement d'un semi-auto s'en trouve altéré.
En France, cette munition est classée en catégorie C 8°. Il est possible de transformer une douille de .308 Winchester en .300 Savage avec un jeu d'outils adapté mais peu de tireurs le font car les douilles de .300 Savage se trouvent facilement dans le commerce, alors que la douille du .308 Winchester est classé en catégorie C 7° (il faut une arme chambrée .308 Winchester pour en acheter).
En France, beaucoup d'armes chambrées d'origine en .308 Winchester ont été transformées en .300 Savage pour être plus accessibles.
Certaines anciennes armes de guerre, conçues à l'origine pour recevoir une douille plus large, ont été transformées au calibre .300 Savage pour échapper à la 1ère catégorie « armes et munitions de guerre » avant 2013. À la suite de cette modification, quelques incidents de tir, parfois graves, ont été enregistrés. Leur cause serait une usure et désolidarisation de la frette.
La 300 Savage est la munition utilisée par le tueur pour assassiner sa victime, maître chanteur, dans le roman d'Ed McBain de la série du 87e District Crédit Illimité (Killer's Payoff, 1958)


(https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.300_Savage)
</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>