<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro .30 R Blaser (N.B. in talune fonti bibliografiche questa cartuccia è nota, seppur più raramente, con la denominazione metrica di 7,62x68mm R) è un derivato parziale della cartuccia calibro .30-06 Springfield (V. voce a se), realizzato dalla tedesca RWS sul finire del XX secolo allo scopo di "...portare nuova linfa..." al settore delle munizioni per armi basculanti. In Germania, ed in tutti i Paesi dell'Europa centrale, è molto diffusa la caccia agli ungulati praticata con armi basculanti a canna rigata e per questo motivo la RWS pensò bene di  movimentare il mercato introducendo una cartuccia basata "...sul vecchio e sempre valido .30-06...", ma capace di prestazioni molto interessanti. 
La cartuccia originale venne proposta in due configurazioni basate rispettivamente su una palla di tipo KS (N.B. un tipo di palla a punta conica / appuntita prodotta esclusivamente dalla RWS) ed una di tipo TUG (N.B. un tipo di palla con ogiva affusolata e base rastremata creata da W. Brenneke e prodotta dalla RWS) da 150 (9,7 GRAMMI) e 180 grs.(11,7 GRAMMI), ed era in grado di sviluppare velocità di 20 - 30m/s superiori. rispetto a quelle del .30-06 Springfield .

(https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/fucili/30RB.html)
</IT>
<EN>
The .30 R Blaser (7.62×68mm R) is a rimmed bottlenecked centerfire cartridge developed for hunting in 1991 by Gerhard Blenk, the then owner of Blaser Jagdwaffen GmbH and Dynamit Nobel which then owned RWS ammunition. 
The cartridge is a de novo design and was constructed to outperform popular hunting cartridges like the .30-06 Springfield and 7.92×57mm Mauser. When compared with the .30-06 Springfield the .30 R Blaser features an equal maximum chamber pressure of 405 MPa (58,740 psi) piezo pressure - which is fairly high for a rimmed rifle cartridge - but more cartridge case capacity, allowing the use of more propellant. The .30 R Blaser performance does however not reach the power level of .30 caliber magnum cartridges like the .300 Winchester Magnum that feature more cartridge case capacity and higher maximum chamber pressure levels.
As a rimmed cartridge the .30 R Blaser is designed for use in break action rifles such as double rifles and combination guns as well as for single shot rifles such as the falling block action rifles. Break action rifles using rimless .30 caliber chamberings like .308 Winchester or .30-06 Springfield can be fairly easy rechambered for the .30 R Blaser.[citation needed]
The cartridge was commercially introduced in 1992 by Blaser Jagdwaffen (Blaser hunting weapons) and RWS ammunition. As of 2009, RWS is its only manufacturer.

The versatility of the .30 R Blaser for hunting all kinds of American and European game and the availability of several factory loads and the fact that it uses standard .30 caliber projectiles all attribute to the .30 R Blaser chambering popularity in break action hunting rifles. Loaded with short light bullets it can be used on small European game like fox or medium game such as roe deer and chamois. Loaded with longer heavy bullets it can be used on medium and big European game like wild boar, fallow deer, red deer, moose and brown bear. The .30 R Blaser offers good penetrating ability due to a fast enough twist rate to enable it to fire relatively long, heavy bullets with a high sectional density. The (former) legal banning of (ex) military service cartridges in countries like Belgium, Italy and France, makes that the .30 R Blaser can be used for hunting in such jurisdictions.

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.30_R_Blaser)
</EN>
<DE>
Die .30 R Blaser ist eine von den Firmen Blaser und RWS 1991 gemeinsam entwickelte Randpatrone für Kipplaufbüchsen, die für den Abschuss von Schalenwild, beispielsweise Wildschweinen, geeignet ist.Sie hat die Maße 7,62 × 68 mm R und ist ein in Deutschland geführtes Kaliber. 

(https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.30_R_Blaser)
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>