<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .318 Westley Richards, also known as the .318 Rimless Nitro Express and the .318 Accelerated Express, is a proprietary medium bore centerfire rifle cartridge developed by Westley Richards.
Westley Richards introduced the .318, primarily for use in their M98 Mauser and later their P14 Enfield based bolt action sporting rifles.
The .318 Westley Richards is a rimless bottlenecked cartridge primarily intended for use in Africa.  The bullet diameter is actually .330", the naming is due to British nomenclature which sometimes names cartridges by their land diameter rather than the more commonly applied groove diameter.
Westley Richards offered solid, soft-point or the revolutionary LT-capped[note 1] bullets in two loadings, the more common being a 250 gr (16 g) bullet with a listed speed of 2,400 ft/s (730 m/s), whilst a lighter loading firing a 180 gr (12 g) bullet at 2,700 ft/s (820 m/s) was also offered for lighter game.  The 250gr bullet possessed high sectional density and thus excellent penetration.
In 1907 British authorities banned military-calibre sporting and hunting rifles in India and Sudan, including ones chambered in .375/303 Westley Richards Accelerated Express. That necessitated to develop an analog in another bore.
Even though most sources state the .318 Westley Richards was introduced in 1910, in fact a Westley Richards catalogue contains a testimonial from a satisfied customer dated March 1909 who used his rifle to take 10 elephants, indicating the cartridge must have been introduced by at least 1908.  Upon the introduction of the .318 Westley Richards, Westley Richards effectively stopped marketing their .375/303.
The .318 Westley Richards was one of the most popular medium-bore cartridges used in Africa, even after the introduction of the .375 Holland &amp; Holland. As with many British proprietary cartridges, the .318 Westley Richards was forced into obsolescence when Kynoch suspended ammunition manufacturing in the 1960s. Kynamco resumed manufacture of the Kynoch range of cartridges in the 1990s meaning the ammunition is again commercially available, although no firearms manufacturers make factory rifles in .318 Westley Richards today with the exception of Westley Richards themselves..
While the cartridge is not intended for dangerous game, it has been used successfully on all African game species up to and including elephant.  The cartridge was a contemporary of and very similar in performance to the .333 Jeffery, both were somewhat overshadowed by the arrival of the .375 Holland &amp; Holland.
In his African Rifles and Cartridges, John "Pondoro" Taylor wrote that the 250gr .318 Westley Richards is "fully capable of driving its bullet the full length of a big elephant's body."
W.D.M. "Karamojo" Bell wrote that the .318 Westley Richards was a more reliable killer for certain shots on bull elephant than his favoured .275, (7mm Mauser) but that he had trouble with misfires with the sporting .318 ammunition. By 1913 he had adopted the .318 in preference to his .275 Rigby-Mauser rifle. On one occasion Bell used a pair of .318 Westley Richards rifles to take nine elephants with nine shots, he later wrote "In my opinion, the 250gr .318, although far from perfect, approaches most nearly the big game hunter's ideal bullet".
James H. Sutherland, who over the course of his life shot between 1,300 and 1,600 elephants, used a .318 Westley Richards along with a .577 Nitro Express double rifle for all his African hunting, in a letter to Westley Richards he wrote "In open country, against Elephants and Rhinoceroses where the quarry is difficult to approach and long shots are often required I find that I can do all that is requisite with the .318 using of course, solid nickel covered bullets."
Bror Blixen once states that if he could only have one rifle with which to hunt it would be the .318 Westly Richards.
Other users of the .318 Westley Richards include Major G.H. Anderson who shot between 350 and 400 elephants; and Quentin Grogan who shot between 250 and 300 elephants.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.318_Westley_Richards)
</EN>
<ES>
 El .318 Westley Richards, conocido también como el .318 Rimless Nitro Express o .318 Accelerted Express, es un cartucho de fuego central para rifle de cerrojo, desarrollado por Westley Richards.
Westley Richards Introdujo el .318 para ser usado en el mecanismo Mauser 98 con el que comúnmente ensamblan sus rifles hasta el día de hoy; así como en el mecanimso Enfield Pattern 1914 también usado para sus rifles deportivos.
El .318 Westley Richards es un cartucho desarrollado principalmente con el objetivo de ser usado en África. Su diseño es en forma de botella y sin anillo. La bala es de .330" de diámetro, pero debido a la nomenclatura Británica que determina el calibre en función al diámetro más angosto de las estrías del cañón, es que se le define como .318
Westley Richards introdujo el cartucho al mercado ofreciendo alternativas de balas sólidas, de punta blanda y el revolucionario "LT-capped" con dos cargas, siendo las más comunes de 250 granos (16 g) que alcanza una velocidad de salida de 2,400 pies por segundo (730 m/s), y  un proyectil más ligero de 180 granos (12 g), con una velocidad de salida de 2,700 pies por segundo (820 m/s) aplicable a la caza de antílopes ligeros.  La bala de 250 granos ofrece una alta densidad seccional que, complmentada con un proyectil de construcción sólida, confiere una excelente penetración.
Diversas fuentes señalan que el .318 Westley Richards fue introducido en 1910, aunque un catálogo de Westley Richards refiere que se utilizó en 1909 para abatir 10 elefantes, lo que indica que el cartucho puede haber sido introducido por al menos en 1908.
El .318 Westley Richards fue uno de los cartuchos de calibre medio más populares usados en África, incluso la introducción del .375 Holland &amp; Holland no le restó popularidad.  Al igual que con muchos cartuchos metálicos británicos, el .318 Westley Richards quedó obsoleto cuando Kynoch suspendió la fabricación de munición en la década de 1960. 
Kynamco reanudó la fabricación de la gama de cartuchos Kynoch en la década de 1990, lo que significa que la munición vuelve a estar disponible comercialmente, aunque hoy en día ningún fabricante de armas de fuego fabrica rifles de fábrica en .318 Westley Richards.
Si bien el .318 Westley Richards no fue desarrollado para la caza de animales peligrosos, este ha sido usado exitosamente para cazar todo tipo de animales africanos, incluyendo elefantes.  Es contemporáneo y balísticamente muy similar al .333 Jeffery.
En su libro African Rifles and Cartridges, John "Pondoro" Taylor escribió que el r .318 Westley Richards con proyectiles de 250 granos es "plenamente capaz de atravesar completamente el cuerpo de un elefante."
W.D.M. "Karamojo" Bell escribió que el .318 Westley Richards más fiable para tiros a ciertos ángulos, que su .275 Rigby, el cual era un "rifle" para "tiros quirúrgicos". En una ocasión, Bell usó un par de rifles .318 Westley Richards para cazar nueve elefantes con nueve tiros, escribiendo después "En mi opinión, .318, con .250 granos, lejos de ser perfecto, es casi la bala ideal del cazador africano".
James H. Sutherland, quién sobre el curso de su vida cazó entre 1,300 y 1,600 elefantes, se limitó a usar solo un .318 Westley Richards junto con un .577 Nitro Express. En una carta dirigida a Westley Richards  escribió  "En campo abierto, para elefantes y rinocerontes, donde la acercarse es difícil y los tiros largos son comunes, encuentro que  que puedo usar perfectamente el .318 utilizando naturalmente, con balas niqueladas."
Otros cazadores que usaron extensivamente el .318 Westley Richards incluyen al comandante GH Anderson, quién cazó entre 350 y 400 elefantes; y Quentin Grogan que disparó entre 250 y 300 elefantes. 
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> con nombre «Barnes» no se utiliza en el texto anterior.
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> con nombre «Clode» no se utiliza en el texto anterior.
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> con nombre «Davie» no se utiliza en el texto anterior.
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> con nombre «Passmore» no se utiliza en el texto anterior.
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> con nombre «Roberts» no se utiliza en el texto anterior.
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> con nombre «Taylor» no se utiliza en el texto anterior.
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> con nombre «Trigger» no se utiliza en el texto anterior.


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.318_Westley_Richards)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>