<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .325 Winchester Short Magnum, commonly known as the 325 WSM is an 8mm caliber rebated rim bottlenecked centerfire short magnum medium bore cartridge.   The cartridge was introduced by Winchester Ammunition in 2005.
Introduced at the 2005 Shot Show in Las Vegas, NV, it is the largest member of the Winchester Short Magnum family of cartridges. The .325 WSM was intended for the hunting of medium and large bodied thin skinned dangerous and non-dangerous big game animals of Africa, Asia, Europe and North America.
Since the introduction of the .300 WSM in 2000 there had been speculation that Winchester and Browning would release further cartridges based on the cartridge case of the .300 WSM.  Then in 2001 Winchester announced the release of the .270 WSM and the 7mm WSM cartridges.  The common wisdom indicated that Winchester would release a .33 caliber (8.38 mm) cartridge based on the .300 WSM case.  However, Winchester surprised the shooting public in 2002 when they introduced the .223 WSSM and the .243 WSSM based on a further shortened WSM case followed by the .25 WSSM in 2003.
The introduction of the .325 WSM in 2005 took the shooting public by surprise, as the 8mm caliber did not have a following in North America.  Earlier introductions of 8mm cartridges in North America were met with failure, as the .30 caliber (7.62 mm) was generally considered the caliber of choice among American hunters.
When introduced, Winchester offered the cartridge loaded with a 180 gr (12 g) Ballistic Silvertip at 3,060 ft/s (930 m/s) (SBST325S), a 200 gr (13 g) Combined Technologies Accubond at 2,950 ft/s (900 m/s) (S325WSMCT), and a  220 gr (14 g) Power-Point at 2,840 ft/s (870 m/s) (X325WSM).
The .325 WSM uses the .300 WSM case necked up to accept the 8mm bullet. The cartridge was influenced by the .404 Jeffery and contemporary cartridge designs calling for a short, fat cartridge operating at high pressures which could be cycled through a short action rifle. The understanding was that such cartridges would provide greater efficiency and uniformity in burning the powder charge which in turn would promote a greater inherent accuracy of the cartridge.  The rebated rim design allows for the cartridge to utilize actions chambered for rifles based on the .375 Holland &amp; Holland bolt face diameter.
The WSM case was designed to be loaded with .30 caliber (7.62mm) bullets. An aspect of the short, fat cartridge design is that it has a narrower acceptable caliber range than a longer cartridge case. It was for this reason that Winchester introduced the WSSM cartridge case to load sub .27 caliber (6.8mm) bullets.  During the testing phase, Winchester had found that, when loaded with .33 caliber bullets, the WSM resulted in the loss of performance and settled for the 8mm caliber instead.  Winchester determined that the .32 caliber was the largest caliber that provided a “magnum” level of performance in the WSM case.
The .325 Winchester Short Magnum has 5.39 ml (83 grain) H2O cartridge case capacity.

.325 Winchester Short Magnum maximum C.I.P. cartridge dimensions. All sizes in millimetres (mm).
Americans would define the shoulder angle at alpha/2 ≈ 35 degrees. The common rifling twist rate for this cartridge is 254 mm (1 in 10 in), 4 grooves, Ø of the lands = 8.00 mm, Ø grooves = 8.20 mm, land width = 4.47 mm and the primer type is large rifle.
According to the official C.I.P. (Commission Internationale Permanente pour l'Epreuve des Armes à Feu Portatives) rulings the .325 Winchester Short Magnum can handle up to 435 MPa (63,091 psi) piezo pressure. In C.I.P. regulated countries every rifle cartridge combo has to be proofed at 125% of this maximum C.I.P. pressure to certify for sale to consumers.
The .325 Winchester Short Magnum is a Delta L problem cartridge, meaning it can present unexpected chambering and/or feeding problems. The Delta L problem article explains this problem in more detail.
The German 8×68mm S cartridge introduced in 1939 is probably the closest ballistic twin of the .325 Winchester Short Magnum. The .325 Winchester Short Magnum is considerably shorter and fatter and has a more radical rebated rim, much steeper shoulder angle and a shorter neck (7.82 mm) than the 8×68mm S. This makes the 8×68mm S case with its 9.11 mm long neck better suited for loading long heavier bullets and due to its sleeker exterior shape bound to cycle more reliably in bolt-action rifles in extreme situations. On the other hand, the proportions of .325 Winchester Short Magnum promote good internal ballistic efficiency that allows the .325 Winchester Short Magnum to fire shorter lighter bullets at slightly higher muzzle velocities whilst using less propellant than the classically proportioned 8×68mm S.
The .325 WSM is an efficient, flat shooting 8mm magnum rifle cartridge. Bullet weights range from 125 to 250 gr (8.1 to 16.2 g).  Performance is on par with the two other magnum cartridges: 8mm Remington Magnum and the German 8×68mmS cartridge with lighter weight bullets.  However, these later two cartridges have a distinct edge of being able to seat long heavy 220 gr (14 g) bullets without encroaching upon the powder space.  Due to the necessity of seating heavier longer bullets more deeply into the powder column due to the short design and maximum overall length of the .325 WSM cartridge, velocity drops off as bullet weight increases. This is particularly evident with mono-metal bullets such as Nosler's E-Tip bullets, and the Barnes X bullets.  These bullets are constructed of copper, which is about 20% less density than that of a conventional lead bullet.  The resulting mono-metal bullets are typically longer, which requires these bullets to be seated more deeply to meet standards set for the cartridge and allow reliable feeding and cycling of the cartridges in rifles.
Maximum muzzle velocity comparison in % of the probably most proliferated European and American 8 mm rifle cartridges out of 650 mm (25.59 in) long barrels loaded with relatively light to heavy 8 mm bullets to their C.I.P. or SAAMI (Sporting Arms and Ammunition Manufacturers’ Institute) sanctioned maximum pressures.
This comparison is not totally objective since the 8mm Remington Magnum and .325 WSM operate at 448.16 MPa (65000 psi), the 8×68mm S at 440 MPa (63817 psi), the 8×64mm S at 405 MPa (58740 psi) and the 7.92×57mm Mauser at 390 MPa (56564 psi) maximum chamber pressure. Higher chamber pressure results in higher muzzle velocities.
The .325 WSM should be considered primarily a hunting or sporting cartridge. It was intended to take medium and large bodied, dangerous thin skinned game up to 1,800 pounds (816 kg).  Bullets of 180 gr or less are intended for smaller deer species such as white tail and mule deer, while those of 200 gr or more are intended for elk, moose and large bear.  The .325 WSM being an 8mm cartridge could find favor among European hunters for elk (European moose), wild boar as its performance is similar to the vaunted 8×68mm S cartridge.  The cartridge is useful for all including the largest bear species.  Most outfitters recommend at least a .30 to .375 calibre magnum class cartridge (depending on the hunters recoil threshold) for the larger bear species such as the Alaskan brown bear and the polar bear.  Due to the flat shooting and long range performance of the .325 WSM it is also a top performer for most African plains game such as kudu, nyala, wildebeest and zebra.
The .325 WSM has not made inroads in competitive shooting sports or military use. However, on the contrary to what some competitive shooters and sportsman believe, and as mentioned above, for reloaders there are quite an array of bullet sizes and shapes to choose from. Bullet weights from 125 gr to 250 gr are offered by premium bullet makers such as Nosler, Sierra, Barnes, Woodleigh, Swift, Hornady and other major manufactures.
Winchester Ammunition's release of the .325 WSM was in conjunction with the release by FN Herstal of rifles chambered in the cartridge under the Browning and Winchester brand names.  Originally, Winchester released the Ultimate Shadow, Camo Ultimate Shadow, Classic Featherweight, Classic Laminated, Super Grade RMEF (Rocky Mountain Elk Foundation) and Super Grade III in the 325 WSM while Browning chambered the 325 WSM in their A-Bolt, X-Bolt and BAR rifle lines.
Typical rifles for the WSM line of cartridges have barrels between 22–24 in (560–610 mm) which is less than the typical magnum rifle.  The short action combined with short barrels allow for a lighter rifle than a standard magnum rifle which would be based on a standard action with a 26 in (660 mm) barrel.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.325_Winchester_Short_Magnum)
</EN>
<ES>

El .325 Winchester Short Magnum, abreviado 325 WSM, es un cartucho metálico en calibre 8 mm de fuego central introducido por Winchester Ammunition en 2005. ​ 
Presentado en el Shot Show de Las Vegas, en el 2005, el .325 WSM es el calibre más grande de la familia de cartuchos Winchester Short Magnum, y se desarrolló con fines cinegéticos, específicamente para la caza mayor de animales de tamaño mediano y grande en los cinco continentes. ​
Desde la introducción del .300 WSM en 2000, se especuló que Winchester y Browning desarrollarían otros calibres a partir del casquillo del .300 WSM. 
Para el 2001, Winchester anunció el lanzamiento de los cartuchos metálicos .270 WSM y 7mm WSM . Se esperaba que el próximo calibre a introducirse a partir del casquillo de la familia WSM fuese el .33 (8.38 mm) . Sin embargo, Winchester sorprendió al público en el 2002 cuando introdujeron el .223 Winchester Super Short Magnum (abreviado .223 WSSM) y el .243 WSSM, que también desarrollados a partir del casquillo WSM recortado. Posteriormente se lanzó el .25 WSSM en 2003. ​
La introducción del .325 Winchester Super Short Magnum en 2005 sorprendió al mercado, ya que el calibre de 8 mm no tenía seguidores en América del Norte. Las introducciones anteriores de cartuchos de 8 mm en América del Norte no lograron la popularidad esperada, ya que el calibre .30 (7.62 mm) generalmente se consideraba el calibre de elección entre los cazadores estadounidenses. ​
El .325 WSM fue inicialmente ofrecido para disparar proyectiles "Silvertip"de 180 granos que logran una velocidad de salida de 3,060 pies por segundo; una opción de 200 granos, con velocidad de salida de 2,950 pies por segundo y una más pesada aún, de 220 granos que alcanza los 2,840 pies por segundo en las cargas comerciales. ​
El casquillo del .325 Winchester Short Magnum tiene una capacidad de H 2 O de 5,39 ml (83 granos ).

El cartucho 8×68 mm S introducido en 1939 es probablemente el gemelo balístico más cercano del .325 Winchester Short Magnum, que a su vez es considerablemente más corto y grueso, además de tener un borde rebajado más radical, un ángulo de hombro mucho más pronunciado y un cuello más corto (7.82 mm) que el 8×68 mm S, resultando en que  el castillo del 8×68mm S con su cuello de 9.1 mm de largo lo haga más adecuado para cargar balas más largas y pesadas. Por otro lado, las proporciones del .325 Winchester Short Magnum promueven una buena eficiencia balística interna que permite que el .325 Winchester Short Magnum dispare balas más cortas y livianas a velocidades de boca ligeramente más altas mientras usa menos propulsor que el 8×68mm S.
El .325 WSM es un cartucho calibre 8 mm muy eficiente y de trayectoria plana, con rendimientos similares a los otros dos cartuchos magnum como el célebre Remington Magnum de 8 mm y el cartucho alemán de 8×68mm S. Sin embargo, estos dos últimos cartuchos tienen la ventaja distintiva de poder acomodar cartuchos largos y pesados. Debido a la necesidad de colocar balas más largas y pesadas más profundamente en la columna de pólvora debido al diseño corto y la longitud total máxima del cartucho .325 WSM, la velocidad disminuye a medida que aumenta el peso de la bala. Esto es particularmente evidente con balas monometálicas como las balas E-Tip de Nosler y las balas Barnes X. Estas balas están construidas con cobre, que tiene aproximadamente un 20 % menos de densidad que una bala de plomo convencional. Las balas monometálicas resultantes suelen ser más largas, lo que requiere que estas balas se asienten más profundamente para cumplir con los estándares establecidos para el cartucho y permitir una alimentación y un ciclo confiables de los cartuchos en los rifles.
El .325 WSM debe considerarse primeramente como una opción de caza deportiva, adecuada para animales peligrosos de piel delgada y pesos de hasta 1800 libras (816 kg). Las balas de 180 gr o menos están destinadas a especies de ciervos más pequeños, como el venado cola blanca y el ciervo mulo, mientras que las de 200 gr o más están destinadas a wapiti, alces y osos grandes. 
El .325 WSM, resulta una alternativa interesante para cazadores europeos de alces, jabalíes, ya que su rendimiento es similar al 8×68 mm S. Siendo una opción versátil que permite cazar hasta los osos más grandes. La mayoría de los proveedores recomiendan al menos un cartucho de clase magnum de calibre .30 a .375 (según el umbral de retroceso del cazador) para las especies de osos más grandes, como el oso pardo de Alaska y el oso polar. Debido al tiro plano y al rendimiento de largo alcance del .325 WSM, también tiene un rendimiento superior para la mayoría de los juegos de las llanuras africanas, como el kudu, el nyala, el ñu y la cebra.


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.325_Winchester_Short_Magnum)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>