<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .338 Marlin Express is a cartridge developed by Marlin Firearms and Hornady.  It is based on the .376 Steyr with a goal to duplicate the venerable .30-06 Springfield's performance in a cartridge compatible with lever-action firearms. The cartridge uses a slightly shorter, rimmed case to function in lever-action rifles with tubular magazines.  As introduced in Hornady's LEVERevolution line of cartridges, it follows the design logic of the .308 Marlin Express which preceded it. The .338MX fires heavier .338 caliber bullets than the .308 Marlin Express at roughly the same velocity. It is chambered in Marlin's Model 338MX and 338MXLR rifles using the Marlin Model 336 action.
Whereas the .308 Marlin Express began by modifying the .307 Winchester, Hornady and Marlin engineers started with a previous collaboration between Hornady and the Austrian arms maker Steyr, the .376 Steyr, when designing the .338 Marlin Express. The case of the .376 Steyr was given a thicker web for added strength, then necked down to .338. The .308 Marlin Express, on the other hand, was made with a thinner web than its parent case, the .307 Winchester, for additional capacity. Although the thicker case webbing reduced capacity, new powders allow the .338 Marlin Express to achieve velocities similar to the .338 Federal with significantly lower pressures. Hornady engineers then looked to the projectile for the new cartridge. They settled on the 200-grain .338 projectile from their .338 Winchester Magnum line. The existing bullet was remade with a thinner jacket in order to promote expansion and upset at longer ranges. This 200-grain .338" projectile is able to impart significantly more energy than the 160 gr projectile used in the .308 Marlin Express, despite similar muzzle velocities. Furthermore, the projectile's high ballistic coefficient allows the .338 Marlin Express to maintain velocity to greater distances than big bore lever cartridges such as .45-70, .444 Marlin, or even the high performance .450 Marlin. Although the heavy bullet weight of these cartridges allow them more muzzle energy, the ballistic advantage of the .338 Marlin Express's projectile begins to show beyond 100 yards. After that point the .338 Marlin Express's projectile retains more energy than even the .450 Marlin. Like the .308 Marlin Express, the .338 Marlin Express was designed to be a relatively flat shooting cartridge, taking advantage of the bullets Hornady designed for the rounds. Its trajectory is similar to the .30-06 Springfield.
The .338 Marlin Express was designed to produce performance similar to the .30-06 Springfield. This would give lever-action hunters improved performance over their .30-30 Winchester rounds. The table below shows how the rounds compare. Note that reloading data for 200-grain (13 g) bullets for some of the cartridges is not available. Extensive loading data for the .338 Marlin Express is not yet available. The powder used in the Hornady loading is also not yet commercially available as of Feb '09. This round was designed with an elastomer tip, so that the .338 projectile would be safe for use in the tubular magazines of lever-action rifles. Traditional spitzer bullets are not compatible with the tubular magazines. This is due to the danger of the hard, pointed bullet-tip igniting the primer of the round in front of it under recoil impulse. The softer tip eliminates the hazards of stacking pointed rounds end to end in a tubular magazine.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.338_Marlin_Express)
</EN>
<ES>
El .338 Marlin Express fue desarrollado por Marlin Firearms y Hornady en conjunto .Se basa en el casquillo del .376 Steyr con el objetivo de duplicar el rendimiento del venerable .30-06 Springfield en un cartucho compatible con armas de fuego de palanca con cargadores tubulares. 
Tal como se introdujo en la línea de cartuchos LEVERevolution de Hornady, sigue la lógica de diseño del .308 Marlin Express que lo precedió. El .338MX dispara balas de calibre .338 más pesadas que el .308 Marlin Express aproximadamente a la misma velocidad. Tiene recámara en los rifles Marlin Modelo 338MX y 338MXLR que utilizan el mecanismo de la carabina Marlin Modelo 336 . ​
Mientras que el .308 Marlin Express nace de la modificación del .307 Winchester, los ingenieros de Hornady y Marlin comenzaron con una colaboración previa entre Hornady y el fabricante de armas austriaco Steyr, el .376 Steyr, al diseñar el .338 Marlin Express. La caja del .376 Steyr recibió una red más gruesa para mayor resistencia, luego se redujo a .338. El .308 Marlin Express, por otro lado, se fabricó con una red más delgada que su carcasa principal, el .307 Winchester, para una capacidad adicional. Aunque la correa de la caja más gruesa redujo la capacidad, los nuevos polvos permiten que el .338 Marlin Express alcance velocidades similares al .338 Federal con presiones significativamente más bajas. Luego, los ingenieros de Hornady buscaron en el proyectil el nuevo cartucho. Se decidieron por el proyectil .338 de 200 granos de su línea .338 Winchester Magnum . La bala existente se rehízo con una cubierta más delgada para promover la expansión y el impacto en distancias más largas. Este proyectil de .338" de 200 granos es capaz de impartir significativamente más energía que el 160 gr proyectil utilizado en el .308 Marlin Express, a pesar de velocidades de salida similares. Además, el alto coeficiente balístico del proyectil permite que el .338 Marlin Express mantenga la velocidad a mayores distancias que los cartuchos de palanca de gran calibre como .45-70, .444 Marlin o incluso el .450 Marlin de alto rendimiento. Aunque el gran peso de las balas de estos cartuchos les permite más energía de boca, la ventaja balística del proyectil del .338 Marlin Express comienza a mostrarse más allá de las 100 yardas. Después de ese punto, el proyectil del .338 Marlin Express retiene más energía que incluso el .450 Marlin. Al igual que el .308 Marlin Express, el .338 Marlin Express fue diseñado para ser un cartucho de tiro relativamente plano, aprovechando las balas que Hornady diseñó para las rondas. Su trayectoria es similar a la del .30-06 Springfield . ​
El .338 Marlin Express fue diseñado para producir un rendimiento similar al .30-06 Springfield . Esto daría a los cazadores de acción de palanca un mejor rendimiento con respecto a sus rondas .30-30 Winchester . La siguiente tabla muestra cómo se comparan las rondas. Tenga en cuenta que los datos de recarga de balas de 200 granos (13 g) para algunos de los cartuchos no están disponibles. Los datos de carga extensos para el .338 Marlin Express aún no están disponibles. El polvo utilizado en la carga de Hornady tampoco está disponible comercialmente a partir de febrero de 2009. Esta ronda fue diseñada con una punta de elastómero, de modo que el proyectil .338 sería seguro para usar en los cargadores tubulares de los rifles de palanca . Las balas Spitzer tradicionales no son compatibles con los cargadores tubulares . Esto se debe al peligro de que la punta de bala dura y puntiaguda encienda el detonador de la bala que tiene delante por impulso de retroceso. La punta más suave elimina los peligros de apilar rondas puntiagudas de punta a punta en un cargador tubular.


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.338_Marlin_express)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>