<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .338 Ruger Compact Magnum or .338 RCM is a rimless, short-length rifle cartridge based on the .375 Ruger case. Sturm Ruger and Hornady jointly developed the round, which was released in 2008 and chambered in various Ruger rifles. The goal of the project was to produce a .338 caliber cartridge with magnum level performance that would fit in a compact, short action rifle. The .338 RCM is conceptually similar to the WSM cartridge family, but is somewhat smaller dimensionally. This often allows for a higher magazine capacity than the WSM equivalent. Like the .338 caliber cartridges which predated it, the round is designed for hunting medium to large sized North American game.
The .338 Ruger Compact Magnum is based on the .375 Ruger cartridge, which originated with Hornady and Ruger. The case is of rimless design, having a base and rim diameter of .532 in (13.5 mm), the same diameter as the belt on belted magnum cases derived from the .300 H&amp;H Magnum and .375 H&amp;H Magnum. This design offers greater case capacity than a belted magnum case of equal length. As Ruger intended the cartridge to be chambered in short length bolt-action rifles, they shortened the .375 Ruger parent case to 2.10 in (53 mm) to ensure a comparable cartridge overall length to the .308 Winchester. Unlike the Winchester Short Magnum cartridges, the Ruger Compact Magnums share the same diameter from case head to body. This allowed Ruger to chamber the cartridge without extensively redesigning their M77 rifle.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.338_Ruger_Compact_Magnum)
</EN>
<ES>
El .338 Ruger Compact Magnum o .338 RCM es un cartucho de rifle de longitud corta desarrollado a partir del casquillo del .375 Ruger. Diseñado por Sturm Ruger y Hornady para ser usado en rifles de cerrojo e introducido al mercado en el año 2008, fue recamarado en varios rifles Ruger, con el objetivo de crear un cartucho de caza mayor, calibre .338 que pudiese ser usado en rifles compactos sin comprometer la performance lograda por otros cartuchos del mismo calibre, como el .338 win mag; concepto similar al de los cartuchos de la familia Winchester Short Magnum (WSM), pero de casquillo más estrecho, lo cual permite almacenar más balas que el equivalente en WSM.​
El .338 Ruger Compact Magnum utiliza un casquillo único diseñado por Hornady y Ruger basado en el potente .375 Ruger. El casquillo, tiene un diámetro de base de .0.352 pulgadas (13.5mm) cuál es el mismo diámetro del cinturón de los belted magnum como el .375 H&amp;H y a la vez ser usado en mecanismos de acción corta equivalentes a los requeridos para utilizar cartuchos del tamaño del .308 Winchester.​ A diferencia de Winchester Short Magnum (.270 WSM, .300 WSM) el Ruger Compact Magnum comparte el mismo diámetro del casquillo desde la base del culote hasta el hombro, permitiendo a Ruger recamarar este tipo de munición en sus mecanismos M77 sin tener que rediseñarlos. 


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.338_Ruger_Compact_Magnum)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>