<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .340 Weatherby Magnum rifle cartridge was introduced in 1962 by creator Roy Weatherby to fill the gap between the .300 Weatherby Magnum and the .378 Weatherby Magnum, and in response to the .338 Winchester Magnum released in 1958.
The .340 Weatherby Magnum uses the same .338 in. diameter bullets as the .338 Winchester Magnum, but it does so at greater velocity than its Winchester competition. Reloaders may have trouble matching the published Weatherby velocities as Weatherby factory ammunition is loaded to maximum specifications. Weatherby no longer loads the 250gr. round-nose cartridge pictured but continues to load the 250 gr. Spire Point and 250 gr. Nosler Partition. Weatherby has also expanded their factory loads including Nosler Ballistic-tip and Barnes TSX bullets complementing the powerful cartridge. Currently  A-square is the only other factory ammunition producer of the .340 Weatherby Magnum, which has led to limited popularity of the caliber. In field tests the .340 clearly outperforms the 300 Ultra mag, .338 Win mag. and even rivals the larger .375 H&amp;H, providing a much flatter shooting and harder hitting performance.
This cartridge is powerful enough for even the largest North American game and is suitable for most African game as well.

This ammunition-related article is a stub. You can help Wikipedia by expanding it.

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.340_Weatherby_Magnum)
</EN>
<ES>
 
El .340 Weatherby Magnum cartucho de rifle introducido en 1962 por Roy Weatherby para llenar el vacío entre .300 Weatherby Magnum y el .378 Weatherby Magnum, y en respuesta al .338 Winchester Magnum introducido en 1958.​
El .340 Weatherby Magnum utiliza la misma bala de .338 pugadas que el .338 Winchester Magnum, pero a mayor velocidad con munición comercial que es cargada con las máximas presiones sugeridas, lo que puede limitar a quienes recargan buscando aumentar las velocidades publicitadas.​ Weatherby Ya no carga balas de 250 granos de punta redonda pero continúa cargando el Spire Point y Nosler Partition, ambos de .250 granos. Actualmente Nosler Ballistic-tip y Barnes TSX complementan la oferta.​ 
En pruebas de campo el .340 Wby Mag claramente supera al el .300 Remington Ultra Magnum y al .338 Winchester Magnum, e incluso se pone a la par con cartuchos más grandes como el .375 H&amp;H, proporcionando una trayectoria más plana y mayor pegda.
Este cartucho es bastante potente incluso para los animales más pesados en Norte América y para cualquier especie de caza mayor en África.​


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.340_Weatherby_Magnum)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>