<loc>

<DE>
Die Gewehrpatrone .375 Ruger entstand 2007, sie wurde in Zusammenarbeit der Firmen Ruger und Hornady für die Großwildjagd entwickelt.
Im deutschen Nationalen Waffenregister (NWR) wird die Patrone unter Katalognummer 1643 geführt.
Die .375 Ruger kann in Standard-Büchsensystemen wie dem Mauser System 98 problemlos untergebracht werden. Sie hat denselben Bodendurchmesser wie die .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum, wegen des fehlenden Gürtels kann die Hülse dicker gehalten werden, wodurch das Hülsenvolumen steigt. Die 30-Grad-Schulter wurde weit nach vorn verlegt, was zusätzlich Platz für Schießpulver schafft. Das Ergebnis war eine Hülse, die bei 65,6 mm Länge (8 mm weniger als bei der .375 H&amp;H Magnum) ein 8 Prozent größeres Hülsenvolumen aufweist.
Damit liegt die erzielbare Mündungsenergie leicht über der .375 H&amp;H Magnum.
Die Patrone ist eine modernere Alternative zur älteren .375 H&amp;H Magnum, einer typischen Gürtelpatrone mit langer Hülse. Die Hülsengeometrie der .375 Ruger begünstigt eine gute Leistungsausbeute in Bezug auf die Pulverladung. Weiterer Vorteil ist das bessere Durchzünden der Pulverladung, was der Verwendung von führigen Waffen mit kürzeren Lauflängen entgegenkommt. In der Praxis bedeutet dies, dass die Ruger aus einem 52 cm kurzen Lauf das gleiche Leistungsniveau wie die H&amp;H aus einem 61 cm langen Lauf erreicht.


(https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/.375_Ruger)
</DE>
<EN>
The .375 Ruger (9.5×65.5mm) is a rimless, standard-length rifle cartridge designed for the hunting of large, dangerous game. It is designed to provide an increase in performance over the .375 H&amp;H cartridge, yet to be chambered in a standard-length action rifle. The cartridge was designed in partnership, by Hornady and Ruger. In 2007, it was released commercially and chambered in the Ruger Hawkeye African and the Ruger Hawkeye Alaskan rifles.
Like the .376 Steyr that originates from the 9.3×64mm Brenneke and the .375 Dakota proprietary cartridge that originates from the .404 Jeffery, the .375 Ruger was designed to compete with the .375 H&amp;H Magnum, yet have the advantage of having a rimless, beltless case and can function through a standard-length bolt-action rifle due to a shorter overall length. 
The .375 Ruger uses a unique cartridge case designed by Hornady and Ruger. The case is of a rimless design having the base and rim diameter of .532 in (13.5 mm), which is the same diameter of the belt on belted magnum cases based on the .300 H&amp;H Magnum and .375 H&amp;H Magnum. This allows the cartridge to have a greater case capacity than a belted magnum case given cases of equal length. As Ruger intended the cartridge to be chambered in standard-length bolt-action rifles, the case length was kept to 2.580 in (65.5 mm), which is only .04 in (1.0 mm) longer than the .270 Winchester case. The maximum overall length of the cartridge is 3.340 in (84.8 mm), which is similar to the maximum overall length to standard-length cartridges such as the .338 Winchester Magnum or the .30-06 Springfield. Unlike Remington Ultra Magnum cartridges, the Ruger Magnums can be chambered in standard-length bolt-action rifles. This allowed Ruger to chamber the cartridge in their existing standard length M77 rifle, without needing to use their M77 Safari Magnum Rifle.
While the .375 H&amp;H Magnum is longer than the .375 Ruger, the latter cartridge has a 4% greater case capacity than the Holland &amp; Holland cartridge, 99 gr. of water (6.42 cm3) compared to the H&amp;H's 95. This is due to the .375 H&amp;H Magnum having a long, tapered body, while the .375 Ruger follows modern cartridge designs in that it has very little taper and a sharper shoulder.
Cartridge standards for the .375 Ruger were issued by SAAMI in June 2007. SAAMI recommends a six-groove barrel having a bore Ø of .366 in (9.3 mm) and a groove Ø of .376 in (9.6 mm) with a groove width of .115 in (2.9 mm). The recommended rate of twist is one revolution in 12 in (304.8 mm). Recommended maximum pressure for the cartridge is 62,000 psi (4,300 bar).
Currently, Hornady and Double Tap manufacture ammunition for the .375 Ruger cartridge. The Hornady Superformance ammunition drives a 270-grain (17 g) SP-RP bullet at 2,840 ft/s (870 m/s) and the 300-grain (19 g) DGS and DGX bullets at 2,660 ft/s (810 m/s). The Double Tap achieves 2,825 ft/s (861 m/s) and 4,700 ft⋅lb (6,400 J) with a 270-grain Barnes TSX from a 23-inch barrel Ruger 77 African. The .375 Ruger's slightly greater case capacity, and the "short fat" cartridge efficiency lead to increases in the neighborhood of 150 fps over the H&amp;H cartridge. Their capabilities remain essentially comparable. Since 2015, O.F. Mossberg &amp; Sons produced bolt-action rifles of the "Patriot" series chambered in .375 Ruger with different stock options.
The .375 Ruger cartridge has functioned as the parent case for the 300 Precision Rifle Cartridge (300 PRC), which is essentially a necked-down version of the .375 Ruger. American ammunition manufacturer Hornady got the 300 PRC SAAMI-standardized in 2018. In 2019 it got C.I.P.-standardized as the 300 PRC. The 300 PRC cartridge case capacity is 6.2 ml (95.5 grains) H2O. The .375 Ruger cartridge case was used by Hornady as the basis for a new extra-long-range cartridge, since it had the capability to operate with high chamber pressures, which combined with a neck and barrel throat optimized for loading relatively long and heavy .308 diameter very-low-drag bullets without the need to seat the bullets deeply recessed into the case result in adequate muzzle velocities from magnum-sized bolt-action rifles. Rifles chambered for the 300 PRC must be capable of handling 3.70 in (93.98 mm) overall length cartridges.
The .300 Ruger Compact Magnum or .300 RCM was designed in 2007 and uses a case designed by Hornady and Ruger based on the .375 Ruger cartridge. The case is of a rimless design having the base and rim diameter of .532 in (13.5 mm), which is the same diameter of the belt on belted magnum cases based on the .300 H&amp;H Magnum and .375 H&amp;H Magnum. This allows the cartridge to have a greater case capacity than a belted magnum case given cases of equal length. As Ruger intended the cartridge to be chambered in short-length bolt-action rifles, the case length was shortened to 2.10 in (53 mm), which is similar to the .308 Winchester case. Unlike Winchester Short Magnum cartridges, the Ruger Compact Magnums share the same diameter from case head to body. This allowed Ruger to chamber the cartridge without extensively redesigning their Ruger M77 rifle to adapt them to the new Ruger cartridge.
The .338 Ruger Compact Magnum or .338 RCM is a rimless, short-length rifle cartridge based on the .375 Ruger case. It was designed by Ruger and Hornady and released in 2008 and chambered in various Ruger rifles. The goal was to create a shorter cartridge than the big .338 magnums that would fit in a more compact rifle with nearly the same performance. Similar to the design ideas for the WSM cartridge family, but somewhat narrower which will frequently allow one more cartridge in the rifle magazine than the WSM equivalent. This round is designed for hunting medium- to large-sized North American game.
The .416 Ruger is a beltless, rimless, bottle-necked cartridge designed as a joint venture by Hornady and Ruger in 2008. The cartridge is based on the .375 Ruger case, which was necked up to accept a .416 in (10.6 mm) bullet. It was designed as a dangerous game cartridge, particularly for use in Alaska and Africa.
The .500 Bushwhacker is a semirimmed magnum handgun cartridge initially developed by fireforming the .375 Ruger case cylindrical, shortening it by 0.13 in, and threading the base for a rim. It was designed by brothers James Tow and Keith Tow of Halsey, Oregon, to provide comparable performance to traditional African stopping rifles from the context of the Magnum Research BFR revolvers.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.375_Ruger)
</EN>
<ES>
El .375 Ruger (9.5×65.5mm)  es un cartucho de rifle de fuego central diseñado para la caza mayor de animales peligrosos. Está diseñado para mejorar el rendimiento del .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum y a su vez ser recamarado en un rifle de acción de longitud estándar. El cartucho estuvo diseñado en sociedad, por Hornady y Ruger. En 2007,  esté liberado comercialmente  en el Ruger M77 Hawkeye African y el Ruger M77 Hawkeye Alaskan.​
Como el .376 Steyr que se basa en el 9.3×64mm Brenneke y el .375 Dakota desarrollado del casquillo del .404 Jeffery, el .375 Ruger estuvo diseñado para competir con el .375 H&amp;H Magnum, con la  ventaja de ser usado en un mecanismo de longitud estándar, similar al usado para cartuchos de la longitud de un .270 Winchester, 30-06 ó 300 Winchester Magnum. 
El .375 Ruger utiliza un casquillo único diseñado por Hornady y Ruger, que tiene un diseño sin anillo en la base y diámetro de brocal de .0,532 plg (13,5 mm) en (13.5 ) que coincide con el diámetro  del cinturón de los belted magnum  desarrollados a partir del .300 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum y .375 H&amp;H Magnum. De esta manera, el casquillo del .375 Ruger logra tener una mayor capacidad de carga que un belted magnum desarrollado para ser alimentado en un mecanismo de longitud estándar, a diferencia de los cartuchos de la familia de los Remington Ultra Magnum, o los Weatherby Magnums, que deben ser alimentados en un mecanismo de acción magnum larga; permitiendo a Ruger no tener que hacer modificaciones en el Ruger M77 para poder recamararlo en este calibre; aplicando la misma filosofía de Winchester a inicios de los años 60 cuando desarrollaron la familia de cartuchos Winchester Magnum. Cuando. Ruger concibió el cartucho para que sea alimentado en rifles de acción la longitud estándar, determinó que el cartucho tuviera una longitud 2.580 en (65.5 mm); sólo 0.04 pulgadas (1.0 mm ) más largo que el casquillo del .270 Winchester .​ La longitud máxima del cartucho es 3.340 en (84.8 ) cuál es similar a la longitud global máxima a cartuchos de longitud estándar como el 300 Winchester Magnum, .338 Winchester Magnum o el .30-06 Springfield.  
Aunque el .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum es más largo que el .375 Ruger, este último tiene un casquillo de mayor capacidad que el cartucho de Holland &amp; Holland. Esto se debe a que el .375 H&amp;H Magnum cuenta con una hombro menos pronunciado y a un casquillo ligeramente más delgado (ambas características hacen del .375 Holland &amp; Holland, un cartucho que será alimentado en la recámara de un rifle de manera más suave). La capacidad del casquillo del .375 Ruger es de 99 g de agua (6.42 cm³) mientras el .375 H&amp;H Magnum tiene una capacidad de caso de 95 gr. De agua (6.16 cm³), un aumento de 4%. 
Estándares de cartucho para el .375 Ruger estuvo emitido por SAAMI en junio de 2007. SAAMI Recomienda un cañón con 6 estrías con un diámetro de cañón de .0,366 plg (9,3 mm) en (9.3 mm) y un diámetro de estrías de .0,376 plg (9,6 mm) en (9.6 mm) con un ancho de estrías de .0,115 plg (2,9 mm) en (2.9 mm). El ratio de giro recomendable es de 1:12 pulgadas  (304.8 mm). La presión máxima recomendable para el cartucho es 62,000 psi (4,300 bar ).
Actualmente Hornady y Double Tap producen el.375 Ruger. La munición Hornady superformance la munición empuja un proyectil de 270 granos a 2,840 pies por segundo (870 m/s) y la bala de 300 granos logra una velocidad de 2,660 pies por segundo (810 m/s). La munición Double Tap logra 2,825 pies por segundo (861 m/s) y 4,700 libras/pie con proyectiles Barnes TSX de 270 granos, de un cañón de 23 pulgadas de un rifle Ruger M77 Hawkeye African.  
El .375 Ruger cuenta con ligeramente mayor capacidad de en el casquillo, y la "eficacia de este casquillo más gordo y corto" genera una ventaja de 150 pies por segundo sobre el 375 H&amp;H mag. Sus capacidades quedan esencialmente comparables. Desde entonces 2015 O.F. Mossberg &amp; Sons produce rifles de cerrojo calibre .375 Ruger en su modelo "Patriot" en diferentes presentaciones.​​​
El casquillo del .375 Ruger ha sido usado como base para el desarrollo del 300 Rifle de Precisión Cartucho (300 PRC), el cual es esencialmente el .375 Ruger con el cuello ajustado a un calibre .308. El fabricante de munición americano Hornady conseguía el 300 Rifle de Precisión Cartucho SAAMI-estandarizado en 2018.​​ En 2019  consiga C.I.P.-Estandarizado como el 300 PRC.​ El 300 PRC capacidad de casquillo del Cartucho es 6.2 ml (95.5 granos) H2O. El casquillo del .375 Ruger  estuvo utilizado por Hornady como la base para un cartucho para tiros a distancias extremas, con el objetivo de operar a presiones muy altas en la recámara que, combinados con un cuello y garganta del cañón optimizados para asentar proyectiles .308 muy largos y pesado, para lograr un coeficiente balístico alto sin que estos proyectiles estén asentados profundamente que pudiesen comprometer la capacidad del casquillo y por consiguiente la velocidad de salida desde un mecanismo para magnum largo. Los rifles recamarados para el 300 PRC tienen una longitud máxima de 3.70 en (93.98 ) .​​
El .300 Ruger Compact Magnum o .300 RCM estuvo diseñado en 2007 y utiliza un casquillo diseñado por Hornady y Ruger basado en el .375 Ruger. El casquillo es de un diseño sin anillo en la base y diámetro de brocal de .0,532 plg (13,5 mm) en (13.5 ) cuál es el mismo diámetro  del cinturón en belted magnum los casos basaron en el .300 H&amp;H Magnum y .375 H&amp;H Magnum. Esto deja el cartucho para tener una capacidad mayor que un belted magnum con casquillos de la misma longitud, siendo la longitud máxima del cartucho de a 2.10 pulgadas (53 mm ) la cuál es similar al .308 Winchester .​ A diferencia de los cartuchos de la familia de los Winchester Short Magnum, el Ruger Compact Magnum compartir el mismo diámetro de casquillo, permitiendo a Ruger recamarar el Ruger M77 Hawkeye en el 300 RCM su acción corta sin tener que rediseñarlo. Sin embargo; el cartucho no logró obtener la popularidad del 300 Winchester Short Magnum y actualmente el Ruger M77 no se produce en este calibre. 
El .416 Ruger es un cartucho desarrollado en base al .375 Ruger, por Hornady y Ruger en conjunto, en 2008. Es básicamente un .375 Ruger rediseñado para aceptar un proyectil de.0,416 plg (10,6 mm) para ser usado para caza mayor de animales peligrosos particularmente en Alaska y África. 


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.375_Ruger)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>