<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .378 Weatherby Magnum was designed by Roy Weatherby in 1953. It was an original belted magnum design with no parent case, inspired by the .416 Rigby and headspacing of the belted .375 H&amp;H Magnum. The 215 magnum rifle primer was developed by Federal specifically for this round. The cartridge can hold upwards of 7.13 g (120 gr) of powder. The 378 Weatherby Magnum cartridge also has the double radius shoulder design found on the first and smaller proprietary line of Weatherby magnum cartridges.
The motivation behind the development of the .378 came from the disappointing performance gains of the improved .375 Weatherby Magnum over its parent case, the .375 H&amp;H Magnum. Roy Weatherby in 1953 killed an African elephant with one shot while on safari. However, in using this event as a marketing tool, it was revealed some African countries have a minimum 10.16 mm (.40 caliber) bullet size for hunting dangerous game. Weatherby responded by necking up the .378 to 11.63 mm (.458 caliber) and called the new cartridge the .460 Weatherby Magnum, which was introduced in 1958.
Considered a safari-grade cartridge, the .378 Weatherby Magnum is appropriate for taking all African game animals from large African antelopes, Nile crocodile, hippopotamus, to the Big Five game. Some hunters on the North American continent employ the .378 for American elk, brown bears, and polar bear.
The .378 Weatherby will generate considerable free recoil, an average of 104 J (77 ft·lbf) from a 4.1 kg (9 lb) rifle. This compares to 27 J (20 ft·lbf) from a rifle chambered for .30-06 Springfield or 49 J (36 ft·lbf) for the .375 H&amp;H Magnum.
The .378 has been responsible for numerous wildcat cartridges, being necked-down as the .22 Eargesplitten Loudenboomer and necked-up as the .500 A-Square. Some of the .378 Weatherby Magnum wildcat cartridges are shortened versions, like the .30-378 Arch (7.62 mm) and the .460 Short A-Square (11.63 mm). Some .378-based wildcats have gone on to be part of the Weatherby line: .30-378, .338-378, .416 and .460.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.378_Weatherby_Magnum)
</EN>
<ES>
Diseñado por Roy Weatherby en 1953 el .378 Weatherby Magnum es un cartucho belted magnum cuyo casquillo no parte de un cartucho predecesor.​ Weatherby se inspiró del .416 Rigby y el .375 H&amp;H Magnum.​ Federal desarrolló el fulminante 215 magnum rifle primer específicamente para este cartucho que puede aguantar más de 7.13 granos (120 g) de pólvora.​ El casquillo del .378 Wby Mag, además del cinturón, tiene un hombro de radio doble característico de los otros Weatherby Magnum.
La motivación de Roy Weatherby para crear el .378 Wby Mag provino porque los rendimientos del .375 Weatherby Magnum no lograron superar significativamente a su predcesor, el .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum con las pólvoras de la época. ​ Si bien Roy Weatherby cazó un elefante africano en 1959 con un solo disparo mientras estaba de safari, en algunos países del África el mínimo permitido para la caza de animales peligrosos es de 10.16mm (.40"), motivo por el cual Weatherby tuvo que desarrollar otro calibre capaz de ajustarse a la norma​ Por Así es que Weatherby Respondió ampliando el cuello del casquillo del.378 a 11.63 mm (.458) y lo llamó el .460 Weatherby Magnum, el cual estuvo introducido en 1958.​
Considerado un cartucho de safari, el .378 Weatherby Magnum es apropiado para cazar todo tipo de animales africanos, desde antílopes africanos grandes, cocodrilo del Nilo, hipopótamo, y los cinco grandes de África. Algunos cazadores en el continente norteamericano emplean el .378 Wby Mag para cazar wapiti americano, osos pardos, y oso polar.
El .378 Weatherby genera un considerable retroceso, en promedio, de 104 J en un rifle de 4.1 kg (9 lb). Considerablemente mayor al .30-06 Springfield del mismo peso genera 27 J o 49 J en un .375 H&amp;H Magnum.​


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.378_Weatherby_Magnum)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>