<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .400 Jeffery Nitro Express or .450/400 Nitro Express 3-inch is a medium bore, bottlenecked, Nitro Express cartridge designed by W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co in 1902, intended for use in single shot and double rifles.
The W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co developed the .400 Jeffery NE from the .450/400 31⁄4-inch Nitro Express, following extraction problems with the latter cartridge.
The .450/400 31⁄4-inch NE was recreated by loading the old .450/400 31⁄4-inch Black Powder Express with cordite, transforming a low-velocity deerstalking cartridge into a genuine big-game hunting round capable of tackling even the largest Indian and African game.  The conversion was not initially entirely successful, under the increased pressures of the cordite loading the long neck could stick in the chamber causing the rim to pull off at extraction, a problem not encountered with the milder black powder loadings.  To counter this, W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co reduced the length of the case to 3-inches and moved the neck further forward, creating this cartridge, as such it was never loaded with black powder.
Unlike earlier .450/400 31⁄4-inch NE cases the .400 Jeffery NE was standardised on the .410 caliber bullets, renewed interest in the double rifles meant more bullets in this caliber were becoming available.
The .450/400 NE in both the 3-inch and 31⁄4-inch versions were extremely popular in Africa and India, prior to the introduction of the .375 Holland &amp; Holland they were considered the best all-round African hunting caliber.  Both cartridges were extremely popular in India with Maharajas and British sportsmen.
Karamojo Bell started his elephant hunting career with a Jeffery built .450/400 double rifle prior to moving to his famous .275 Rigby. Jim Corbett switched from a .500 Black Powder Express to a W.J. Jeffery boxlock double rifle in .400 Jeffery NE which he used along with a .275 Rigby.
In his African Rifles and Cartridges, John "Pondoro" Taylor stated the 3-inch and 31⁄4-inch .450/400 NE cartridges to be "the grandest weapons imaginable for all big game hunting" adequate for all African game in almost all conditions when used by an experienced hunter.  He further stated "I derived greater pleasure from using the .400 than any other calibre; and no weapon behaved more successfully in my hands. I would happily finish the remainder of my career with a pair of them and nothing else-unless it was a third!"
Major Percy Powell-Cotton wrote the "Jeffery .400 ejector express rifle I first carried in my Abyssinian expedition is my favourite weapon for dangerous game.  With all nickel-covered bullets it is excellent for head or heart shots at elephant.  With the lead just showing at the nose they do good work on rhino and buffalo; whilst with half the lead exposed I do not think you can get a better weapon for lion."
Elmer Keith stated this cartridge would be his first choice when hunting brown bear in Alaska.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.400_Jeffery_Nitro_Express)
</EN>
<ES>
El .400 Jeffery Nitro Express o .450/400 Nitro Express de 3 pulgadas es un cartucho Nitro Express de calibre mediano y cuello de botella diseñado por WJ Jeffery &amp; Co en 1902, para sus rifles dobles .
El WJ Jeffery &amp; Co desarrolló el .400 Jeffery NE del casquillo del cartucho.450/400 31⁄4Nitro Express, debido a que este reportaba problemas de extracción.
El .450/400 Nitro Express de 31⁄4 pulgadas fue recreado cargando el viejo .450/400 3<span data-cx="[{&amp;quot;adapted&amp;quot;:true,&amp;quot;partial&amp;quot;:false,&amp;quot;targetExists&amp;quot;:true}]" data-mw="{&amp;quot;parts&amp;quot;:[{&amp;quot;template&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;target&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;wt&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Fracción&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;href&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;./Plantilla:Fracción&amp;quot;},&amp;quot;params&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;wt&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;1&amp;quot;},&amp;quot;2&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;wt&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;4&amp;quot;}},&amp;quot;i&amp;quot;:0}}]}" data-ve-no-generated-contents="true" id="mwGQ" typeof="mw:Transclusion"> </span>Black Powder Express con cordita, que transforma un cartucho de baja velocidad, con prestaciones modestas para la caza de cérvidos en una genuina ronda de caza mayor capaz de abatir a las especies más grandes en India y el África. Inicialmente, no fue del todo exitoso, debido al aumento de presión generado por cordita, no sucedía con las cargas más suaves de pólvora negra. Para contrarrestar esto, WJ Jeffery &amp; Co redujo la longitud del casquillo a 3 pulgadas y movió el cuello más hacia adelante, creando este cartucho,  como tal, nunca se cargó con pólvora negra.
A diferencia del .450/400 NE 31⁄4  pulgadas, el .400 Jeffery NE se estandarizó en las balas calibre .410, el renovado interés en los rifles dobles significó que más balas en este calibre estaban disponibles.
El .450/400 NE tanto en 3 pulgadas como en 31⁄4 alcanzaron gran popularidad, hasta la introducción del .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum.
Karamojo Bell inició su carrera como cazador de elefantes con un rifle doble .450/400 hecho por Jeffery, antes de usar el .275 Rigby .  Jim Corbett cambió su .500 Black Powder Express por un rifle doble WJ Jeffery boxlock en .400 Jeffery NE que usó junto con un .275 Rigby. 
En su libro African Rifles and Cartridges, John "Pondoro" Taylor afirmó que los rifles de 3 pulgadas y 31⁄4 del.450/400 NE eran "las mejores armas imaginables para toda la caza mayor" adecuados para toda la caza africana en casi todas las condiciones cuando los utiliza un cazador experimentado.  Dijo además: "Me complació más usar el .400 que cualquier otro calibre; y ningún arma se comportó con más éxito en mis manos. Felizmente terminaría el resto de mi carrera con un par de ellos y nada más, ¡a menos que fuera un tercero!" 
El comandante Percy Powell-Cotton escribió que "el rifle express eyector Jeffery .400 que llevé por primera vez en mi expedición a Abisinia es mi arma favorita para la caza peligrosa. Con todas las balas cubiertas de níquel, es excelente para disparos a la cabeza o al corazón de un elefante. Con la correa asomando por la nariz, hacen un buen trabajo con rinocerontes y búfalos; mientras que con la mitad del plomo expuesto, no creo que puedas conseguir un arma mejor para el león". 
Elmer Keith dijo que este cartucho sería su primera opción para cazar osos pardos en Alaska. 
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> pertenece al grupo «» no declarado en el texto anterior.
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> pertenece al grupo «» no declarado en el texto anterior.
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> pertenece al grupo «» no declarado en el texto anterior.
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> pertenece al grupo «» no declarado en el texto anterior.
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> pertenece al grupo «» no declarado en el texto anterior.


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.400_Jeffery_Nitro_Express)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>