<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>

The .400 Purdey, also known as the .400 3-inch Straight and .400 Purdey Light Express 3-inch, is an obsolete rifle cartridge developed by James Purdey &amp; Sons.
The .400 Purdey is a rimmed straight walled centerfire rifle cartridge intended for use in single shot and double rifles. It fires a bullet of .405 inches (10.3 mm) diameter weighing 230 grains (15 g), driven by 47 grains (3.0 g) of cordite, at a listed speed of 2,050 feet per second (620 m/s).
In Britain, from the inception of breech-loading rifles there were a large number of straight black powder .40 in (10 mm) paper and coiled brass cartridges developed of varying case lengths from 2 to 31⁄4 inches.  Around 1905, Purdey loaded the 3 inch brass cartridge with a light cordite load to create this cartridge.  Unusually for a proprietary cartridge, the .400 Purdey was introduced as a "Nitro for Black" loading, typically a mild loading of smokeless powder for a Black Powder Express cartridge, carefully balanced through trial to replicate the ballistics of the black powder version.
In 1899 John Rigby &amp; Company shortened the black powder predecessor of the .400 Purdey to 2.75 inches (70 mm) and necked it down to .358 inches (9.1 mm) to create the .400/350 Nitro Express which in turn later became the .350 Rigby No 2.
The .400 Purdey was reasonably popular in India for deer, boar and even tiger, and was available in both double rifles and more reasonably priced Martini action sporting rifles.  Whilst obsolete, cartridges can still be purchased today from manufacturers such as Kynoch.

This ammunition-related article is a stub. You can help Wikipedia by expanding it.

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.400_Purdey)
</EN>
<ES>
El .400 Purdey, también conocido como .400 Straight de 3 pulgadas o .400 Purdey Light Express de 3 pulgadas, es un cartucho de rifle obsoleto desarrollado por James Purdey &amp;amp; Sons .
El .400 Purdey es un cartucho de rifle de percusión central anillado, diseñado para usarse en rifles de un solo tiro y dobles . Dispara una bala de 0.405 pulgadas de diámetro con un peso de de cordita, a una velocidad indicada de 2050 pies por segundo (624,8 m/s) .  
En Gran Bretaña, desde el inicio de los rifles de retrocarga hubo una gran cantidad de pólvora negra recta 0,4 plg (10,2 mm) cartuchos de papel y latón en espiral desarrollados con diferentes longitudes de caja de 2 a 31⁄4 pulgadas. Alrededor de 1905, Purdey cargó el cartucho de latón de 3 pulgadas con una carga ligera de cordita para crear este cartucho. Inusualmente para un cartucho patentado, el .400 Purdey se introdujo como una carga "Nitro for Black", generalmente una carga suave de pólvora sin humo para un cartucho Black Powder Express, cuidadosamente equilibrada mediante pruebas para replicar la balística de la versión de pólvora negra.  
En 1899 , John Rigby &amp;amp; Company acortó el predecesor de pólvora negra del .400 Purdey a 2,75 pulgadas (69,9 mm) y lo redujo a 0,358 pulgadas (9,1 mm) para crear el .400/350 Nitro Express que a su vez más tarde se convirtió en el .350 Rigby No 2 . 
El .400 Purdey era razonablemente popular en la India para cazar ciervos, jabalíes e incluso tigres, y estaba disponible tanto en rifles dobles como en rifles deportivos de acción Martini a un precio más razonable. Si bien están obsoletos, los cartuchos aún se pueden comprar hoy en día a fabricantes como Kynoch . 
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> pertenece al grupo «» no declarado en el texto anterior.
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> pertenece al grupo «» no declarado en el texto anterior.


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.400_Purdey)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>