<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .404 Jeffery is a rifle cartridge designed for hunting large, dangerous game animals, such as the "Big Five" (elephant, rhino, cape buffalo, lion and leopard) of Africa. The cartridge is standardized by the C.I.P. and is also known as .404 Rimless Nitro Express. It was designed in 1905 by London based gunmaker W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co to duplicate the performance of the .450/400 Nitro Express 3-inch in bolt-action rifles. The .404 Jeffery fired a bullet of .422 in (10.72 mm) diameter of either 300 gr (19 g) with a muzzle velocity of 2,600 ft/s (790 m/s) and muzzle energy of 4,500 foot-pounds force (6,100 N⋅m) or 400 gr (26 g) with a muzzle velocity of 2,150 ft/s (660 m/s) and 4,100 foot-pounds force (5,600 N⋅m) of energy. It is very effective on large game and is favored by many hunters of dangerous game. The .404 Jeffery was popular with hunters and game wardens in Africa because of its good performance with manageable recoil. By way of comparison, the .416 Rigby and .416 Remington Magnum cartridges fire .416 in (10.57 mm) bullets of 400 gr (26 g) at 2,400 feet per second (730 m/s) with a muzzle energy of approximately 5,000 foot-pounds force (6,800 N⋅m). These cartridges exceed the ballistic performance of the .404 Jeffery but at the price of greater recoil and, in the case of the .416 Rigby, rifles that are more expensive.
Originally the .404 Jeffery was very popular with hunters in Africa and saw significant use in both British and German colonies. As the British Empire began to shrink, many of the popular British big-bore cartridges also dwindled in popularity, and the .404 Jeffery was one of them. By the 1960s it had all but disappeared from common firearm usage. This condition was mostly the result of the closing of the British ammunition giant Kynoch, which was the primary manufacturer of the .404 Jeffery and many other British cartridges. The introduction of the .458 Winchester Magnum in 1956 in the Winchester Model 70 bolt-action rifle provided an affordable alternative to the big Nitro Express rifles and cartridges. Winchester also started a marketing campaign at about this time called "Winchester in Africa" with much success. Renewed interest in heavy game rifles combined with political stability in Africa has led to a resurgence in African hunting and the rifles suited for it. Several ammunition makers like Kynoch, Norma, Federal, and Hornady are offering .404 Jeffery sporting ammunition.
A more recent development by Norma of Sweden has been the introduction of 450 gr ammunition under their African PH banner. The increase in bullet weight and sectional density improves the ballistics of the .404 Jeffery. Fired at 2,150 fps, the cartridge now outperforms most of its peers with a relatively mild recoil due to the efficient design of the cartridge.
In 1908, W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co created the .333 Jeffery by shortening the .404 case, giving it greater taper and necking it down to .333 in (8.5 mm). In 1913, Jeffery further necked down the .333 Jeffery to .288 inches, creating the .280 Jeffery.
In recent times, the .404 case has seen a resurgence in use by wildcatters. This case has no belt, unlike many other magnum cartridges,  which can be desirable for handloading because of possible problems with case head separation with repeated reloading of belted magnum cartridges. The rimless design also contributes to smooth feeding from the box magazine of bolt-action rifles.
Some common commercial children of the .404 Jeffery case are the Remington Ultra Magnum (RUM) cartridge family, which in turn spawned the Remington Short Action Ultra Magnum (RSAUM) cartridges. Also, the Winchester Short Magnum (WSM) and the Winchester Super Short Magnum (WSSM) families are believed to derive from the 404 Jeffery case. Both the Winchester and Remington cartridges have also spawned many current wildcats, like the popular .338 Edge.
All but one (.450 Dakota, based on .416 Rigby) of the proprietary cartridges of Dakota Arms such as .375 Dakota, and the .400 Tembo by Velocity USA, and the once-famous .460 G&amp;A, used by Jeff Cooper in his "baby" rifles, are all based on .404 Jeffery.
More examples of the popularity of creating small-bore, high-velocity cartridges based on the .404 Jeffery design are the .26 Nosler, .28 Nosler, .30 Nosler and, the latest, .33 Nosler, introduced by Nosler  between 2013 and 2016.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.404_Jeffery)
</EN>
<ES>
El .404 Jeffery (.404 Rimless Nitro Express) es un cartucho de rifle, diseñado sin anillo para ser usado en rifles de cerrojo y aplicado a la caza deportiva de animales granes y peligrosos en África y Asia, como los "cinco grandes de África".​ 
El cartucho fue estandarizado por el C.I.P.​ y diseñado en 1905 por W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co en Londres, con el objetivo de replicar el rendimiento del .450/400 Nitro Express de 3 pulgadas​ disparando una bala de .422 pulgadas (10.72 mm) de diámetro y de 300 granos (19 g) a una velocidad de salida de 2,600 pies/s (790 m/s), con una energía cinética de 4,500 libras-pie; o un proyectil de 400 granos (26 g) con una velocidad de salida de 2,150 pies/s (660 m/s) y 4,100 libras-pie de energía; performance que lo volvió muy eficaz y popular entre cazadores en el África. 
Comparándolo con el .416 Rigby y el .416 Remington Magnum, que usan proyectiles de .416 pulgadas (10.57 mm) con pesos de 400 granos (26 g) que generan velocidades aproximadas de 2,400 pies por segundo (730 m/s) con una energía de morro de aproximadamente 5,000 libras-pie; si bien el .404 Jeffery no logra estos rendimientos pero tampoco genera el retroceso, haciéndolo más fácil de disparar.
Originalmente el .404 Jeffery se volvió muy popular entre los cazadores en África y fue bastante usado tanto en colonias Inglesas como Alemanas. Cuando el Imperio británico empezó para reducirse en el continente africano, el .404 Jeffery, entre muchos otros calibres grandes empezaron a perder popularidad. Durante la década de los años 1960, el .404 Jefferey estaba prácticamente descontinuado, en gran parte debido a que el fabricante británico de munición, Kynoch, era prácticamente el único productor. Es con la introducción del .458 Winchester Magnum en 1956 en el Winchester Modelo 70 que se renueva el interés por los rifles de calibres grandes, además de la estabilidad política en África, resultando en la resurgencia de la caza deportiva en África. Es así que varios fabricantes de munición como Kynoch, Norma, Federal, y Hornady empezaron a ofrecer munición .404 Jeffery.
Recientemente la compañía Norma ha introducido munición .404 Jeffery con proyectiles de 450 granos.. El aumento en peso de bala y la densidad seccional mejora el balística del .404 Jeffery. despidiendo estos proyectiles a 2,150 pies/s.
En 1908, W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co creó el .333 Jeffery recortando el casquillo del .404 y ajustando el cuello para alojar un proyectil calibre.333 (8.5 mm).​ En 1913, Jeffery ajustó más el cuello del .333 Jeffery a .288 pulgadas, creando el .280 Jeffery.
En tiempos recientes, el casquillo del .404 ha resurgido en el desarrollo de nuevos cartuchos, en parte porque no tiene ningún cinturón, que es una característica deseable para quienes recargan munición..
Algunos descendientes comerciales comunes del casquillo del.404 Jeffery son los Remington Ultra Magnum (RUM) y los Remington Short Action Ultra Magnum (RSAUM) . También, los casquillos Winchester Short Magnum (WSM) y Winchester Super Short Magnum (WSSM) derivan del casquillo del 404 Jeffery. .
Todos los Calibres desarrollados por Dakota Arms, excepto el.450 Dakota, que se desarrollo del casquillo .416 Rigby, como, por ejemplo, el .375 Dakota, y el .400 Tembo, y el alguna vez famoso .460 G&amp;A, utilizado por Jeff Cooper en sus "baby rifles", parten del casquillo del .404 Jeffery.​
La nueva línea de calibres Nosler, incluyendo el .26 Nosler, 27 Nosler, .28 Nosler, .30 Nosler y, el , .33 Nosler, introducidos por Nosler entre 2013 y 2018, están desarrollados a partir del casquillo del .404 Jeffery.
La gran ventaja del .404 Jeffery radica en el balance entre la efectividad que tiene para cazar búfalos y leones, sin generar el retroceso de otros cartuchos que deben ser usados en rifles más pesados, mientras que un rifle en .404 Jeffery puede pesar unas 8.5 libras.​


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.404_Jeffery)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>