<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .416 Ruger is a .41 caliber (10.6 x 65.5mm), rimless, bottlenecked cartridge designed as a joint venture by Hornady and Ruger in 2008. Designed to equal the 416 Rigby and 416 Remington magnum but in a standard length 30-06 length action. The standard length actions are less expensive to manufacture thus making a dangerous game caliber available to a greater amount of customers. Gun manufacturers have not followed Ruger's lead. This also applies to the 375 Ruger. The 416 Ruger is suitable for the biggest land animals and dangerous game.
The cartridge is based on the .375 Ruger case which was necked up to accept a .416 in (10.6 mm) bullet. It was designed as a dangerous game cartridge particularly for use in Alaska and Africa. The .416 Ruger duplicates the performance of the .416 Rigby and the .416 Remington Magnum. All three cartridge fire a 400 gr (26 g) bullet at 2,400 ft/s (730 m/s) generating 5,115 ft⋅lbf (6,935 J) of energy. However, unlike the Remington or Rigby .416s, the Ruger .416 can be chambered in a standard length action, as the cartridge has a length of 3.34 inches. The cartridge has the same diameter of belted magnum cases but without the belt. This provides the cartridge a larger propellant capacity than a standard length magnum cartridge of the same length. The rimless design allows for smoother feeding and extraction of the cartridge.
The .416 Ruger is chambered in the bolt-action Ruger M77 Hawkeye "African" and "guide gun" rifles, and Krieghoff rifles. No other manufacturer currently chambers this cartridge. Ammunition is available from Hornady and Buffalo Bore.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.416_Ruger)
</EN>
<ES>
El .416 Ruger es un cartucho de fuego central para rifle calibre .41 (10.4 mm), diseñado con fines de caza mayor de animales peligrosos, por Hornady y Ruger en conjunto con el objetivo de igualar las prestaciones del 416 Rigby y 416 Remington magnum pero para ser alimentado en un mecanismo de acción de longitud estándar, similar a la usada para el .30-06 Springfield, y que este calibre pueda ser usado en el mecanismo estándar del Ruger M77 Hawkeye. Al igual que el 375 Ruger, el 416 Ruger es recomendable para cazar animales grandes y peligrosos.
El cartucho está desarrollado a partir del casquillo del .375 Ruger, al que se le expandió el cuello para permitir alojar una bala de 0.416 pulgadas (10.6 mm ). Esté diseñado como calibre de caza mayor de animales peligrosos , particularmente para ser usado en Alaska y África. El .416 Ruger duplica el rendimiento del .416 Rigby y el .416 Remington Magnum. Los 3 cartuchos disparan balas de 400 granos (26 g) a 2,400 pies por segundo (730 m/s) generando 5,115 pies libras de energía. Aun así, a diferencia del .416 Remington Magnum o del .416 Rigby, el .416 Ruger puede ser alimentado en una acción de longitud estándar al tener una longitud máxima de 3.34 pulgadas, similar al del 300 Winchester Magnum. El cartucho tiene el mismo diámetro de un belted magnum  pero sin el cinturón, proporcionándole una mayor capacidad de carga de pólvora que el de otro cartucho de la familia de los belted magnum, de la misma longitud. 
Actualmente el Ruger M77 Hawkeye "africano" y en el "guide gun" de la guía, además de los rifles alemanes Krieghoff . Actualmente no existe otro fabricante que produzca rifles en este cartucho. La munición es disponible de Hornady y Buffalo Bore.

 

(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.416_Ruger)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>