<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .416 Taylor is a rifle cartridge. According to Ken Waters in Pet Loads, it was created by Robert Chatfield-Taylor in the early 1970s, with the first rifle in this caliber being a factory barreled Winchester Model 70.  The case is based on the .458 Winchester Magnum necked down to accept .416 caliber bullets.
The .416 Taylor uses a .416 in (10.6 mm) bullet diameter. With maximum loads, the cartridge is capable of propelling a 400-grain (26 g) bullet at an average of 2,350 ft/s (720 m/s) from a 24 in (61 cm) barrel  yielding a muzzle energy of 4,903 ft⋅lbf (6,648 J). The work on this caliber (performed by Waters) was done with an experimental factory Ruger Model 77. He reported that an absolute maximum load of certain listed powders would push a 400-grain (26 g) bullet to 2,400 ft/s (730 m/s), thereby equaling (and perhaps exceeding) the performance of the .416 Rigby (presuming moderate temperatures and barometric pressures). Waters also reported that 400-grain (26 g) bullets could exceed 2,600 ft/s (790 m/s) when propelled by certain listed powders. Under normal hunting conditions, the Taylor cartridge is therefore capable of taking any of the largest and most dangerous game animals in the world.
Gunsmiths are rebarreling Browning BAR .338 Winchester Magnum rifles with .416 Taylor barrels thereby creating semi-automatic hunting rifles in a true dangerous game caliber.
The cartridge was created to replace the magnum length .416 Rigby which at that time was nearly obsolete, with a cartridge that would fit into a standard length bolt-action rifle. The shorter action rifles are not only easier to carry in heavy cover, but also make it more convenient to carry more ammunition. The advantages to cartridges in .416 inch bullet diameter are that they generally present the shooter with less recoil and flatter trajectory than the larger .458 caliber dangerous game rifles (like the .458 Winchester Magnum). They also have more striking power and penetration than medium bores like the .375 H&amp;H Magnum. The Taylor cartridge is simply a necked down .458 Winchester Magnum with no changes. They have the same shoulder height and angle as the .264 Winchester Magnum. The 416 Taylor was a SAAMI standardized cartridge, and was offered as a standard production item by A-Square until it closed in 2011.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.416_Taylor)
</EN>
<ES>
El cartucho metálico .416 Taylor fue creado por Robert Chatfield-Taylor a principios de la década de 1970, siendo el primer rifle producido comercialmente para este cartucho el Winchester Model 70. ​ El diseño parte del casquillo del .458 Winchester Magnum con el cuello ajustado para aceptar balas de calibre .416.
El .416 Taylor dispara un proyectil de 10.6mm (.416"). ​ Con cargas máximas, el cartucho es capaz de propulsar una bala de 400 granos a 2350 pies/s (716,3 m/s) con un cañón de 24 pulgadas ​ produciendo una energía inicial de 4,903 pies/libra . Los ensayos iniciales (realizados por Waters) se realizaron un un rifle Ruger Modelo 77, reportando haber logrado alcanzar los 2400 pies/s (731,5 m/s) con un proyectil de 400 granos; igualando la performance del .416 Rigby (suponiendo temperaturas y presiones barométricas moderadas). Waters también informó que las balas podrían exceder los 2600 pies/s (792,5 m/s) con ciertas pólvoras. 
Algunos armeros están recañonando rifles Browning BAR .338 Winchester Magnum con cañones .416 Taylor, creando así rifles de caza semiautomáticos en un arma para la caza de animales peligrosos. ​
El cartucho se creó para reemplazar el .416 Rigby de longitud magnum, que en ese momento estaba casi obsoleto, con un cartucho que cabría en un rifle de cerrojo de longitud estándar. Los rifles de acción más cortos no solo son más fáciles de transportar en una cubierta pesada, sino que también hacen que sea más conveniente llevar más municiones. ​ Las ventajas de los cartuchos con un diámetro de bala de .416 pulgadas son que generalmente presentan al tirador menos retroceso y una trayectoria más plana que los rifles de juego peligroso de calibre .458 más grandes (como el .458 Winchester Magnum). También tienen más fuerza de impacto y penetración que los calibres medianos como el .375 H&amp;H Magnum . El cartucho Taylor es simplemente un .458 Winchester Magnum con el cuello hacia abajo sin cambios. Tienen la misma altura de los hombros y el mismo ángulo que el .264 Winchester Magnum . El 416 Taylor era un cartucho estandarizado de SAAMI, ​ y A-Square lo ofreció como un artículo de producción estándar hasta que cerró en 2011.


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.416_Taylor)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>