<loc>

	<DE>N/A</DE>
	<EN>
The .45-70, also known as the .45-70 Government, is a .45 caliber rifle cartridge originally holding 70 grains of black powder that was developed at the U.S. Army's Springfield Armory for use in the Springfield Model 1873. It was a replacement for the stop-gap .50-70 Government cartridge, which had been adopted in 1866, one year after the end of the American Civil War, and is known by collectors as the "Trapdoor Springfield."
The predecessor to the .45-70 was the .50-70-450 cartridge, adopted in 1866 and used until 1873 in a variety of rifles, many of them were percussion rifled muskets converted to trapdoor action breechloaders. The conversion consisted of milling out the rear of the barrel for the trapdoor breechblock, and placing a .50 caliber "liner" barrel inside the .58 caliber barrel. The .50-70 was popular among hunters, as the bullet was larger than the .44 caliber and also hit harder (see terminal ballistics), but the military decided as early as 1866 that a .45 caliber bullet would provide increased range, penetration and accuracy. The .50-70 was nevertheless adopted as a temporary solution until a significantly improved rifle and cartridge could be developed.
The result of the quest for a more accurate, flatter shooting .45 caliber cartridge and firearm was the Springfield trapdoor rifle. Like the .50-70, the .45-70 used a copper center-fire case design. A reduced power loading was also adopted for use in the Trapdoor carbine. This had a 55 grain (3.6 g) powder charge.
Also issued was the .45-70 "Forager" round, which contained a thin wooden bullet filled with birdshot, intended for hunting small game to supplement the soldiers' rations. This round in effect made the .45-70 rifle into a 49 gauge shotgun.
The .45-caliber Springfield underwent a number of modifications over the years, the principal one being a strengthened breech starting in 1884. A new, 500 grain (32 g) bullet was adopted in that year for use in the stronger arm. The M1873 and M1884 Springfield rifles were the principal small arms of the U.S. Army until 1893.
The .45-70 round was also used in several Gatling gun models from 1873 until it was superseded by the .30 Army round beginning with the M1893 Gatling gun. Some .45-70 Gatling guns were used on U.S. Navy warships launched in the 1880s and 1890s.
The Navy used the .45-70 caliber in several rifles: the M1873 and M1884 Springfield, the Model 1879 Lee Magazine Navy contract rifle, and the Remington-Lee, the last two being magazine-fed turnbolt repeating rifles. The Marine Corps used the M1873 and M1884 Springfield in .45-70 until 1897, when supplies of the new M1895 Lee Navy rifle in 6mm Lee Navy, adopted two years before by the Navy, were finally made available.
Realizing that single-shot black-powder rifles were rapidly becoming obsolete, the U.S. Army adopted the Norwegian-designed .30 Army caliber as the Springfield Model 1892 in 1893. However, the .45-70 continued in service with the National Guard, Navy, and Marine Corps until 1897. The .45-70 was last used in quantity during the Spanish–American War, and was not completely purged from the inventory until well into the 20th century. Many surplus rifles were given to reservation Indians as subsistence hunting rifles and now carry Indian markings.
The .45-70 cartridge is still used by the U.S. military today, in the form of the "cartridge, caliber .45, line throwing, M32," a blank cartridge which is used in a number of models of line throwing guns used by the Navy and Coast Guard. Early models of these line throwing guns were made from modified Trapdoor and Sharps rifles, while later models are built on break-open single-shot rifle actions.

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.45-70)
	</EN>
	<ES>
El cartucho de fusil .45-70, también conocido como .45-70 Government, fue desarrollado en el Arsenal de Springfield del Ejército de los Estados Unidos para ser utilizado por el fusil Springfield Modelo 1873. Este nuevo cartucho fue el reemplazo del cartucho provisorio .50-70 Government adoptado en 1866, un año después del término de la Guerra de Secesión.
La identificación completa del nuevo cartucho era .45-70-405, pero también fue llamado como ".45 Government" en catálogos de ventas. La nomenclatura de su tiempo se basaba en tres propiedades del cartucho:
La precisión o puntería aceptable del .45-70 de 1873 era de aproximadamente 100 mm a 91 metros, aunque la pesada y lenta bala describía una trayectoria en forma de parábola, ya que esta caía varios metros al ser disparada a distancias más lejanas de 200 metros. Un tirador avezado, disparando a una distancia conocida, podría acertar consistentemente un blanco de 1,8 x 1,8 metros a 550 metros—el blanco estándar del ejército estadounidense. La precisión de este cartucho fue de algún valor real solo cuando se efectuaban múltiples tiros a la vez, ya que realizar tiros de precisión a un blanco del tamaño de un hombre solo era efectivo hasta aproximadamente 270 m.
Después de las pruebas de Sandy Hook en 1879, se comenzó a producir una nueva variante de este cartucho, el .45-70-500, el cual montaba una bala de 500 granos (32,5 g). Esta bala más pesada presentaba superiores características balísticas y podía alcanzar blancos a 3.120 m, mucho más que el alcance máximo del .45-70-405. Mientras que el alcance efectivo del .45-70 en blancos individuales era limitado a unos 915 m, la bala más pesada podía infligir heridas mortales a 3.200 m. A esas distancias, las balas golpeaban con la punta por delante, en un ángulo de 30°, penetrando tablones de roble con un espesor de 2,5 cm para luego seguir su trayectoria, atravesando otros 20 cm de la arena que estaba detrás. Se esperaba que el alcance incrementado del .45-70-500 permitiría fuego en ráfaga a mayores distancias de las normalmente esperadas del fuego de infantería.​
Mientras el diámetro nominal del ánima del cañón era de 11,4 mm (.450 pulgadas), el diámetro del ánima rayada era cercano a 11,6 mm (.458 pulgadas). En ese entonces era costumbre que varios cartuchos comerciales producidos en Estados Unidos viniesen envueltos en un par de capas de papel fino. Este parche ayudaba a sellar el ánima, evitando que la suave bala de plomo estuviese en contacto directo con el ánima rayada. Tal como el trozo de tela o el papel utilizado en las armas de avancarga, este parche de papel caía tan pronto como la bala salía del cañón. Las balas parchadas eran fabricadas en plomo blando y presentaban un diámetro de 11,4 mm. Cuando eran envueltas en dos capas de papel de algodón, estas alcanzaban un diámetro final de 11,6 mm, igualando así el del ánima rayada. Estas balas parchadas aún se encuentran disponibles, y algunos tiradores que utilizan cartuchos de pólvora negra aún "enrollan" sus propias balas para utilizarlas en caza y tiro competitivo.​​ 


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.45-70)
	</ES>
	<FR>
Cet article ne cite pas suffisamment ses sources (janvier 2016).
Si vous disposez d'ouvrages ou d'articles de référence ou si vous connaissez des sites web de qualité traitant du thème abordé ici, merci de compléter l'article en donnant les références utiles à sa vérifiabilité et en les liant à la section « Notes et références » 
En pratique : Quelles sources sont attendues ? Comment ajouter mes sources ?
La .45-70 Government (.45-70, .45-70 Springfield ou .45-70 Mle1873...) est une munition créée aux États-Unis en 1871, où elle resta réglementaire jusqu'en 1892. Cette munition équipa l'armée française jusqu'en 1918 (réserve, seconde ligne et milice), l'armée russe jusqu'en 1903, le Japon...
Sa balistique acceptable (une centaine de mètres), sa simplicité à être rechargée et son efficacité nous ont transmis cette très ancienne cartouche inchangée, toujours employée pour la chasse au gros gibier.
L'origine du nom vient du calibre de la munition utilisé (0,45 pouce (11,43 mm), mais en réalité le calibre est légèrement plus grand (0,458 pouce (11,6332 mm)) associé à la masse de poudre noire (70 grains ou 4,536 g).
Elle forme la première cartouche standardisée : 45-70-405 (respectivement : calibre (en centièmes de pouce), masse de la poudre noire (en grains) et masse de l'ogive (en grains).
Plusieurs fusils furent chambrés pour cette cartouche :


(https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/.45-70_Government)
	</FR>
	<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>