<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>

The .450 No 2 Nitro Express also known as the .450 Nitro Express 31⁄2-inch was developed by Eley Brothers in 1903.
The .450 No 2 Nitro Express is rimmed, bottlenecked, .458-inch (11.6 mm) calibre cartridge designed for use in single-shot and double rifles, it fires a 480-grain (31 g) projectile at over 2,175 feet per second (663 m/s).
The .450 No 2 Nitro Express has a massive 3.5-inch (89 mm) long cartridge case which has a large case capacity and compared to other similar Nitro Express cartridges has a thicker rim and heavier walls.  The size of the cartridge case gives it some of the lowest chamber pressures amongst the Nitro Express cartridges which, when combined with its thick rim and heavy walls, makes it almost impervious to sticking in the chamber.
Following early extraction problems encountered with the revolutionary .450 Nitro Express which had been created by John Rigby &amp; Company in 1898, Eley took the unusual step for the time of creating their own completely new cartridge and release it to the market in 1903, allowing all rifle makers to chamber weapons for their round. This was unusual for two reasons, the first was this cartridge has no blackpowder express forebear, the second is it was designed by an ammunition maker, as most cartridges of the period were designed by rifle makers.  The .450 No 2 Nitro Express was so named to differentiate it from the original.
Ballistically, the .450 No 2 Nitro Express is almost identical to the original .450 Nitro Express and Holland &amp; Holland's .500/450 Nitro Express also intended to replace the original. The early problems of the .450 Nitro Express were however soon resolved and the .450 No 2 Nitro Express was never as popular as its predecessor.
Following the British Army 1907 ban of .450 caliber ammunition into India and the Sudan, Eley developed the .475 No. 2 Nitro Express by necking up the .450 No 2 Nitro Express.
The .450 No 2 Nitro Express is suitable for all dangerous game including elephant.  In his African Rifles and Cartridges, John "Pondoro" Taylor states the .450 No 2 Nitro Express is as good as but no better than any other .450-.476 calibre Nitro Express cartridges in terms of killing power.  Taylor further states there is a psychological appeal attached to the .450 No 2 Nitro Express, the size of the enormous cartridge giving the hunter confidence that they are carrying a deadlier weapon that one chambering a similar cartridge.
Pondoro Taylor owned four rifles chambered in .450 No 2 Nitro Express, with them he killed several hundred elephant, scores of rhinoceros and several hundred buffalo.  Other notable users of this cartridge include Philip Percival who hunted with a pair of .450 No 2 Nitro Express boxlock double rifles made by Joseph Lang, and Nripendra Narayan, Maharaja of Koch Bihar, who hunted with a large battery of rifles including a .450 No 2 Nitro Express double rifle by Manton &amp; Co.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.450_No_2_Nitro_Express)
</EN>
<ES>
El .450 No 2 Nitro Express o .450 Nitro Express 31⁄2 fue desarrollado por los Eley Brothers en 1903.
El .450 No 2 Nitro Express tiene un casquillo con anillo y diseño de cuello de botella para alojar proyectiles de 0,458 pulgadas (1,2 cm) y ser usado en fusiles doblesy de un solo cañón. La bala alcanza una velociad de salida de 2175 pies por segundo (662,9 m/s) .
La gran capacidad del casquillo, de 3.5 pulgadas (8,9 cm) de largo tiene una gran capacidad de carga de pólvora, y, en comparación con otros cartuchos Nitro Express similares, tiene un anillo y paredes del casquillo más gruesas, otorgándoles presiones bajas comparadas con otros Nitro Express que, cuando se combina con su borde grueso y sus paredes pesadas, hace que sea casi imposible que se atraque en la recámara.
Después de los primeros problemas de extracción experimentados con el .450 Nitro Express desarrollado por John Rigby &amp;amp; Company en 1898, Eley dio el paso inusual para el momento de crear su propio cartucho completamente nuevo y lanzarlo al mercado en 1903, permitiendo que todas las armerías que fabricaban rifles pudieran recamararlo, lo que era algo inusual por dos razones, la primera es que este cartucho no tiene un antepasado express de pólvora negra, la segunda es que fue diseñado por un fabricante de municiones, ya que la mayoría de los cartuchos de la época fueron diseñados por fabricantes de rifles. El .450 No 2 Nitro Express recibió ese nombre para diferenciarlo del original.  
Balísticamente, el .450 No 2 Nitro Express es casi idéntico al .450 Nitro Express original o al .500/450 Nitro Express diseñado por Holland &amp; Holland, el cual también fue creado para reemplazar al original. Sin embargo, los primeros problemas del .450 Nitro Express se resolvieron pronto y el .450 No 2 Nitro Express nunca fue tan popular como su predecesor.  
Después de la prohibición del ejército británico de 1907 de municiones de calibre .450 en India y Sudán, Eley desarrolló el .475 No. 2 Nitro Express ajustando el .450 No. 2 Nitro Express.  
El .450 No 2 Nitro Express es óptimo para la caza de animales peligrosos de pellejo grueso, como el elefante. En su African Rifles and Cartridges, John "Pondoro" Taylor afirma que la letalidad del .450 No 2 Nitro Express es tan eficaz como la de cualquier otro Nitro Express calibre .450-.476, pero no mejor. Taylor afirma además que hay un atractivo psicológico adjunto al .450 No 2 Nitro Express, el tamaño del enorme cartucho le da al cazador la confianza de que está llevando un arma más letal que la que lleva un cartucho similar.​ 
Pondoro Taylor tuvo cuatro rifles calibre .450 No 2 Nitro Express, con los que cazó cientos de elefantes, decenas de rinocerontes y cientos de búfalos. Otros notables cazadores que lo usaron extensivamente incluyen a Philip Percival, que cazaba con un par de rifles dobles boxlock .450 No 2 Nitro Express fabricados por Joseph Lang, y Nripendra Narayan, maharajá de Koch Bihar, que cazaba con una gran batería de rifles, la cual incluía el .450 Rifle doble No 2 Nitro Express de Manton &amp; Co.   
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> con nombre «CoochBehar» no se utiliza en el texto anterior.
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> con nombre «Henton» no se utiliza en el texto anterior.
Error en la cita: La etiqueta <ref> definida en las <references> con nombre «Taylor» no se utiliza en el texto anterior.


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.450_No_2_Nitro_Express)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>