<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .450/400 Nitro Express  is a Nitro Express rifle cartridge that is produced in three case lengths: 23⁄8-inches, 3 inches and 31⁄4-inches, and is intended for use in single shot and double rifles. The 3-inch and 31⁄4-inch versions are considered classic Nitro Express cartridges.
Both the .450/400 23⁄8-inch NE and .450/400 31⁄4-inch NE were created by loading the .450/400 Black Powder Express cartridges of both case lengths with smokeless cordite.
The .450/400 23⁄8 inch Nitro Express was loaded with a 400 gr. RN bullet with 42 or 43 grains of cordite and was meant for use in newer rifles chambered for the .450/400 23⁄8  inch case as this loading generates greater pressure than the Black Powder Express versions of the cartridge.
This cartridge is better known as the .400 Jeffery Nitro Express.
The .450/400 31⁄4-inch NE conversion was not initially entirely successful, under the increased pressures of the cordite loading the long neck could stick in the chamber causing the rim to pull off at extraction, a problem not encountered under the milder black powder loadings.  To counter this, the rim was increased in thickness to .042-inches.  W.J. Jeffery &amp; Co further improved the cartridge by reducing the length of the case to 3-inches and moving the neck further forward, creating the .450/400 3-inch NE.
Additionally, the caliber had to be standardised, slight variations existed in both the rifles and the  low-pressure black powder cartridges produced by different manufacturers, the bullet diameter is nominally given as .405 inches, bore as large as .411 existed, not a significant problem in black-powder rifles.  In Nitro Express loadings, an undersized bullet in an oversized bore may experience accuracy issues while an oversized bullet fired in an undersized bore may cause a catastrophic failure in the firearm.
The .450/400 31⁄4-inch Nitro Express fires a 400 gr. jacketed bullet ahead of a charge of 56 - 60 gr. of cordite at a velocity of 2,150 ft/s (660 m/s). This cartridge is considered unsafe to use for older rifles chambered for the black powder version of this cartridge due to higher pressures generated by this loading. .450/400 31⁄4-inch Nitro Express rifles are heavier and were considered as the minimum cartridge necessary when hunting dangerous game.
The .450/400 NE in both the 3-inch and 31⁄4-inch versions were extremely popular in Africa and India, prior to the introduction of the .375 Holland &amp; Holland they were considered the best all-round African hunting caliber.  Both cartridges were extremely popular in India with Maharajas and British sportsmen for hunting tiger.
In his African Rifles and Cartridges, John "Pondoro" Taylor stated the 3-inch and 31⁄4-inch .450/400 NE were adequate for all African game in almost all conditions when used by an experienced hunter.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.450/400_Nitro_Express)
</EN>
<ES>
 El .450/400 Nitro Express es un cartucho Nitro Express de rifle que está producido en dos longitudes de casquillo: 2⅜-pulgadas y 3¼-pulgadas, para ser usado en rifles rifles dobles y monotiro.
Tanto el .450/400 2⅜ pulgadas NE y .450/400 3¼ pulgadas NE fueron originalmente creados para cargar el .450/400 Black Powder Express con cordita.
Estuvo cargado con una bala de 400 granos y 42 o 43 granos de cordita generando mayores presiones que la versión de pólvora negra del cartucho, por lo que fue desarrollado para rifles más modernos.
Más conocido como el .400 Jeffery Nitro Express.
Despide una bala enchaquetada de 400 granos cargadas con 56 - 60 g de cordita, a una velocidad de 2,150 pies por segundo (660 m/s).Los rifles 450/400 NE 3¼pulgadas eran más pesados y el mínimo considerado para la caza de animales peligrosos.
El .450/400 NE, ambos, el de 3  pulgadas y las versiones de 3¼ pulgadas fueron muy populares en África e India, antes de la introducción del .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum.  Ambos cartuchos eran extremadamente populares en India entre Maharajás y cazadores británicos para cazar tigre.​
En su libro "African Rifles and Cartridges", John "Pondoro" Taylor declaró que ambos, el de 3-pulgadas y 3¼-pulgadas, eran adecuados para toda especie africana en casi todas las condiciones aplicables cuando son usadas por un cazador experimentado.​

 

(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.450/400_Nitro_Express)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>