<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
.450 Nitro Express also known as the .450 Nitro Express 31⁄4-inch is a rifle cartridge designed for hunting dangerous game such as elephant, rhino, cape buffalo, lion, and leopard. This cartridge is used almost exclusively in double rifles for hunting in the Tropics or hot climates in general and is associated with the Golden Age of African safaris and Indian shikars.
The .450 Nitro Express was the first Nitro Express cartridge, developed around 1898 by John Rigby. This cartridge was based on the then popular .450 Black Powder Express case with 70 grains (5 g) of Cordite and a 480-grain (31 g) jacketed bullet. Muzzle velocity is listed at 2,150 feet per second (655 m/s) with 4,909 ft⋅lbf (6,656 J) of muzzle energy. This straight case has a length of 3.25 in (83 mm) with a .624 in (15.8 mm) rim.
Early cartridges used the black powder case that was designed for around 22,000 psi and not the 34,000 psi that the Cordite load generated. Case extraction was difficult, especially in warmer climates such as Africa and India where the cartridge was primarily used. To remedy this problem, a reinforced case was produced and Kynoch made a reduced load to lower the case pressure.  Another problem lay in the sensitivity of Cordite, loads developed in the cool British climate performed differently in the tropical heat of Africa and India, resulting in excessive pressures.  The manufacturers responded by developing "tropical loads" with reduced propellant.
These initial problems led to Holland &amp; Holland developing the .500/450 Nitro Express and Eley Brothers developing the .450 No 2 Nitro Express, both of which offered very similar performance to the original .450 Nitro Express.  By the time these two cartridges appeared, the early issues with the .450 Nitro Express had been resolved, and it quickly became the most popular and widely used dangerous game hunting round.
Following the British Army 1907 ban of .450 caliber ammunition into India and the Sudan, instead of developing their own replacement Rigby adopted Joseph Lang's .470 Nitro Express as their standard double rifle cartridge. By the time the ban was lifted the .470 NE had largely supplanted the .450 NE as the industry's most popular elephant cartridge, and Mauser's Gewehr 98 bolt actioned rifles offered cheaper alternatives to the expensive double rifles required by the Nitro Express cartridges.
In 1914 and early 1915, German snipers were engaging British Army positions with impunity from behind steel plates that were impervious to .303 British ball ammunition. In an attempt to counter this threat, the British War Office purchased 62 large bore sporting rifles from British rifle makers, including 47 of .450 caliber rifles, which were issued to Regiments, some British officers also supplied their own.
On one notable occasion, Richard "Dickie" Cooper brought down three Albatros D.III fighters from Ernst Udet's squadron, Jagdstaffel 15, with his Holland &amp; Holland .450 Nitro Express big-game double rifle. Cooper is recorded as saying: "I aimed well ahead of the leader. He came down like a pheasant, as did the one that followed, and I had time to reload and fire again at the third before he passed over - he also crashed."
Prominent users of the  .450 Nitro Express include Agnes Herbert, Arthur H. Neumann, Major Chauncey H. Stigand and Denys Finch Hatton, the latter had a gunsmith rebarrel his .475 No 2 Nitro Express Lancaster double rifle into .450 Nitro Express as it was easier to find ammunition.


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.450_Nitro_Express)
</EN>
<ES>
.450 Nitro Express también sabido como el .450 Nitro Express 3 1⁄4- pulgadas, es un cartucho metálico diseñado para cazar animales peligrosos como el elefante, rinoceronte, búfalo de cabo, león, y leopardo. Se usa en rifles dobles para cazar en los Trópicos o climas cálidos en general y está asociado con la Época dorada de safaris africanos e indios shikars.
El .450 Nitro Express fue el primer Nitro Express, desarrollado alrededor 1898 por John Rigby. Estuvo basado en el caquillo del entonces popular .450 Black Powder Express con 70 granos (5 g) de Cordita que propulsaban una bala de 480 granos (31 g). La Velocidad de salida estaba listada en 2,150 pies por segundo (655 m/s) con 4,909 ft⋅lbf (6,656 ) de energía. Este casquillo recto tiene una longitud de 3.25 pulgadas (83 mm) con un diámetro de anillo de .0,624 plg (1,6 cm) en (15.8 mm).
Los primeros cartuchos utilizaron el casquillo para pólvora negra, diseñado para soportar una presión de alrededor de 22,000 psi y no de 34,000 psi que generaba la carga de Cordita. Es por eso que la extracción del casquillo se hacía difícil, especialmente en climas más tibios como en África e India tropical, donde el cartucho era principalmente utilizó. Para remediar este problema, se reforzó el casquillo y  Kynoch desarrolló una carga reducida para bajar la presión.  Otro problema pone en la sensibilidad de Cordita al clima Los fabricantes respondieron desarrollando cargas "tropicales" con menor cantidad de cordita.
Estos problemas iniciales resultaron en que Holland &amp; Holland desarrollara el .500/450 Nitro Express y Eley Brothers el .450 No. 2 Nitro Express, ambos ofrecido un rendimiento muy similar al .450 Nitro Express original.  Pero para cuando estos cartuchos fueron introducidos al mercado, los problemas con el .450 Nitro Express habían sido resueltos, y este se volvió el cartucho más popular y utilizado para cazar animales peligrosos.
Después de la prohibición de uso de munición calibre .450 por el ejército británico en India y el Sudán, Rigby adoptó el  .470 Nitro Express como su cartucho para rifle doble. Para cuando la prohibción se levantó, el .470 NE había suplantado al .450 NE.
Con proyectiles sólidos es considerado excelente para la caza de elefantes y rinocerontes, mientras que los proyectiles de punta suave y los semi suaves desarrollados por Westley Richards, son preferidos para la caza de búfalos y tiros frontales a leones. El cazador que pretenda cazar antílopes con el .450 Nitro Express, deberá siempre usar proyectiles de punta suave para estos fines.​ 
Usuarios prominentes del  .450 Nitro Express incluyen a Agnes Herbert, Arthur H. Neumann, Major Chauncey H. Stigand Y Denys Finch Hatton; este último hizo recañonar su .475 No 2 Nitro Express a .450 Nitro Express cuando fue más fácil conseguir la munición.


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.450_Nitro_Express)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>