<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .465 H&amp;H Magnum also known as .465 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum, is a modern big bore firearms cartridge introduced by Holland &amp; Holland in 2003 together with the .400 H&amp;H Magnum. The .465 H&amp;H Magnum is a .468 caliber, belted, rimless bottlenecked cartridge. The cartridge is a necked-up, shoulder-lowered tapered cartridge based on the .378 Weatherby Magnum case.
Holland &amp; Holland began receiving requests from potential customers for a cartridge that would provide more power than the .375 H&amp;H Magnum. Holland &amp; Holland director Russell Wilkins undertook the project which culminated in the .400 H&amp;H Magnum and the .465 H&amp;H Magnum cartridge designs. The original design requirements called for a muzzle energy of over 6,000 ft⋅lbf (8,100 J). To meet this requirement Holland &amp; Holland chose the .460 Weatherby Magnum case as a starting point in their design.
This .465 H&amp;H Magnum cartridge is not the same as the famous .500/465 Nitro Express also designed by Holland &amp; Holland for "India" double rifles. The .500/465 Nitro Express is the only other cartridge with the same bullet diameter as the .465 H&amp;H Magnum. Both cartridges are designed to fire a 480-grain (31 g) .468 caliber (11.89 mm) bullet. Although the cartridge is capable of operating at rather high pressures, Holland &amp; Holland chose to load the cartridge to a moderate pressure of around 47,000 psi (3,200 bar). The moderate pressure of the cartridge ensures reliability and safety in the tropical climes in which the cartridge was intended to be used.  Furthermore, the taper and shallow shoulder of the cartridge aids in the smooth, reliable feeding and extraction.
The .465 H&amp;H Magnum is an excellent cartridge for all-around game and African dangerous game including the Big 5. It has a similar trajectory to that of the .375 H&amp;H Magnum.
Ammunition for the .465 H&amp;H Magnum is being manufactured by Wolfgang Romey for Holland &amp; Holland.
Both .465 H&amp;H Belted Magnum cartridge and chamber specifications were standardized by CIP on 2006-09-19. 
The .465 H&amp;H Magnum is based on the .460 Weatherby Magnum case, itself based on the .378 Weatherby Magnum. The .378 Wea. Mag. was itself based on adding a belt to the .416 Rigby case &amp; giving it a Weatherby double radius shoulder. Holland &amp; Holland took the .460 Weatherby case and moved the shoulder back, creating a longer neck for the cartridge, and increased the body taper of the cartridge to improve feeding reliability. The case is also necked up to accept a .465 caliber (11.65 mm) bullet.
Rifles chambered for the .465 H&amp;H Magnum have a bore ∅ of 11.65 mm (0.459 in) and a groove ∅ of 11.87 mm (0.467 in). Twist rate for rifles can range from one revolution in 406 mm (16.0 in) to 711 mm (28.0 in). The maximum average pressure suggested for the cartridge is 4,300 bar (62,000 psi).


(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.465_H%26H_Magnum)
</EN>
<ES>
El .465 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum, abrevidado .465 H&amp;H Mag, es un cartucho moderno de gran calibre introducido por la firma inglesa Holland &amp; Holland en el año 2003, junto con el .400 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum. 
El diseño del .465 H&amp;H Magnum se basa en un proyectil de.468 pulgadas, cuyo casquillo deriva de una modificación del .378 Weatherby Magnum, al que se le amplió el diámetro del cuello y se le rebajó el hombro.
Holland &amp; Holland empezó recibir peticiones de clientes potenciales para desarrollar un cartucho que proporcionara una performance superior al .375 H&amp;H Magnum. 
Russell Wilkins, director de Holland &amp; Holland se encargó de conducir el proyecto que culminó en el diseño del .400 H&amp;H Magnum y del .465 H&amp;H Magnum, siendo el objetivo desarrollar un proyectil que generase una energía de 6,000 libra.pie (8,100 J) en la boca del cañón; para lograr esto, Holland &amp; Holland escogió el casquillo del .460 Weatherby Magnum como punto de partida en su diseño.​
Esto .465 H&amp;H Magnum no es similar al famoso 500/465 Nitro Express, también diseñado por Holland &amp; Holland décadas atrás para ser usado con rifles dobles en la India. Tanto el .500/465 Nitro Express como .465 H&amp;H Magnum están diseñados para despedir un proyectil de 480 granos (31 g)  calibre .468 (11.89 mm). 
Si bien el nuevo cartucho es capaz de ser cargado a presiones bastante altas, Holland &amp; Holland escogió cargar el cartucho a una presión moderada de alrededor 47,000 psi (3,200 bar). La presión moderada del cartucho asegura fiabilidad y seguridad en los climas tropicales donde el cartucho sería aprovechado.  Además, el diseño del casquillo está concebido para asegurar una alimentación lisa y una extracción fiable.​
El .465 H&amp;H Magnum es un cartucho excelente para la caza mayor de todo tipo de especies peligrosas africanas, incluyendo los cinco grandes. Su trayectoria es similar a la del .375 Holland &amp; Holland Magnum.​ 
La munición para el .465 H&amp;H Magnum está siendo fabricada por Wolfgang Romey para Holland &amp; Hollanda.
Tanto el cartucho como la recámara del .465 H&amp;H Belted Magnum fueron estandarizados por CIP el 19-9-2006.​​ 
El diseño del casquillo del .465 H&amp;H Magnum está basado en el .460 Weatherby Magnum, el que a su vez se basa en el casquillo del .378 Weatherby Magnum, el que a su vez se diseño usando el casquillo de .416 Rigby, al que Weatherby le incluyó un cinturón y le dio el característico doble radio de hombros. Holland &amp; Holland lando rebajó el hombro, aumentando el cuello y modificándole el diámetro para permitir alojar un proyectil calibre .465 (11.65 mm).
 

(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.465_H%26H_Magnum)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>