<loc>

<DE>N/A</DE>
<EN>
The .476 Nitro Express, also known as the .476 Westley Richards, is a British  rifle cartridge introduced by Westley Richards around 1907.
The .476 Nitro Express is one of several rounds (including the .500/465 Nitro Express, .470 Nitro Express, .475 Nitro Express, and .475 No. 2 Nitro Express) developed as a replacement for the .450 Nitro Express following the British Army 1907 ban of .450 caliber ammunition into India and the Sudan, all with comparable performance.
Westley Richards created the .476 Nitro Express by necking down the .500 Nitro Express 3".
Available in single-shot and double rifles, it was less popular than the above-mentioned rounds. It is nearly identical in performance to a number of others in the same class.
The .476 is considered adequate for all African and Indian big game, including elephant and rhinoceros. Its ballistics resemble the .458 Winchester Magnum, with a larger diameter bullet; whether this is an advantage remains in dispute.
Commercial rifles are no longer available in .476 Nitro Express except by special order, ammunition is no longer commercially available, and handloading data are scant, the factory load used 75 gr (4.86 g) of cordite under a 520 gr (33.7 g) slug.

This ammunition-related article is a stub. You can help Wikipedia by expanding it.

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.476_Nitro_Express)
</EN>
<ES>
El .476 Nitro Express, o .476 Westley Richards, ​ es un cartucho de rifle introducido por Westley Richards alrededor de 1907 en Gran Bretaña.
El .476 Nitro Express es una más de las alternativas desarrolladas para la caza mayor a inicios del siglo 20, debido a la prohibición del ejército británico al uso del calibre .450, en India y Sudán, en 1907. Estas vriantes incluyen al .500/465 Nitro Express, .470 Nitro Express, .475 Nitro Express y .475 No. 2 Nitro Express, todos con un rendimiento muy similar. ​
Westley Richards creó el .476 Nitro Express ajustando cuello del casquillo del .500 Nitro Express 3" . ​
Básicamente para ser usado en rifles dobles, el .476 NE fue menos popular que las otras variantes mencionadas anteriormente. 
Sin embargo, el .476 se considera adecuado para toda la caza mayor africana e india, ​ incluidos los elefantes y los rinocerontes . Su balística se parece al .458 Winchester Magnum, con una bala de mayor diámetro; si esto es una ventaja sigue en disputa. ​
Actualmente no se fabrican rifles recamarados para alojar al .476 Nitro Express excepto a pedido especial, las municiones ya no son disponibles comercialmente y los datos de carga manual son escasos, la carga de fábrica usó 75 gr (4,86 g) de cordita debajo de una bala de 520 gr (33,7 g) . ​


(https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/.476_Nitro_Express)
</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
<IT>N/A</IT>
</loc>