<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia oggi nota come 6mm Remington (N.B. nota in alcune fonti bibliografiche,seppur raramente, come 6x57 Remington o 6x56 Remington) non è altro che la risposta della Remington Arms Company al successo commerciale del famosissimo .243 Winchester (V. voce a se). Essa nacque, nel 1955, con il nome di .244 Remington, ma la sua diffusione ed il suo successo vennero immediatamente offuscati dal fenomenale successo commerciale del .243 Winchester (V. voce a se). A ciò dovette poi aggiungersi che i cacciatori americani desideravano poter impiegare palle del peso di 100 - 105grs. (6,4 - 6,8 GRAMMI), 
cosa che non era possibile con il .244 Remington, ma che era invece possibilissima con il neonato .243 Winchester. Per cercare di correre ai ripari, nel 1964 la Remington reintrodusse sul mercato il .244 Remington con la denominazione di 6mm Remington, nome con il quale questa cartuccia è nota ancora oggi. Allo stato attuale è dunque possibile imbattersi sia in armi che recano la scritta ".244 Remington", sia in armi che portano la scritta " 6mm Remington ". Nonostante le apparenze, si tratta della STESSA identica cartuccia, poichè l'unica differenza sta nel passo di rigatura !! Infatti, mentre "...il vecchio  .244 Remington..." impiegava un passo di  1 giro in 12", "...il nuovo 6mm Remington..." adotta un passo di 1 giro in 9".

(https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/fucili/6R.html)

La 6mm. Remington nasce nel 1963 per sostituire la .244 poco usata. La Remington corresse l'errore di progettazione della .244 introducendo la nuova cartuccia. Le armi camerate per la vecchia poterono cosi essere modificate con poca spesa per la nuova cameratura.
Entrambe le munizioni nacquero unicamente per la piccola caccia Americana, l'energia sviluppata è poco superiore a quella della .243 Win. In Europa l'interesse a questa cartuccia scaturisce solo per i cacciatori di camosci che però prediligono munizioni più commercializzate nel vecchio continente. 

(http://www.tiropratico.com/ammunition/pagine/6mm-remington.html)
</IT>
<EN>
The 6mm Remington rifle cartridge, originally introduced in 1955 by Remington Arms Company as the .244 Remington, is based on a necked down .257 Roberts cartridge (itself a necked-down 7×57mm Mauser) using a .24/6mm bullet. Known for a combination of high velocity, long range, flat trajectory, and accuracy, it is suitable as a dual use hunting cartridge for both medium-sized big game and varmints. When used in the less common earlier slow twist barrels, it offers exceptional range for varmint applications. While not as commercially popular today as the .243 Winchester, the 6mm Remington enjoys a slight ballistic advantage and continues to be popular with handloaders and custom rifle builders. 
By the early 1950s, there had been a significant amount of experimentation and 'wildcatting' in developing the .24 caliber bullet as a dual purpose hunting round. Popular cartridges necked down for this purpose included the .257 Roberts (based on the 7x57mm Mauser) and .308 Winchester. Fred Huntington of RCBS had developed what was known as the .243 Rock Chucker wildcat cartridge. This was a necked down .257 Roberts casing shooting a .24/6mm bullet. This ultimately became the .244 Remington. Mike Walker, who had previously designed the Remington Model 722, 'productized' Huntington’s wildcat cartridge and adapted the Model 722 chambering for it in 1955.
The existing Remington Model 722 was chambered for the new .244 Remington cartridge with a 1 in 12-inch twist. Remington originally offered this cartridge with 75 grain bullets for varmints and 90 grain bullets for medium-sized big game such as deer and antelope.
Remington determined that a 90 grain soft point .244 hunting bullet was well suited for medium-sized big game hunting purposes. For the length and weight of its 90 grain soft point hunting bullet, Remington selected a 1 in 12-inch twist. By selecting the slowest twist possible, Remington was seeking to avoid excessive spin. By avoiding excessive spin they were able to maximize velocity, range and accuracy of their 90 grain big game hunting bullet as well as lighter varmint loads.
Public perception and understanding of ballistics in the 1950s did not agree with this approach. By 1958, Remington was obliged to increase the 722s twist to 1 in 9 inches, well in excess of what is needed to stabilize a 90 grain bullet. Remington continued to offer factory ammo in 75 and 90 grain bullets.
Remington also added several other rifles chambered for the .244 cartridge including the Model 740, Model 742, Model 760 and finally the Model 725. However, by 1962, presumably due to lack of sales, Remington no longer chambered rifles for .244 cartridge.
In 1963, on the heels of its successful first year launch of the new Remington Model 700 bolt action hunting rifle, the .244 was re-introduced but renamed 6mm Remington. The 700 continued with the 1 in 9-inch twist and Remington also introduced new 6mm ammunition loaded with a 100 grain Cor-Lokt bullet. The new model could also shoot any .244 ammunition. Previous Remington 722 rifles made after 1957 with 1 in 9-inch twist could also shoot the newer 6mm 100 grain ammunition.
Remington labeled their new 100 grain bullet ammunition as "6mm" when introduced. However Remington continued to manufacture and label the 75 and 90 grain bullet ammunition as ".244" for a number of years. From the late 1960s until the early 1970s Remington transitioned to labeling all such ammunition regardless of bullet grain weight only as "6mm." 

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/6mm_Remington)
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
La munition 6 mm Remington (appellation anglo-saxonne : .244 Remington) est une cartouche de chasse convenant pour le chamois, le chevreuil et l'isard. Elle est fabriquée industriellement aux États-Unis par la société Remington Arms, mais est peu répandue en France. 
    Masse de la balle : 4,9 g, 5,2 g ou 6,5 g.
    Vitesse initiale : 945-1057 m/s
    Énergie initiale : 2636-2906 joules

(https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/6_mm_Remington)
</FR>
</loc>