<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro 7mm Remington Magnum è, secondo la ricostruzione storica più diffusa, un derivato parziale della cartuccia calibro .275 Belted Nitro Express (altresì noto come .275 Holland &amp; Holland), che venne commercializzato per la prima volta dalla Remington Arms Company nel 1962 (N.B. cioè 40 anni dopo la commercializzazione del .275 Holland &amp; Holland. Viceversa, secondo una diversa ricostruzione storica, il 7mm Remington Magnum deriverebbe da una cartuccia sperimentale americana (wildcat), il 7mm Mashburn Super Magnum, che non giunse mai ad avere una stabile diffusione commerciale. Infine, c'è chi ritiene il 7mm Remington Magnum un derivato del preesistente .264 Winchester Magnum (V. voce a se) con il colletto allargato fino a consentire l'introduzione di palle da 7mm di diametro. Quale che sia la verità, nel 1962, congiuntamente alla presentazione della nuova cartuccia venne commercializzata una nuova carabina da caccia, appartenente alla serie 700, che era stata appositamente migliorata ed adattata per il 7mm Remington Magnum. Così com'era successo 40 anni prima con il .275 Holland &amp; Holland , anche il 7mm Remington Magnum venne concepito come cartuccia da caccia per prede di medie dimensioni, in grado di essere impiegata con profitto fino a distanze di 300 - 400m. 
La sua elevata velocità alla bocca garantiva un'ottima resistenza alla deflessione impressa dal vento ed una traiettoria estremamente tesa anche sulle lunghe distanze. Si può dire, a ragion veduta, che i tecnici della Remington progettarono il 7mm Remington Magnum con in mente un ipotetico cacciatore americano impegnato in una battuta di caccia all'alce o al cervo, piuttosto che all'orso bruno o alla capra delle montagne. Dal punto di vista della lesività, il 7mm Remington Magnum ha un'energia cinetica tale da abbattere con sicurezza tutti i più grossi mammiferi europei ed americani, e può essere impiegata validamente contro tutti i mammiferi africani a pelle tenera.

(https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/fucili/7RM.html)
</IT>
<EN>
The 7mm Remington Magnum rifle cartridge was introduced as a commercially available round in 1962, along with the new Remington Model 700 bolt-action rifle. It is a member of the belted magnum family that is directly derived from the venerable .375 H&amp;H Magnum. The original purpose of the belted magnum concept taken from the .300 H&amp;H Magnum and .375 H&amp;H Magnum, was to provide precise headspace control, since the sloping shoulders, while easing cartridge extraction, were unsuitable for this purpose. Improved cartridge extraction reliability is desirable while hunting dangerous game, which would be of concern when needing a fast follow up shot. The 7mm Remington Magnum is based on the commercial .264 Winchester Magnum, .338 Winchester Magnum, and .458 Winchester Magnum, which were based on the same belted .300 H&amp;H Magnum and .375 H&amp;H Magnum cases, trimmed to nearly the same length as the .270 Weatherby Magnum.
On its introduction, the 7mm Remington Magnum substantially usurped the market share held by the .264 Winchester Magnum, which went into sharp decline in popularity and sales after 1962. Remington has offered Managed Recoil ammunition for achieving reduced recoil when shooting and for generating less meat damage when hunting smaller game. 

The 7mm Remington Magnum offers ballistics better than the .30-06 Springfield with all available bullet weights, one of the more popular loads being a 160 grain spitzer loaded to 3,000 ft/s (910 m/s). This is due both to the higher muzzle velocity of the magnum compared to the Springfield and that .284 diameter bullets tend to have better ballistic coefficients than .308 diameter bullets of comparable mass. Because of the smaller bullet diameter .284 diameter also have higher sectional density than .308 diameter bullets, and because of that better penetration in the target (it takes a 206 grain .308 diameter bullet to get the same sectional density as a 175 grain .284 bullet, an increased weight that requires 15-20% more muzzle energy to get the same muzzle velocity). The heaviest commercially loaded ammo available for the 7mm is 180 grains, while the .30-06 Springfield can be loaded with bullets up to 220 grains, but for a .308 caliber to equal the flat trajectory and penetration of a .284 diameter 180 grain bullet with a muzzle velocity of 2,860 ft/sec, as offered for the 7mm Remington Magnum, requires muzzle energy close to what the .300 Winchester Magnum can offer, i.e. well beyond what the .30-06 can deliver. 

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/7mm_Remington_Magnum)
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
La cartouche de fusil 7 mm Remington Magnum a été introduite dans le commerce en 1962 ainsi que le nouveau fusil Remington modèle 700. Il est de la famille des belted magnum dérivé directement de la vénérable .375 H&amp;H Magnum. Le 7 mm Remington Magnum est basé sur le .264 Winchester Magnum, .338 Winchester Magnum et le .458 Winchester Magnum qui reposaient sur la même douille .300H&amp;H et 375H&amp;H.
À son introduction, la 7 mm Remington Magnum dépassait sensiblement la part de marché détenue par le .264 Winchester Magnum, qui est entré en déclin en popularité et en ventes après 1962. La pression maximale est définie par la SAAMI à 4200 bars. 
Balistique indicative

    Masse de la balle : de 6,5 à 11,6 g (100 à 180 grains)

    Marque : RWS
    Type : KS, 10,5 g (162 gr)
        Vitesse initiale : 930 m/s
        Énergie initiale : 4549 J

    Marque : RWS
    Type : ID Classic, 11,5 g (177 gr)
        Vitesse initiale : 890 m/s
        Énergie initiale : 4559 J

    Marque : RWS
    Type : EVO, 10,3 g (159 gr)
        Vitesse initiale : 895 m/s
        Énergie initiale : 4125 J

    Marque : Sologne
    Type : GPA, 9,7 g (150 gr)
        Vitesse initiale : 320 m/s
        Énergie initiale : 495 J

La faible énergie de cette dernière s'explique par le fait qu'elle est subsonique. C'est ce type de munition qui, utilisé avec un silencieux, permet de faire moins de bruit. Mais pour cela, sa vitesse initiale doit être inférieure à la vitesse du son (343 m/s). En divisant sa vitesse par 3, son énergie est divisée par 9. 

(https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/7_mm_Remington_Magnum)
</FR>
</loc>