<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro 7x54mm (nota in talune fonti bibliografiche come 7mm finnico o 7x54mm finlandese) è un derivato diretto della cartuccia calibro 6,5x55mm (V. voce a se) ottenuto taglio del colletto e successivo allargamento del medesimo fino a fargli accogliere un proiettile del diametro nominale di 7mm (.284"). 
La nascita di questa cartucia va ricercata nel fatto che nel suo Paese di origine, cioè in Finlandia, il calibro 6,5x55 Mauser era considerato "...cartuccia da guerra..." negli anni immediatamente successivi alla fine del secondo conflitto mondiale. Questa situazione che rendeva IMPOSSIBILE utilizzare il 6,5x55 Mauser determinò la nascita di una nuova cartuccia. Allargando il colletto del 6,5x55 Mauser e riducendone la lunghezza di 1mm,  i limiti legali vennero birllantemente AGGIRATI ed il 7x54mm vide la luce in maniera alquanto semplice.

(https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/fucili/7x54.html)
</IT>
<EN>
The 7×54mm Finnish is a rifle cartridge which was designed by Lapua as a moose hunting cartridge. It was loaded by two factories, Sako and Lapua in Finland from about 1944 until 1974. It is a 6.5×55mm SE necked up to take a 7mm (.285) bullet. It may be loaded with modified 6.5×55mm SE dies drilled to fit 8mm neck diameter. It was usually loaded with a lightweight bullet.
Dimensions were measured from a cartridge loaded by Lapua and from (if two measurements) a case that had been shot with an modified Arisaka. Because caliber is a wildcat, those can vary greatly. Rim diameter of the 6.5×55mm is 0.480" (12.20 mm)
In 1948, the gunsmith M. Jean Fournier sold some hunting rifles based on the MAS-36 rifle and the 7.5×54mm cartridge Mod 1929. As the French public could not use military cartridges, it was made possible in this case by reducing the caliber to 7mm, keeping the rest the same.
Not to be confused with the 7×54mm Finnish, the naming is similar but the cartridges are not compatible. 

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/7%C3%9754mm_Finnish)
</EN>
<DE>N/A</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>N/A</FR>
</loc>