<loc>
<IT>
La cartuccia calibro 7x64 Brenneke (o più raramente come 7x64mm), venne realizzata da Wilhelm Brenneke durante la metà del primo conflitto mondiale. Diversamente da molte altre cartucce di quel periodo, il 7x64 NON deriva da NESSUNA cartuccia preesistente e (piuttosto curiosamente) nonostante fosse stata realizzata nel 1917 (o, secondo altre fonti, nel periodo tra il 1918 ed il 1919), essa non era stata destinata ad impiegi militari, bensì ad applicazioni eminentemente sportive o venatorie. Si tratta infatti di una delle più belle cartucce, per la caccia alla selvaggina europea, di tutti i tempi!! 
A oltre 90 anni dalla sua introduzione, il 7x64 è ancora enormemente popolare in Europa, tant'è vero che molte aziende produttrici di armi (principalmente italiane e tedesche) hanno in catalogo numerosi modelli camerati in questo illustre calibro. Chiaramente, non mancano le aziende che forniscono munizioni commerciali di qualità più o meno elevata, come RWS, Hirtenberger o Sako. Così come accade spesso per molte cartucce europee, anche il 7x64 ha "...un fratello gemello..." costruito su un bossolo di tipo orlato, il 7x65R, idoneo ad essere impiegato in fucili di tipo basculante. Le due cartucce sono molto simili tra di loro, con la sola DIFFERENZA che il 7x65R ha una INFERIORE pressione di esercizio, la quale si attesta sui 3800 bar (380 MPa). Per questo motivo, i dati di ricarica presentati in questa pagina per il 7x64 NON possono essere impiegati per il 7x65R: non incorrete nell'errore di usare gli stessi dati perchè le due cartucce appaiono simili tra loro!! Ricordatevi che "simile" NON  significa "identico", soprattutto in balistica interna.

(https://www.grurifrasca.net/oldsite/Sito/Ricarica/fucili/7x64.html)
</IT>
<EN>
The 7×64mm (also unofficially known as the 7×64mm Brenneke, though its designer's name was never officially added as a part of the cartridge name) is a rimless bottlenecked centerfire cartridge developed for hunting. As is customary in European cartridges, the 7 denotes the 7 mm bullet caliber and the 64 denotes the 64 mm (2.5 in) case length. The 7×64mm is a popular hunting cartridge in Central Europe due to its 11.95 mm (0.470 in) case head diameter and 84 mm (3.3 in) overall length allowing it to easily be chambered in the Mauser 98 bolt action rifle that was once standard German military issue. 
At the start of the 20th century the famous German gun and ammunition designer Wilhelm Brenneke (1865–1951) was experimenting with the engineering concept of lengthening and other dimensional changes regarding standard cartridge cases like the M/88 cartridge case, then used by the German military in their Mauser Gewehr 98 rifles, to obtain extra muzzle velocity.
In 1912, Brenneke designed the commercially rather unsuccessful 8×64mm S cartridge (again in production since 2001). It was intended as a ballistic upgrade option for the Mauser Gewehr 98 rifles that were standard issue in the German military. The German military chose, however, to stay with their 8×57mm IS rifle cartridge avoiding rechambering their service rifles for a cartridge that, due to its more favourable bore area to case volume ratio, would ballistically outperform the .30-06 Springfield cartridge of the United States Army. Brenneke’s engineering concept was to create new, very powerful (for the era) cartridges by enlarging exterior cartridge case dimensions like overall length and slightly larger case head diameter compared to the German 8×57mm IS military cartridge case, coupled with an increase in maximum pressure. The concept was essentially sound, and he persisted in the development of new cartridges along this line.
In 1917 Brenneke necked down his 8×64mm S design of 1912 to 7 mm calibre, introduced it as the 7×64mm, and achieved major commercial success. The 7×64mm offered 10-12% more muzzle velocity than the 7×57mm Mauser. This results in a flatter trajectory and better performance at longer range. In the years between World War I and World War II, the 7×64mm was often regarded by German hunters as a "miracle cartridge", and dozens of different factory loads were available on the German market. It was so highly regarded that the Nazi German Wehrmacht, during the 1930s, even considered replacing the 8×57mm IS in favour of the 7×64mm for their snipers. The Wehrmacht decided — just like the German Army had in 1912 — to stay with the 8×57mm IS cartridges for their Mauser Karabiner 98ks to keep logistics as simple as possible.
Besides the 7×64mm rifle cartridge, Brenneke also designed a rimmed version for break action rifles such as double rifles and combination rifles, as well as for single shot rifles in 1917. The rimmed 7×65mmR variant of the cartridge was also immediately a commercial success
In countries where military service cartridges are banned for civil ownership, the 7×64 Brenneke is a successful cartridge for hunting and marksmanship. 
The 7×64mm is one of the favoured rifle cartridges in Central Europe, and is offered as a chambering option in every major European hunting rifle manufacturer's product palette. The versatility of the 7×64mm for hunting all kinds of European game and the availability of numerous factory loads all attribute to the 7×64mm chambering's popularity. Loaded with short, light bullets, it can be used on small European game like fox and geese or medium game such as roe deer and chamois. Loaded with long, heavy bullets, it can be used on big European game like boar, red deer, moose and brown bear. The 7×64mm offers very good penetrating ability due to a fast twist rate that enables it to fire long, heavy bullets with a high sectional density. 
The 7×64mm's rimmed sister cartridge, the 7×65mmR, is also very popular in Central Europe for the same reasons as the 7×64mm. The legal banning of ex-military service cartridges like the .308 Winchester, 7×57mm Mauser, 8×57mm I, 8×57mm IS and the .30-06 Springfield in countries like France and Belgium also promoted acceptance and use of the 7×64mm and the 7×65mmR. 

(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/7%C3%9764mm)
<DE>
Die Patrone 7 × 64 mm (auch Kaliber 7 × 64) ist eine Büchsenmunition. Dabei steht die 7 für das Nennkaliber des Geschosses und die 64 für die Länge der Patronenhülse in mm. Die 7 × 64 wird überwiegend als Jagdmunition eingesetzt. 
Der Leipziger Wilhelm Brenneke entwickelte im Jahre 1917 die Patrone 7 × 64 mm sowie deren Randversion 7 × 65 mm R. Diese Patronen waren Brennekes Antwort auf die damals in den höchsten Tönen gelobte .280 Ross und die im Jahre 1906 vorgestellte Militärpatrone .30-06 Springfield.
Brenneke zog die damals mit mäßigem Erfolg von ihm entwickelte 8×64-mm-Patrone auf 7 mm ein und stellte die neue Patrone als 7 × 64 mm vor. Die 7 × 64 mm hatte im Vergleich zur 7 × 57 mm einen höheren Gebrauchsgasdruck. Daher fliegen die Geschosse etwa zehn Prozent schneller als bei der 7 × 57 mm und haben eine höhere Reichweite. Nicht selten wurde die 7 × 64 mm damals als „Wunderkaliber“ bezeichnet, da bereits in den 1930er-Jahren mehrere Dutzend verschiedener Laborierungen auf dem deutschen Markt verfügbar waren. 

Auch heute noch ist die 7 × 64 mm eine der am häufigsten geführten Büchsenpatronen im mitteleuropäischen Raum. Der Umstand, dass zivilgenutzte Militärpatronen wie die .308 Winchester, 7 × 57 mm oder die 7,92 × 57 mm in einigen europäischen Staaten verboten sind, förderte die Verbreitung der 7 × 64 mm sehr.
Die zahlreich angebotenen Laborierungen, die das Einsatzgebiet der 7 × 64 mm erweitern, sind auch heute noch ein Grund für die Anschaffung einer Waffe dieses Kalibers: Mit leichteren Geschossen wird Rehwild und Gams, mit schwereren Rot- und Schwarzwild gejagt. 

(https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/7_%C3%97_64_mm)
</DE>
<ES>N/A</ES>
<FR>
Le 7 × 64mm est un calibre de munition d'origine allemande, (également connu sous le nom de 7 × 64 mm Brenneke).
Le « 7 » correspond au diamètre de l'ogive et le « 64 » correspond à la longueur de l'étui, exprimés en millimètres. Ce calibre est très bien adapté pour le tir de chevreuil, chamois, sanglier, cerf. 

(https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/7_%C3%97_64_mm)
</FR>
</loc>